<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2013ARTO0403. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2013ARTO0403</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse porte sur l'établissement de similarités de données textuelles dans le domaine de la gestion de la relation client.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This Ph.D. thesis is about the establishment of textual data similarities in the client relation domain.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle se décline en deux parties : - l'analyse automatique de messages courts en réponse à des questionnaires de satisfaction ; - la recherche de produits à partir de l'énonciation de critères au sein d'une conversation écrite mettant en jeu un humain et un programme agent.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Two subjects are mainly considered : - the automatic analysis of short messages in response of satisfaction surveys ; - the search of products given same criteria expressed in natural language by a human through a conversation with a program.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La première partie a pour objectif la production d'informations statistiques structurées extraites des réponses aux questions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The first subject concerns the statistical information from the surveys answers.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les idées exprimées dans les réponses sont identifiées, organisées selon une taxonomie et quantifiées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The ideas recognized in the answers are identified, organized according to a taxonomy and quantified.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La seconde partie vise à transcrire les critères de recherche de produits en requêtes compréhensibles par un système de gestion de bases de données.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The second subject concerns the transcription of some criteria over products into queries to be interpreted by a database management system.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les critères étudiés vont de critères relativement simples comme la matière du produit jusqu'à des critères plus complexes comme le prix ou la couleur.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The number of criteria under consideration is wide, from simplest criteria like material or brand, until most complex criteria like color or price.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les deux parties se rejoignent sur la problématique d'établissement de similarités entre données textuelles par des techniques de TAL.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The two subjects meet on the problem of establishing textual data similarities thanks to NLP techniques.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les principales difficultés à surmonter sont liées aux caractéristiques des textes, rédigés en langage naturel, courts, et comportant fréquemment des fautes d'orthographe ou des négations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The main difficulties come from the fact that the texts to be processed, written in natural language, are short ones and with lots of spell checking errors and negations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'établissement de similarités sémantiques entre mots (synonymie, antonymie, etc) et l'établissement de relations syntaxiques entre syntagmes (conjonction, opposition, etc) sont également des problématiques abordées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Establishment of semantic similarities between words (synonymy, antonymy, ...) and syntactic relations between syntagms (conjunction, opposition, ...) are other issues considered in our work.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous étudions également dans cette thèse des méthodes de regroupements et de classification automatique de textes afin d'analyser les réponses aux questionnaires de satisfaction.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We also study in this Ph. D. thesis automatic clustering and classification methods in order to analyse answers to satisfaction surveys.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>