<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2016GREAL028. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2016GREAL028</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le principal enjeu de notre recherche est d'aboutir à un modèle intégratif fonctionnel pour l'analyse des verbes d'affect en français et en arabe.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The paramount stake of this research is to achieve an integrative functional model for the analysis of affective verbs in French and Arabic.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous avons choisi d'étudier quatre V_affect : deux verbes d'émotion (étonner et énerver en français et leurs équivalents [ʔadhaʃa], [ʕaɣḍaba] en arabe]) et deux verbes de sentiment (admirer et envier et leurs équivalents [ʔaʕʒaba] et [ħasada]) appartenant aux champs sémantiques de la surprise, la colère, l'admiration et la jalousie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>I have chosen four affective verbs: two verbs of emotion (to astonish and to rage in French and their equivalent in Arabic) and two verbs of sentiment (to admire and to envy in French and their equivalent [ʔadhaʃa], [ʔaɣḍaba] in Arabic) they belong to semantic dictions of Surprise, Anger, Admiration, and Jealousy.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Plus concrètement, l'analyse se situe :</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>More concretely, the analysis is shaped:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>– au niveau sémantique et syntaxique : les dimensions sémantiques véhiculées par les collocatifs verbaux comme étonner tellement, énerver prodigieusement, en français, et [ʔaʕʒaba ʔiʕʒāban kabīran] (admirer admiration grand), [ɣaḍaba ɣaḍabaan ʃadīdan] (énerver colère sévère), en arabe, sont systématiquement reliées à la syntaxe (les constructions grammaticales récurrentes) (Hoey, 2005).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>- On the semantic and syntactic level: the semantic dimensions carried by verbal collocations such as to extremely astonish, to rage prodigiously in French, and [ʔaʕʒaba ʔiʕʒāban kabīran] (admire admiration big) *, [ɣaḍaba ɣaḍabaan ʃadīdan] (to rage rage extreme), and in Arabic are systematically linked to syntax (the recurrent grammatical constructions) (Hoey 2005).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>– au niveau syntaxique et discursif : les emplois actifs, passifs, et pronominaux des V_affect sont étudiés dans la perspective des dynamiques informationnelles au sein de la phrase (Van Valin et LaPolla, 1997).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>- On the syntactic and discursive level: the usage of passive, active and reflexive forms of affective verbs are dealt with from the perspective of informational dynamics in the sentence (Van Valin et LaPolla 1997).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>D'un point de vue méthodologique, l'étude s'appuie sur une démarche quantitative et qualitative de la combinatoire verbale et privilégie la démarche contrastive.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>From a methodological point of view, the study is based on the quantitative and qualitative approach of the verbal combination and favours the contrastive one.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle est fondée sur le corpus journalistique français de la base de données EmoBase (projet Emolex 100 M de mots) et du corpus journalistique ArabiCorpus (137 M de mots).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It is founded on the French journalistic corpus of Emobase Database (Emolex project 100 M of words) and the journalistic corpus Arabicorpus) (137 M of words).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La thèse contribue ainsi à l'étude des valeurs sémantiques, du comportement syntaxique et discursif de la combinatoire des V_affect, en arabe et en français, ce qui permet de mieux structurer le champ lexical des affects par rapport à ce que proposent les études existantes en lexicologie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Furthermore, the thesis participates in the studies of semantic values, the syntactic and the discursive behavior of affective verbs'combinations, in Arabic and in French, which will enable to better structure the diction of emotions in relation to what is proposed by current studies in lexicography.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les principaux résultats de l'étude peuvent être appliqués en didactique des langues, en traductologie et en traitement automatisé du lexique des affects dans les deux langues comparées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The main results of the study can be applied in language teaching, translation, and automated processing of emotions'lexicon in the two compared languages.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>