<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for TAL-2016-57_1_ID=2-Danlos-TAL57-1. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2016-57_1_ID=2-Danlos-TAL57-1</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>VerbNet est une ressource lexicale pour les verbes anglais qui est largement utilisée en TAL du fait de sa bonne couverture lexicale et syntaxique et de son encodage systématique des rôles thématiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>VerbNet is a lexical resource for English verbs that has proven useful for NLP thanks to its high lexical and syntactic coverage and its systematic coding of thematic roles.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous présentons comment nous avons développé Verbenet à partir de VerbNet tout en utilisant au maximum les ressources lexicales existantes du français, et comment sont encodées les différentes alternances du français en mettant l'accent sur les différences avec l'anglais (l'existence de formes pronominales, par exemple).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We present how we have developed Verbenet from VerbNet while using as far as possible the available lexical resources for French, and how the various French alternations are coded, focusing on differences with English (existence of pronominal forms, for example).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cet article devrait permettre à un chercheur en TAL une utilisation simple et efficace de Verbenet pour une tâche comme l'annotation en rôles sémantiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This paper should allow an NLP researcher to use Verbenet in a simple and efficient way for a task such as semantic role labeling.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>