<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2009TOU20079. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2009TOU20079</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous proposons la prise en compte d'indices linguistiques et discursifs variés et faisant appel à des niveaux d'analyses différents.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The method we propose takes into account various linguistic and discursive cues calling on different levels of analysis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'obsolescence étant un phénomène non linguistique, notre hypothèse est qu'il faut considérer les indices linguistiques et discursifs en termes de combinaisons.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As obsolescence is a non-linguistic phenomenon, our hypothesis is that linguistic and discursive cues must be considered in terms of combinations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un système d'apprentissage automatique est ensuite mis en place afin de faire émerger les configurations d'indices pertinentes dans les segments obsolescents caractérisés par les experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A machine learning system is then implemented to bring out relevant cue configurations in the obsolescent segments characterized by the experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nos objectifs sont remplis : nous proposons une description fine de l'obsolescence dans notre corpus de textes encyclopédiques et ainsi qu'un prototype logiciel d'aide à la mise à jour des textes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Both our objectives have been achieved: we propose a detailed description of obsolescence in our corpus of encyclopaedic texts as well as a prototype aid to updating.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une double évaluation a été menée : par validation croisée sur le corpus d'apprentissage et par les experts sur un corpus de test.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A double evaluation was carried out: by cross validation on the corpus used for machine learning and by experts on a test corpus.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>