<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2019SACLC101. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2019SACLC101</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’évaluation de la gravité et la surveillance des maladies pulmonaires chroniques représentent deux challenges importants pour la prise en charge des patients et l’évaluation des traitements.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Disease staging and monitoring of chronic lung diseases are two major challenges for patient care and evaluation of new therapies.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La surveillance repose principalement sur les données fonctionnelles respiratoires mais l’évaluation morphologique reste un point essentiel pour le diagnostic et l’évaluation de sévérité.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Monitoring mainly relies on pulmonary function testing but morphological assessment is a key point for diagnosis and staging In the first part, we propose different models to score bronchial disease severity on computed tomography (CT) scan.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une approche simple par seuillage adaptatif et une méthode plus sophistiquée de radiomique sont évaluées Dans la seconde partie, nous évaluons une méthode d’apprentissage profond pour contourer automatiquement l’atteinte fibrosante de la sclérodermie en scanner.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A simple thresholding approach using adapted thresholds and a more sophisticated machine learning approach with radiomics are evaluated In the second part, we evaluate deep learning methods to segment lung fibrosis on chest CT scans in patients with systemic sclerosis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans la dernière partie, nous démontrons que l’étude de la déformation pulmonaire en IRM entre inspiration et expiration peut être utilisée pour repérer les régions pulmonaires en transformation fibreuse, moins déformables au cours de la respiration, et qu’en scanner, l’évaluation de la déformation entre des examens successifs de suivi peut diagnostiquer l’aggravation fibreuse chez les patients sclérodermiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We combine elastic registration to atlases of different thoracic morphology and deep learning to produce a model performing as well as radiologists In the last part of the thesis, we demonstrate that lung deformation assessment between inspiratory and expiratory magnetic resonance images can be used to depict fibrotic lung areas, which show less deformation during respiration and that CT assessment of lung deformation on serial CT scans can be used to diagnose lung fibrosis worsening</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>