<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2019SACLS116. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2019SACLS116</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les méthodologies classiques utilisées pour la détection de piétons</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This study deals with pedestrian detection in high-density crowds from a mono-camera system.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous considérons un système à plusieurs classifieurs (Multiple Classifier System, MCS), composé de deux ensembles différents, le premier basé sur les classifieurs SVM (SVM-ensemble) et le deuxième basé sur les CNN (CNN-ensemble), combinés dans le cadre de la Théorie des Fonctions de Croyance (TFC).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We cast the detection problem as a Multiple Classifier System (MCS), composed by two different ensembles of classifiers, the first one based on SVM (SVM-ensemble) and the second one based on CNN (CNN-ensemble), combined relying on the Belief Function Theory (BFT) to exploit their strengths for pixel-wise classification.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La TFC nous permet de prendre en compte une valeur d’imprécision supposée correspondre soit à une imprécision dans la procédure de calibration, soit à une imprécision spatiale.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>BFT allows us to take into account the imprecision in addition to the uncertainty value provided by each classifier, which we consider coming from possible errors in the calibration procedure and from pixel neighbor's heterogeneity in the image space.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cet algorithme s’appuie sur des mesures évidentielles déduites des fonctions de croyance.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, scarcity of labeled data for specific dense crowd contexts reflects in the impossibility to obtain robust training and validation sets.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour le second ensemble, pour exploiter les avancées de l’apprentissage profond, nous avons reformulé notre problème comme une tâche de segmentation en soft labels.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>By exploiting belief functions directly derived from the classifiers'combination, we propose an evidential Query-by-Committee (QBC) active learning algorithm to automatically select the most informative training samples.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une architecture entièrement convolutionelle a été conçue pour détecter les petits objets grâce à des convolutions dilatées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>On the other side, we explore deep learning techniques by casting the problem as a segmentation task with soft labels, with a fully convolutional network designed to recover small objects thanks to a tailored use of dilated convolutions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour conclure, nous montrons que la sortie du MCS peut être utile aussi pour le comptage de personnes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Finally, we show that the output map given by the MCS can be employed to perform people counting.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>