<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2011AVIG0188. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2011AVIG0188</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une deuxième difficulté qui handicape grandement les systèmes de dialogue est le fort taux d’erreur du système de reconnaissance vocale.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this work a framework to interface efficient probabilistic modeling for both the SLU and the DM modules is described and investigated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Certaines propositions récentes permettent de réduire la complexité du modèle.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Tractability is ensured by the use of an intermediate summary space.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un premier suivi de croyance (belief update) est réalisé dans l’espace maitre (en intégrant des observations probabilistes sous forme de listes nbest).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Also to reduce the development cost of SDS an approach based on clustering is proposed to automatically derive the master-summary mapping function.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les tests réels sur des utilisateurs humains montrent qu’un système optimisé par renforcement obtient cependant de meilleures performances sur le critère pour lequel il a été optimisé.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A implementation is presented in the Media corpus domain (touristic information and hotel booking) and tested with a simulated user.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>