<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2015GREAI053. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2015GREAI053</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le développement d'un environnement collaboratif est un processus complexe.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Development of collaborative environment is a complex process.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La complexité réside dans le fait que ce développement implique beaucoup de prise de décisions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The complexity lies in the fact that collaborative environment development involves a lot of decision making.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De multiples compromis doivent être faits pour répondre aux exigences actuelles et futures d'utilisateurs aux profils variés.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Several tradeoffs need to be made to satisfy current and future requirements from a potentially various set of user profiles.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La prise en compte de cette complexité pose des problèmes aux chercheurs, développeurs et utilisateurs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The handling of these complexities poses challenges for researcher, developers and companies.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les informations et données requises pour prendre des décisions adéquates de conception et évaluer rigoureusement ces décisions sont nombreuses, parfois indéterminées et en constante évolution.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The knowledge required to make suitable design decisions and to rigorously evaluate those design decisions is usually broad, complex, and evolving.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous en déduisons trois modèles : SyCoW (travail collaboratif synchrone), SyCoE (environnement collaboratif synchrone) et SyCoEE (évaluation environnement collaboratif synchrone).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The results generate three models: SyCoW (synchronous collaborative work), SyCoE (synchronous collaborative environment) and SyCoEE (synchronous collaborative environment evaluation).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans la partie II de cette thèse, nous proposons un processus pour la sélection / développement d'un environnement collaboratif, où nous démontrons comment les modèles SyCoW, SyCoE et SyCoEE structurent ce processus.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In Part-II of this thesis we proposed a process for selection/development of collaborative environment, where we demonstrate how SyCoW, SyCoE and SyCoEE support this process in different ways.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les résultats de l'évaluation ont confirmé la convivialité de MT-DT et fournissent des éléments de validation des choix que nous avons faits au cours du développement de MT-DT.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The results of evaluation confirmed the usability of MT-DT and provide arguments for our choices which we made during development of MT-DT.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>