<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en" srclang="EN" tgtlang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2024-11-15" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for MERSENNE-mersenne20. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>mersenne20</docid>
        <url_src>https://comptes-rendus.academie-sciences.fr/geoscience/articles/10.5802/crgeos.112/</url_src>
        <url_tgt>https://comptes-rendus.academie-sciences.fr/geoscience/articles/fr/10.5802/crgeos.112/</url_tgt>
        <author>Laurent Cormier , Louis Hennet , Gerald Lelong , Gabriel J. Cuello , Alexei Bytchkov</author>
        <title_en>Structure from glass to melt: a case study along the MgSiO$_{{3}}$–CaSiO$_{{3}}$ join using neutron and X-ray diffraction</title_en>
        <title_fr>Structure de l'état vitreux à l'état liquide : étude de cas sur le joint MgSiO3–CaSiO3 en utilisant la diffraction des neutrons et des rayons</title_fr>
        <volume>CRGEOS, 2022, Volume 352, Le verre, un matériau omniprésent</volume>
        <translator>Romain Dziegielinski</translator>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">EN</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">FR</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <prop type="paragraph">1</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Structure from glass to melt: a case study along the MgSiO$_{{3}}$–CaSiO$_{{3}}$ join using neutron and X-ray diffraction</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Structure de l'état vitreux à l'état liquide : étude de cas sur le joint MgSiO3–CaSiO3 en utilisant la diffraction des neutrons et des rayons</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Glass and melt structures are inherently complex and disordered with significant changes expected to occur with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les structure à l'état vitreux et à l'état liquide sont intrinsèquement complexes et désordonnées, et des changements significatifs devraient se produire avec la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the present paper, a comparison of the structure of glasses and liquids along the MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join is carried out using neutron and X-ray diffraction (XRD).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans le présent article, une comparaison de la structure des verres et des liquides le long de la jonction MgSiO3-CaSiO3 est effectuée à l'aide de la diffraction des neutrons et des rayons X (XRD).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Empirical Potential Structure Refinement (EPSR) simulations were used to fit the experimental data.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des simulations EPSR (Empirical Potential Structure Refinement) ont été utilisées pour ajuster les données expérimentales.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average coordination number (CN) and site distribution is obtained for Mg and Ca showing distinct sites between the two cations and higher coordinated sites in the liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le nombre moyen de coordination (CN) et la distribution des sites sont obtenus pour Mg et Ca, montrant des sites distincts entre les deux cations et des sites mieux coordonnés dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The major glass to melt modifications is observed at the scale of intermediate range order (IRO) by rearrangement of the (Ca,Mg)–Si and (Ca,Mg)–(Ca,Mg) connections.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les principales modifications du verre à la fusion sont observées à l'échelle de l'ordre intermédiaire (IRO) par réarrangement des connexions (Ca,Mg)-Si et (Ca,Mg)-(Ca,Mg).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The structural evolution with temperature, especially concerning the cationic environments, illustrates the differences between glass and melt organization.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'évolution de la structure en fonction de la température, en particulier en ce qui concerne les environnements cationiques, illustre les différences entre l'organisation du verre et celle de la matière fondue.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These changes highlight the important contribution of cations to thermodynamical properties, diffusion and glass forming ability.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces changements soulignent la contribution importante des cations aux propriétés thermodynamiques, à la diffusion et à la capacité de formation du verre.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Supplementary Materials:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Compléments :</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Supplementary material for this article is supplied as a separate file:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des compléments sont fournis pour cet article dans le fichier séparé :</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>crgeos-112-suppl.pdf</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>crgeos-112-suppl.pdf</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <prop type="paragraph">3</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>1. Introduction</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>1. Introduction</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The structure of silicate melts is of considerable importance in igneous processes and in industrial applications (furnace conditions) as the atomic-scale organization strongly affects their dynamical and physico-chemical properties (for instance, density, entropy, crystal-melt element partitioning and transport properties including viscosity and diffusivity).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La structure des liquides silicatés est d'une importance considérable dans les processus ignés et dans les applications industrielles (conditions des fours) car l'organisation à l'échelle atomique affecte fortement leurs propriétés dynamiques et physico-chimiques (par exemple, la densité, l'entropie, la répartition des éléments entre les phases cristallines et fondues, les propriétés de transport, y compris la viscosité et la diffusivité).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="14">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Glasses have long been acknowledged as good analogues of liquids with a structure that can be easily revealed experimentally.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les verres sont depuis longtemps reconnus comme de bons analogues des liquides dont la structure peut être facilement révélée expérimentalement.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="15">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>On the contrary, measurements at elevated temperatures can be challenging and can give less detailed structural information.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Au contraire, les mesures à des températures élevées peuvent être difficiles et peuvent donner des informations structurales moins détaillées.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="16">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, important changes in properties occur above the glass transition temperature, T_(g), such as an increase in heat capacity and thermal expansivity, a decrease in viscosity, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, des changements importants de propriétés se produisent au-dessus de la température de transition vitreuse, T_(g), tels qu'une augmentation de la capacité thermique et de la dilatation thermique, une diminution de la viscosité, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="17">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These observations imply that the glass structure reflects only the supercooled liquid structure frozen in at T_(g) with, additionally, a strong dependence due to the thermal history, i.e. typically the quenching rate [Allwardt and Stebbins 2004, Henderson etal. 2006].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces observations impliquent que la structure du verre ne reflète que la structure du liquide surfondue figée à T_(g) avec, en plus, une forte dépendance due à l'histoire thermique, c'est-à-dire typiquement la vitesse de trempe [Allwardt et Stebbins 2004, Henderson etal. 2006].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="18">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Therefore, glasses may show significant structural differences compared to high-temperature liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Par conséquent, les verres peuvent présenter des différences structurales significatives par rapport aux liquides à haute température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="19">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To understand how data obtained on glasses can be extrapolated to melts, it is pertinent to track how the structure evolves with temperature, how fast the structural changes happen and how they can affect bulk properties [Stebbins 2008].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour comprendre comment les données obtenues sur les verres peuvent être extrapolées aux produits fondus, il est pertinent de suivre l'évolution de la structure en fonction de la température, la rapidité avec laquelle les changements structuraux se produisent et la manière dont ils peuvent affecter les propriétés générales [Stebbins 2008].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="20">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Liquids and glasses are both characterized by a lack of long range order.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les liquides et les verres sont tous deux caractérisés par un manque d'ordre à grande échelle.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="21">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Unlike crystals for which a unique, accurate structural model can be established, the glass/melt structure is described statistically, by considering average information on the structure extending over short and intermediate range scale, referred to as SRO (short range order) and IRO.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Contrairement aux cristaux pour lesquels un modèle structural unique et précis peut être établi, la structure du verre/liquide est décrite statistiquement, en considérant des informations moyennes sur la structure s'étendant sur des échelles de portée courte et intermédiaire, appelée SRO et IRO (respectivement short range order et intermediate range order).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="22">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Among the many experimental tools allowing the elucidation of the complexity of silicate glasses/melts, X-ray and neutron diffraction offer the possibility to probe both SRO and IRO [Cormier 2019, Cormier etal. 2001, Wilding and Benmore 2006] and benefits from the availability of high-temperature devices [Cuello etal. 2014, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Parmi les nombreux outils expérimentaux permettant d'élucider la complexité des verres/liquides silicatés, la diffraction des rayons X et des neutrons offre la possibilité de sonder à la fois les SRO et les IRO [Cormier 2019, Cormier etal. 2001, Wilding et Benmore 2006] et bénéficie de la disponibilité d'appareils opérationnels à haute température [Cuello etal. 2014, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="23">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Diffraction gives access to a pair distribution function (PDF) in real space that is the probability of finding an atom at a distance r from an atom taken at the origin.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La diffraction donne accès à une fonction de distribution de paires (PDF, pair distribution function) dans l'espace réel qui représente la probabilité de trouver un atome à une distance r d'un atome pris à l'origine.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="24">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In addition to experimental data, a structural description provided by modelling approaches is usually required to reveal many structural aspects.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En plus des données expérimentales, une description structurale fournie par des approches de modélisation est généralement nécessaire pour révéler de nombreux aspects structuraux.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="25">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This can be readily obtained from diffraction data using methods such as reverse Monte Carlo (RMC) or Empirical Potential Structure Refinement (EPSR) [Majérus etal. 2004, Nienhuis etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci peut être facilement obtenu à partir de données de diffraction en utilisant des méthodes telles que le Monte Carlo inverse (RMC, reverse Monte Carlo) ou l'affinement structural avec potentiel empirique (EPSR, Empirical Potential Structure Refinement) [Majérus etal. 2004, Nienhuis etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="26">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Comparatively to glasses, structural data for liquids are lacking, which preclude an evaluation of the glass/melt comparison and do not offer experimental validation for developing new, more accurate potentials in molecular dynamics (MD) simulations [Shih etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Comparativement aux verres, les données structurales pour les liquides font défaut, ce qui exclut une évaluation de la comparaison verre/liquide et n'offre pas de validation expérimentale pour développer de nouveaux potentiels plus précis dans les simulations de dynamique moléculaire (DM) [Shih etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="27">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ (CMS) join is a simple system with two non-network forming cations (Mg, Ca), and having a complete glass formation region between the two end members, MgSiO₃ and CaSiO₃.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le joint MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ (CMS) est un système simple avec deux cations non-formateurs de réseaux (Mg, Ca), et ayant une région vitrifiable complète entre les deux membres terminaux, MgSiO₃ et CaSiO₃.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="28">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It contains three minerals of interest to the geochemistry of upper mantle, enstatite (MgSiO₃), diopside (CaMgSi₂O₆) and wollastonite (CaSiO₃).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il contient trois minéraux d'intérêt pour la géochimie du manteau supérieur, l'enstatite (MgSiO₃), le diopside (CaMgSi₂O₆) et la wollastonite (CaSiO₃).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="29">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Enstatite and diopside are pyroxene minerals [Thompson and Downs 2004, 2003].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'enstatite et le diopside sont des minéraux pyroxéniques [Thompson et Downs 2004, 2003].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="30">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Their structure consists of single-chains of corner-sharing SiO₄ tetrahedra.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Leur structure est constituée de chaînes simples de tétraèdres SiO₄ à sommets partagés.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="31">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These chains are connected by their apices to regular octahedral M1 sites that form a chain of edge-shared octahedra.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces chaînes sont reliées par leurs sommets à des sites M1 octaédriques réguliers qui forment une chaîne d'octaèdres à arêtes partagés.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="32">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Parallel to the M1 chains, there is a second octahedral chain with M2 sites that are larger and more distorted than M1 sites enabling the introduction of large cations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Parallèlement aux chaînes M1, il existe une deuxième chaîne octaédrique avec des sites M2 plus grands et plus déformés que les sites M1 permettant l'introduction de grands cations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="33">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In diopside, Ca atoms fill the large M2 sites while Mg atoms fill the regular M1 sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans le diopside, les atomes de Ca occupent les grands sites M2 tandis que les atomes de Mg occupent les sites M1 standards.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="34">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Due to its size, Ca atoms cannot be accommodated in M1 sites so that CaSiO₃ has a slightly different structure and is referred as a pyroxenoid.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En raison de leur taille, les atomes de Ca ne peuvent pas être accueilli dans les sites M1, de sorte que CaSiO₃ a une structure légèrement différente et est appelé un pyroxénoïde.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="35">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In wollastonite [Hesse 1984, Trojer 1968], the tetrahedral chain periodicity is modified (3 repeat SiO₄ rather than 2 repeat SiO₄ for pyroxenes) to allow Ca entering M1-type sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans la wollastonite [Hesse 1984, Trojer 1968], la périodicité de la chaîne tétraédrique est modifiée (3 répétitions de SiO₄ au lieu de 2 répétitions de SiO₄ pour les pyroxènes) pour permettre au Ca d'accéder aux sites de type M1.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="36">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This results in a lower crystal symmetry.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il en résulte une symétrie cristalline plus faible.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="37">
            <prop type="paragraph">7</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>^(∗)Number of non-bridging oxygen (NBO) per SiO₄ tetrahedra (Q), calculated with the formula NBO∕Q =(2O–4Q)/Q.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>^(*)Nombre d'oxygène non-pontant (ONP) par tétraèdre de SiO₄ (Q), calculé avec la formule ONP∕Q =(2O–4Q)/Q.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="38">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Ca–Mg mixing in glasses/melts adds complexity to the structure with possible evolution with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le mélange Ca–Mg dans les verres/liquides ajoute de la complexité à la structure avec une évolution possible en fonction de la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="39">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As the cations have the same nominal electric charge but different cationic size (r_(Mg²⁺) = 0.71Å, r_(Ca²⁺) = 1.14Å [Shannon 1976]), distinct site preferences are expected and local coordination change or local site distortion could arise with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Comme les cations ont la même charge électronique nominale mais une taille cationique différente (r_(Mg²⁺) = 0.71Å, r_(Ca²⁺) = 1.14Å [Shannon 1976]), on s'attend à des préférences de site distinctes et un changement de coordinence locale ou une distorsion locale du site pourrait survenir avec la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="40">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Ca–Mg mixing along the MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join yields a non-linear variation of the viscosity, with a lower viscosity (at a given temperature) for the diopside composition compared to either end members and a minima that is enhanced near T_(g) [Neuville and Richet 1991].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le mélange Ca–Mg le long du joint MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ produit une variation non linéaire de la viscosité, avec pour la composition de diopside une viscosité plus faible (à une température donnée) par rapport aux deux membres terminaux et un minimum qui est augmenté près de T_(g) [Neuville et Richet 1991].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="41">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The authors have shown that this behavior can be interpreted by an excess in configurational entropy for the liquids implying ideal cation mixing behavior.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les auteurs ont montré que ce comportement peut être interprété par un excès d'entropie de configuration pour les liquides impliquant un comportement idéal de mélange de cations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="42">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Much of the excess entropy is retained in intermediate compositions at T_(g).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une grande partie de l'entropie excédentaire est conservée dans des compositions intermédiaires à T_(g).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="43">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Structural analysis of CMS glasses support random cation mixing as these compounds are described with a disordered distribution of Ca and Mg cations [Allwardt and Stebbins 2004, Cormier etal. 2010].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'analyse structurale des verres CMS soutient le mélange aléatoire des cations car ces composés sont décrits avec une distribution désordonnée des cations Ca et Mg [Allwardt et Stebbins 2004, Cormier etal. 2010].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="44">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Though glasses in this system have been widely investigated [Cormier and Cuello 2012, 2011, De Sousa Meneses etal. 2006, Gaskell etal. 1991, Kalampounias etal. 2009, Kohara etal. 2011, Kroeker and Stebbins 2000, Schneider etal. 2003, Shimoda etal. 2008, 2007, Taniguchi etal. 1997, 1995, Wilding etal. 2004, Yin etal. 1983, Zhang etal. 1997], experimental studies in the liquid state are limited to MgSiO₃ [Wilding etal. 2010, 2008] and CaSiO₃ [Benmore etal. 2020, 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Bien que les verres dans ce système aient été largement étudiées [Cormier et Cuello 2012, 2011, De Sousa Meneses etal. 2006, Gaskell etal. 1991, Kalampounias etal. 2009, Kohara etal. 2011, Kroeker and Stebbins 2000, Schneider etal. 2003, Shimoda etal. 2008, 2007, Taniguchi etal. 1997, 1995, Wilding etal. 2004, Yin etal. 1983, Zhang etal. 1997], les études expérimentales à l'état liquide sont limitées au MgSiO₃ [Wilding etal. 2010, 2008] et CaSiO₃ [Benmore etal. 2020, 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="45">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It would thus be valuable to have further investigation of the molten structure of intermediate compositions, including the important diopside composition, for which entropic and structural effects are maximized.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il serait donc intéressant de poursuivre l'étude de la structure de la phase fondue des compositions intermédiaires, y compris la composition importante du diopside, pour laquelle les effets entropiques et structuraux sont maximisés.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="46">
            <prop type="paragraph">9</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this paper, we aim to explore the structural evolution along the MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join using neutron diffraction (ND) and X-ray diffraction (XRD) at high temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans cet article, nous avons pour objectif d'explorer l'évolution structurale le long du joint MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ en utilisant la diffraction des neutrons (DN) et la diffraction des rayons X (DRX) à haute température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="47">
            <prop type="paragraph">9</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The experimental data have been fitted using the EPSR approach to reveal structural differences between glasses and melts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les données expérimentales ont été ajustées en utilisant l'approche EPSR pour révéler les différences structurales entre les verres et les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="48">
            <prop type="paragraph">10</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>2. Experimental</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>2. Expérimental</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="49">
            <prop type="paragraph">11</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>2.1. Sample preparation</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>2.1. Préparation d'échantillon</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="50">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Glasses along the Ca–Mg pyroxene join (Ca_(x)Mg_(1−1x)Si₂O₆, where x = 0, 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, and 1) were prepared from powders of SiO₂, CaCO₃ and MgO in high purity commercial forms.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des verres le long du joint pyroxène Ca–Mg (Ca_(x)Mg_(1−1x)Si₂O₆ où x = 0, 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, et 1) ont été préparés à partir de poudres de SiO₂, CaCO₃ et MgO sous des formes commerciales très pures.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="51">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The decomposition of the carbonates was obtained by heating at 800°C overnight.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La décomposition des carbonates a été obtenue par chauffage à 800°C pendant une nuit.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="52">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The mixtures were subsequently melted, at 100°C above their respective melting temperatures, during 1h in a Pt-10%Rh crucible.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les mélanges ont ensuite été fondus, à 100°C au-dessus de leurs températures de fusion respectives, pendant 1h dans un creuset Pt-10%Rh.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="53">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The glasses were obtained by quenching the melts, dipping the bottom of the crucibles in water.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les verres ont été obtenus par trempe des verres ramollis, en plongeant le fond des creusets dans l'eau.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="54">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The samples were crushed in an agate mortar and remelted two times to improve the glass chemical homogeneity.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les échantillons ont été broyés dans un mortier d'agate et refondus deux fois pour améliorer l'homogénéité chimique du verre.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="55">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Glasses are labeled CMSx.y where x =mol% CaO, y =mol% MgO and (100 − x − y) =mol% SiO₂.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les verres sont notés CMSx.y où x =%mol CaO, y =%mol MgO et (100 − x − y) =%mol SiO₂.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="56">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pieces of each glass were embedded in epoxy resin, polished, carbon-coated and chemically analyzed using an electron probe micro-analyzer (CAMECA SX50) at the Camparis Centre (Sorbonne Université, France), as reported previously [Cormier and Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des morceaux de chaque verre ont été intégrés dans une résine époxy, polis, recouverts de carbone et analysés chimiquement à l'aide d'un micro-analyseur à sonde électronique (CAMECA SX50) au Centre Camparis (Sorbonne Université, France), comme indiqué précédemment [Cormier et Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="57">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The chemical compositions (Table1) are obtained by averaging ten different points.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les compositions chimiques (tableau1) sont obtenues en faisant la moyenne de dix points différents.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="58">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Glass densities were measured at room temperature by the Archimedes method with toluene as immersion liquid.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les densités de verre ont été mesurées à température ambiante en utilisant la poussée d'Archimède avec du toluène comme liquide d'immersion.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="59">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Melt densities were obtained or extrapolated from experimental data [Courtial and Dingwell 1999, 1995].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les densités des verres fondus ont été obtenues ou extrapolées à partir de données expérimentales [Courtial et Dingwell 1999, 1995].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="60">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Table1 gives the densities and the experimental temperatures used in diffraction measurements.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le tableau1 indique les densités et les températures expérimentales utilisées dans les mesures de diffraction.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="61">
            <prop type="paragraph">14</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>2.2. X-ray diffraction</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>2.2. Diffraction des rayons X</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="62">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>High energy XRD measurements were carried out at the beamline ID11 at the European Synchrotron Radiation Facility (ESRF) using an aerodynamic levitation and laser heating device [Drewitt etal. 2011, Hennet etal. 2011].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des mesures DRX à haute énergie ont été effectuées sur la ligne de faisceau ID11 à l'installation européenne de rayonnement synchrotron (ESRF) à l'aide d'un dispositif de lévitation aérodynamique et de chauffage laser [Drewitt etal. 2011, Hennet etal. 2011].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="63">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The synchrotron X-ray beam, 100 × 100μm² in cross-sectional area and 100.456keV in energy, was incident on the spherical liquid droplets that are levitating above the nozzle of the levitator using an argon gas flow through an aluminum conical nozzle.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le faisceau synchrotron de rayons X, d'une section transversale de 100 × 100 μm² et d'une énergie de 100.456 keV, a été incident sur les gouttelettes liquides sphérique qui sont en lévitation au-dessus de la buse d'un lévitateur à l'aide d'un flux de gaz argon à travers une buse conique en aluminium.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="64">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Two 125 W CO₂ laser beams were used for heating, with temperatures measured at 1973K (CMS00.50, CMS38.12, CMS50.00) or 1773K (CMS12.38, CMS25.25).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Deux faisceaux laser CO₂ de 125 W ont été utilisés pour la chauffe, avec des températures mesurées à 1973K (CMS00.50, CMS38.12, CMS50.00) ou 1773K (CMS12.38, CMS25.25).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="65">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Two-dimensional diffraction patterns were recorded with ESRF-designed FReLoN CCD camera [Labiche etal. 2007].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des diagrammes de diffraction bidimensionnels ont été enregistrés avec une caméra CCD FReLoN conçue par l'ESRF [Labiche etal. 2007].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="66">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The scattered beam was positioned at the corner of the detector which allows a wide total scattering momentum (Q) range extending to Q_(max) = 23.6Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le faisceau diffusé a été positionné à l'angle du détecteur, ce qui permet une large gamme de vecteurs de diffusion total (Q) s'étendant jusqu'à Q_(max) = 23.6Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="67">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The sample-to-detector distances, beam center and detector tilt were determined by comparison between the known d-spacings of a Si calibrant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les distances échantillon-détecteur, le centre du faisceau et l'inclinaison du détecteur ont été déterminés par comparaison entre les distances-d connus d'un calibrant Si.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="68">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The diffraction data were flat-fielded and corrected for dark current noise, geometrical effects and incident beam polarization and reduced to one-dimensional patterns using FIT2D software.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les données de diffraction ont d'abord subi une correction de champ plat (flat-field) puis ont été corrigées pour tenir compte du bruit du courant de signaux 'noirs', des effets géométriques et de la polarisation du faisceau incident et réduites à des figures unidimensionnelles à l'aide du logiciel FIT2D.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="69">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The measured diffracted intensities were scaled to fit the sum of the Compton and self-scattering, which was then subtracted to obtain the total structure factor F^(X)(Q), using standard procedure [Drewitt etal. 2013, 2011].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les intensités diffractées mesurées ont été mises à l'échelle pour correspondre à la somme de l'effet Compton et de l'autodiffusion, qui a ensuite été soustraite pour obtenir le facteur de structure total F^(X)(Q), en utilisant une procédure standard [Drewitt etal. 2013, 2011].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="70">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>2.3. Neutron diffraction</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>2.3. Diffraction des neutrons</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="71">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The ND measurements were carried out on the D4C diffractometer at the Institut Laue-Langevin, using an aerodynamic levitation and laser heating device [Hennet etal. 2006].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les mesures de DN ont été réalisées sur le diffractomètre D4C de l'Institut Laue-Langevin, à l'aide d'un dispositif de lévitation aérodynamique et de chauffage laser [Hennet etal. 2006].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="72">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Acquisitions at high temperature were obtained on the liquid samples and the empty levitation device inside the diffraction chamber.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces acquisitions à haute température ont été obtenues sur les échantillons liquides et le dispositif de lévitation vide à l'intérieur de la chambre de diffraction.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="73">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A vanadium standard was also measured at room temperature for absolute normalization of the scattering intensity.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un étalon au vanadium a également été mesuré à température ambiante pour la normalisation absolue de l'intensité de diffusion.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="74">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The neutron wavelength was 0.4979Å⁻¹, giving a useable Q-range up to Q_(max) = 23.6Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La longueur d'onde des neutrons est de 0.4979Å⁻¹, ce qui produit une gamme de Q utilisable jusqu'à Q_(max) = 23.6Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="75">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The program CORRECT was used to process the data corrections for attenuation, background, multiple scattering and inelasticity effects [Howe etal. 1996], giving the neutron total structure factor, F^(N)(Q).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le programme CORRECT a été utilisé pour corriger les données des effets d'atténuation, de bruit de fond, de diffusion multiple et d'inélasticité [Howe etal. 1996], donnant le facteur de structure totale des neutrons, F^(N)(Q).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="76">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The ambient ND data are those previously published, also acquired on the D4C diffractometer [Cormier etal. 2010], except the CMS25.25 glass that has been measured during this experiment.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les données DN ambiantes sont celles précédemment publiées, également acquises sur le diffractomètre D4C [Cormier etal. 2010], à l'exception du verre CMS25.25 qui a été mesuré au cours de cette expérience.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="77">
            <prop type="paragraph">18</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>3. Empirical potential structure refinement</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>3. Affinement structural avec potentiel empirique</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="78">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Structural models for the glasses and the liquids were derived from the diffraction data using EPSR [Soper 2005].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les modèles structuraux pour les verres et des liquides ont été dérivés des données de diffraction en utilisant l'EPSR [Soper 2005].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="79">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This method refines atomic positions within a box model and interatomic potentials between atomic pairs to progressively get an agreement between the simulated and measured diffraction data.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette méthode affine les positions atomiques dans un modèle de boîte et les potentiels interatomiques entre les paires atomiques pour obtenir progressivement une adéquation entre les données de diffraction simulées et mesurées.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="80">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The fitting procedure was performed simultaneously on the neutron and X-ray data for all glasses, while for the liquids only X-ray data were available for CMS12.38 and CMS38.12.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La procédure d'ajustement a été effectuée simultanément sur les données de diffraction des neutrons et des rayons X pour tous les verres, tandis que pour les liquides, seules les données de rayons X étaient disponibles pour CMS12.38 et CMS38.12.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="81">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The potential parameters used for EPSR modelling were determined as previously reported [Weigel etal. 2008] and are given in Table2.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les paramètres des potentiels utilisés pour la modélisation de l'EPSR ont été déterminés comme indiqué précédemment [Weigel etal. 2008] et figurent dans le tableau2.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="82">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The atomic cubic box specifications are listed in Table3.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les spécifications de la boîte atomique cubique sont énumérées dans le tableau3.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="83">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Initial random configurations of 5000 atoms were generated and equilibrated at room temperature (glass) or at high temperature (liquid) close to the experimental one, using the reference potential.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des configurations aléatoires initiales de 5000 atomes ont été générées et équilibrées à température ambiante (verre) ou à haute température (liquide) proche de l'expérimentale, en utilisant le potentiel de référence.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="84">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, the empirical potentials were refined by variation of the requested energy amplitude (ereq values) between 0–50kJ⋅mol⁻¹ in order to reproduce the experimental datasets.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ensuite, les potentiels empiriques ont été affinés par variation de l'amplitude énergétique demandée (valeurs ereq) entre 0–50kJ⋅ mol⁻¹ afin de reproduire les jeux de données expérimentales.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="85">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Once a good fit is obtained, with an equilibrated internal energy, statistical structural data were collected by averaging over ensembles of &gt;1500 configurations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une fois qu'un bon ajustement est obtenu, avec une énergie interne équilibrée, des données structurales statistiques ont été collectées en faisant la moyenne sur des ensembles de &gt;1500 configurations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="86">
            <prop type="paragraph">20</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>R_(𝜒) are reliability factors calculated in the real space over the range 1⩽r⩽8Å [Wright 1993].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>R_(𝜒) sont des facteurs de fiabilité calculés dans l'espace réel sur la plage de 1⩽r⩽8Å [Wright 1993].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="87">
            <prop type="paragraph">20</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Temperatures used during simulations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Températures utilisées lors des simulations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="88">
            <prop type="paragraph">21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>4. Results</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>4. Résultats</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="89">
            <prop type="paragraph">22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>4.1. Structure factors</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>4.1. Facteurs de structure</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="90">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The experimental X-ray/neutron structure factors for the samples in the glass and liquid states are shown in Figure1.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les facteurs de structure expérimentaux des rayons X/neutrons pour les échantillons à l'état vitreux et liquide sont présentés à la figure1.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="91">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As MgO is replaced by CaO in glasses, the position of the first peak, Q_(p), in F^(N)(Q) functions is shifted from 1.92 ± 0.01Å⁻¹ for CMS00.50 to 2.05 ± 0.01Å⁻¹ for CMS50.00, and the Q_(p) peak intensity slightly decreases.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Quand MgO est remplacé par CaO dans les verres, la position du premier pic, Q_(p), dans les fonctions F^(N)(Q) est décalée de 1.92 ± 0.01Å⁻¹ pour CMS00.50 à 2.05 ± 0.01Å⁻¹ pour CMS50.00, et l'intensité du pic Q_(p) diminue légèrement.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="92">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These positions are related to density fluctuations separated by a distance d = 2π∕Q_(p), giving values between 3.29 ± 0.02Å for CMS00.50 to 3.06 ± 0.02Å for CMS50.00.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces positions sont reliées à des fluctuations de densité séparées par une distance d = 2π∕Q_(p), produisant des valeurs comprises entre 3.29 ± 0.02Å pour CMS00.50 et 3.06 ± 0.02Å pour CMS50.00.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="93">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>On melting, the Q_(p) peak is clearly shifted to lower Q-values, at ∼1.67Å⁻¹, but the low statistics does not allow to distinguish any compositional variations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Lors de la fusion, le pic Q_(p) est clairement décalé vers des valeurs de Q inférieures, à environ 1.67Å⁻¹, mais les faibles statistiques ne permettent pas de distinguer des variations avec la composition.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="94">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This displacement implies higher correlation distances in the liquids compared to the glasses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce déplacement implique des distances de corrélation plus élevées dans les liquides que dans les verres.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="95">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This can be attributed either to a density effect (lower densities in the liquid state) or to structural changes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cela peut être attribué soit à un effet de densité (densités plus faibles à l'état liquide), soit à des changements structuraux.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="96">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A similar peak is observed in F^(X)(Q) functions for glasses and liquids and, in this case, a strong chemical dependence is observed: the intensity increases as more CaO is substituted to MgO.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un pic similaire est observé dans les fonctions F^(X)(Q) pour les verres et les liquides et, dans ce cas, on observe une forte dépendance chimique: l'intensité augmente à mesure que CaO se substitue à MgO.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="97">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Additionally, the peak position shifts from 2.04 ± 0.02Å⁻¹ to 2.12 ± 0.01Å⁻¹ in glasses with increasing CaO content and from 1.98 ± 0.02Å⁻¹ to 2.15 ± 0.02Å⁻¹ in liquids with increasing CaO content.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De plus, la position du pic passe de 2.04 ± 0.02Å⁻¹ à 2.12 ± 0.01Å⁻¹ dans les verres à teneur croissante en CaO et de 1.98 ± 0.02Å⁻¹ à 2.15 ± 0.02Å⁻¹ dans les liquides à teneur croissante en CaO.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="98">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This peak is thus particularly sensitive to cation organization.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce pic est donc particulièrement sensible à l'organisation des cations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="99">
            <prop type="paragraph">24</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For both neutron and X-ray datasets, the presence of isobestic points (common points in the diffraction patterns) is observed for the glass and the melt series (Supplementary FigureS1).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour les ensembles de données sur les neutrons et les rayons X, on observe la présence de points isobestiques (points communs dans les diagrammes de diffraction) pour les séries verre et liquide (figure supplémentaire S1).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="100">
            <prop type="paragraph">24</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These points indicate that F^(N)(Q) or F^(X)(Q) functions for intermediate compositions can be obtained using a linear combination of the functions for the two end members, i.e. CMS00.50 and CMS50.00 samples [Cormier etal. 2010, Cormier and Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces points indiquent que les fonctions F^(N)(Q) ou F^(X)(Q) pour des compositions intermédiaires peuvent être obtenues en utilisant une combinaison linéaire des fonctions pour les deux membres terminaux, c'est-à-dire les échantillons CMS00.50 et CMS50.00 [Cormier etal. 2010, Cormier and Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="101">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>F^(N)(Q) functions vary mainly between 4–12Å⁻¹ while oscillations are very similar above 12Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les fonctions F^(N)(Q) varient principalement entre 4 et 12Å⁻¹ alors que les oscillations sont très similaires au-dessus de 12Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="102">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This latter region is mainly dominated by SRO associated with the silicate network.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette dernière région est principalement dominée par le SRO associé au réseau silicaté.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="103">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the liquid state, the differences between samples are observed on a limited Q-region 3–7Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A l'état liquide, les différences entre échantillons sont observées sur une région Q limitée entre 3 et 7 Å⁻¹.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="104">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The differences with temperature reflect essentially increased degree of structural disorder.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les différences en fonction de la température reflètent essentiellement un degré accru de désordre structural.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="105">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Above 7Å⁻¹, structure factors are not importantly changed because SRO remains very similar in glasses and liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Au-dessus de 7Å⁻¹, les facteurs de structure ne sont pas modifiés de manière importante parce que le SRO reste très similaire dans les verres et les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="106">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At low Q values, broadening of the signal features is apparent in the liquid state.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour de faibles valeurs de Q, l'élargissement des caractéristiques du signal est apparent à l'état liquide.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="107">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The wollastonite compositions CMS50.00 have previously been studied in detail in the molten state using neutron and XRD techniques in combination with MD simulations [Benmore etal. 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les compositions de wollastonite CMS50.00 ont été précédemment étudiées en détail à l'état liquide en utilisant des techniques de diffraction des neutrons et des rayons X combinées à des simulations DM [Benmore etal. 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="108">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Our ND data have better statistics, allowing more confidence at high Q-values.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nos données DN ont de meilleures statistiques, permettant une confiance accrue sur les valeurs de Q élevées.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="109">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Q_(p) peak has a higher intensity compared to Skinner et al. [Skinner etal. 2012], which is in better agreement with room temperature data.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le pic Q_(p) a une intensité supérieure à celle de Skinner et al.[Skinner etal. 2012], ce qui est en meilleur accord avec les données à température ambiante.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="110">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The F^(X)(Q) functions for the CMS50.00 glass and liquid are similar to those measured by Benmore etal. [2010], indicating reduced CaO evaporation during measurements.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les fonctions F^(X)(Q) pour le verre et le liquide CMS50.00 sont similaires à celles mesurées par Benmore etal. [2010], indiquant une évaporation réduite de CaO pendant les mesures.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="111">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>CMS00.50 has also been previously studied in the liquid state by Wilding et al. [Wilding etal. 2010, 2008] and their XRD data are similar to those in the present study.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>CMS00.50 a également été précédemment étudié à l'état liquide par Wilding et al. [Wilding etal. 2010, 2008] et leurs données DRX sont similaires à celles de la présente étude.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="112">
            <prop type="paragraph">27</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>4.2. Real-space functions</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>4.2. Fonctions dans l'espace réel</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="113">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Fourier transformation of the total structure factor gives the corresponding real-space function (Figure2), called total PDF D(r).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La transformée de Fourier du facteur de structure total fournit la fonction correspondante dans l'espace réel (figure2), appelée fonction de distribution totale de paires (PDF) ou D(r).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="114">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The first three major peaks in D(r) are well understood and correspond to Si–O (1.62Å), Mg–O (2.00Å) and Ca–O (2.40Å) correlations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les trois premiers pics principaux de D(r) sont bien compris et correspondent aux corrélations Si–O (1.62Å), Mg–O (2.00Å) et Ca–O (2.40Å).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="115">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Each radiation has a different sensitivity to the elements: XRD data are dominated by elements with high atomic number (O &lt; Mg &lt; Si &lt; Ca) while ND data are dominated by elements with a high neutron scattering length, b, evolving as b_(Si) = 4.153fm &lt; b_(Ca) = 4.76fm &lt; b_(Mg) = 5.37fm &lt; b_(O) = 5.803fm.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Chaque rayonnement a une sensibilité différente aux éléments: les données DRX sont dominées par les éléments de numéro atomique élevé (O &lt; Mg &lt; Si &lt; Ca) tandis que les données DN sont dominées par les éléments ayant une longueur de diffusion de neutrons élevée, b, évoluant comme b_(Si) = 4.153fm &lt; b_(Ca) = 4.76fm &lt; b_(Mg) = 5.37fm &lt; b_(O) = 5.803fm.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="116">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These different sensitivities explain that the Ca–O correlation is clearly distinguished at 2.38Å in D^(X)(r) functions while they appear in D^(N)(r) functions as a small hump on the low-r side of the peak at 2.63Å that is dominated by O–O contributions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces différentes sensibilités expliquent que la corrélation Ca–O se distingue clairement à 2.38Å dans les fonctions D^(X)(r) alors qu'elles apparaissent dans les fonctions D^(N)(r) sous la forme d'un petit épaulement sur le côté des r bas du pic à 2.63Å qui est dominé par les contributions O-O.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="117">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The presence of isobestic points can also be observed in the D(r) functions (Supplementary FigureS2).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La présence de points isobestiques peut également être observée dans les fonctions D(r) (figure supplémentaire S2).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="118">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Variations at medium range distances are mainly associated with the silicate network in D^(N)(r) functions and with correlations involving cations in D^(X)(r) functions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les variations à moyenne échelle sont principalement associées au réseau silicaté dans les fonctions D^(N)(r) et à des corrélations impliquant des cations dans les fonctions D^(X)(r)</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="119">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In XRD data, the peak attribution has previously indicated that contributions near 3.16Å are mainly due to Si–Mg and Mg–Mg correlations and contributions near 3.56Å are mainly due to Ca–Ca and Ca–Si correlations [Cormier and Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les données DRX, l'attribution du pic a précédemment indiqué que les contributions proches de 3.16Å sont principalement dues aux corrélations Si-Mg et Mg–Mg et les contributions proches de 3.56Å sont principalement dues aux corrélations Ca–Ca et Ca–Si [Cormier et Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="120">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The functions for all liquids have similar SRO compared to glasses, with a distinct Si–O contribution that is slightly shifted from 1.62Å to 1.63Å with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les fonctions de tous les liquides ont des SRO semblables à celles des verres, avec une contribution distincte de Si–O qui est légèrement décalée de 1.62Å à 1.63Å en fonction de la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="121">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, the Mg–O and Ca–O peaks are no longer resolved indicating important thermal disordering due to broad distributions of Mg–O and Ca–O distances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, les pics de Mg–O et de Ca–O ne sont plus résolus, ce qui indique un désordre thermique important dû à de larges distributions des distances Mg-O et Ca-O.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="122">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the liquids, the Mg–O peak overlaps with the Si–O one and the Ca–O peak is less resolved in the XRD data.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les liquides, les pics de Mg–O et de Si-O se chevauchent et le pic de Ca–O est moins résolu dans les données DRX.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="123">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The structural peaks in the D^(X)(r) functions are clearly less resolved than in D^(N)(r) functions at high temperature and the broadening of the peaks in D^(X)(r) functions is increasing as the CaO content is increased.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les pics structuraux dans les fonctions D^(X)(r)) sont nettement moins résolus que dans les fonctions D^(N)(r) à haute température et l'élargissement des pics dans les fonctions DX(r) augmente à mesure que la teneur en CaO augmente.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="124">
            <prop type="paragraph">30</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>4.3. EPSR models</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>4.3. Modèles EPSR</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="125">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Accurate information about the cation–oxygen local environment is difficult to obtain from direct analysis, for instance from Gaussian fits, due to large overlap between the various contributions, which is even enhanced as the temperature is increased.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il est difficile d'obtenir des informations précises sur l'environnement local cation-oxygène à partir d'une analyse directe, par exemple à partir d'ajustements gaussiens, en raison du chevauchement important entre les différentes contributions, qui s'accentue encore lorsque la température augmente.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="126">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>EPSR modelling is an alternative fitting method allowing the extraction of detailed structural information from atomic configurations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La modélisation EPSR est une méthode d'ajustement alternative permettant l'extraction d'informations structurales détaillées à partir de configurations atomiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="127">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A good agreement is obtained by fitting simultaneously the neutron and XRD data, as seen in Figure3 for all glasses and in Figure4 for all liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On obtient une correspondance correcte en ajustant simultanément les données issues des diffractions de neutrons et de rayons X, comme on le voit à la figure3 pour tous les verres et à la figure4 pour tous les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="128">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The corresponding D(r) functions are in Supplementary FiguresS3 and S4.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les fonctions D(r) correspondantes apparaissent dans les figures supplémentaires S3 et S4.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="129">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The reliability factors R_(𝜒) are determined on the D(r) functions following Wright [Wright 1993] and the values are reported in Table3.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les facteurs de fiabilité R_(𝜒) sont déterminés sur les fonctions D(r) suivant Wright [Wright 1993] et les valeurs sont reportées dans le tableau3.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="130">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A good level of agreement between the EPSR models and the experimental data is achieved with R_(𝜒) factors comparable or better than published in previous studies [Gong etal. 2021, Guignard and Cormier 2008].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un bon niveau de correspondance entre les modèles EPSR et les données expérimentales est atteint avec des facteurs R_(𝜒) comparables ou meilleurs que ceux publiés dans les études précédentes [Gong etal. 2021, Guignard and Cormier 2008].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="131">
            <prop type="paragraph">32</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The EPSR-derived partial pair distribution functions (PPDFs) are shown in Figure5 only for CMS00.50, CMS25.25 and CMS50.00 for clarity (all PPDFs for each glass/melt are in Supplementary Figure S5).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les fonctions de distribution partielle de paires (PPDF, partial pair distribution functions) dérivées de l'EPSR sont illustrées à la figure5 uniquement pour CMS00.50, CMS25.25 et CMS50.00 pour plus de clarté (tous les PPDF pour chaque verre/liquides apparaissent dans la figure supplémentaire S5).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="132">
            <prop type="paragraph">32</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The first peak in the Mg–O and Ca–O PPDFs exhibits a considerable broadening in the liquid state indicating that the oxygen disorder increases around these cations with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le premier pic des PPDF Mg–O et Ca–O présente un élargissement considérable à l'état liquide indiquant que le désordre de l'oxygène augmente autour de ces cations en fonction de la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="133">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Using the minimum after the first main peak in Si–O, Mg–O and Ca–O PPDFs as a cutoff distance, the number of O neighbors around Si, Mg and Ca were determined.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En utilisant le minimum après le premier pic principal dans les PPDF Si–O, Mg–O et Ca–O comme distance de coupure, le nombre de voisins O autour de Si, Mg et Ca a été déterminé.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="134">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Cutoff distances are reported in Table4.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les distances de coupure sont indiquées dans le tableau4.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="135">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average coordination numbers (CNs) are plotted in Figure6.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les nombres moyens de coordination (NC) sont indiqués à la figure6.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="136">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Silicon is mainly four-fold coordinated in all compositions for all glasses and liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le silicium est principalement quadricoordonné dans toutes les compositions pour tous les verres et liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="137">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Small amounts of three and five-coordinated Si sites ( &lt;3%) are observed and their proportion does not change significantly with composition or temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De petites quantités de sites Si tricoordonnés et pentacoordonnés (&lt;3%) sont observées et leur proportion ne change pas significativement avec la composition ou la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="138">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is consistent with a corner-sharing tetrahedral silicate network dominating the liquid structure at ambient pressure.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci est cohérent avec un réseau silicaté de tétraèdres partageants les sommets qui dominent la structure liquide à pression ambiante.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="139">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The CN(Mg–O) is around 4.5 in glasses and increases by ∼0.25 with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le NC(Mg–O) est de ∼4.5 dans les verres et augmente de ∼0.25 avec la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="140">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Similarly the CN(Ca–O) increases from ∼5.8 in glasses to ∼6.3 in liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De même, le NC(Ca–O) passe de ∼5.8 dans les verres à ∼6.3 dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="141">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However the CN as a function of r, CN(r) (Figure7), shows that defining a cutoff distance in the liquid state is difficult since no clear plateau is apparent for Mg and Ca, contrary to Si.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, le NC en fonction de r, NC(r) (figure7), montre qu'il est difficile de définir une distance de coupure à l'état liquide puisqu'aucun plateau clair n'apparaît pour Mg et Ca, contrairement à Si.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="142">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Therefore, defining the first shell of oxygen neighbors around Mg and Ca in the liquid state is non-ambiguous.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Par conséquent, la définition de la première couche de voisins de l'oxygène autour de Mg et Ca à l'état liquide est non ambiguë.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="143">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is due to the continuous distribution of Mg–O and Ca–O distances as revealed by the lack of minima going to zero in the Mg–O and Ca–O PPDFs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci est dû à la distribution continue des distances Mg–O et Ca–O révélée par l'absence de minimum atteignant zéro dans les PPDF Mg–O et Ca-O.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="144">
            <prop type="paragraph">34</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The site distribution for Mg and Ca in glasses and liquids is provided in Figure8, using the cutoff distances in Table4.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La distribution des sites pour Mg et Ca dans les verres et les liquides est fournie à la figure8, en utilisant les distances de coupure du tableau4.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="145">
            <prop type="paragraph">34</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The x-fold sites are denoted ^([x])Mg or ^([x])Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les sites en coordinence x sont notés ^([x])Mg ou ^([x])Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="146">
            <prop type="paragraph">34</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In glasses, the site distribution indicates a majority of ^([4])Mg sites, with some ^([5])Mg sites, and a majority of ^([6])Ca sites with the coexistence of ^([5])Ca and ^([7])Ca sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les verres, la distribution des sites indique une majorité de sites ^([4])Mg, avec certains sites ^([5])Mg, et une majorité de sites ^([6])Ca avec la coexistence de sites ^([5])Ca et ^([7])Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="147">
            <prop type="paragraph">34</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Ca and Mg site distributions show close similarities with previous models obtained by coupling MD and RMC (see Supplementary Figure S6) [Cormier and Cuello 2012, 2011].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les distributions des sites Ca et Mg montrent de grandes similitudes avec les modèles précédents obtenus en couplant DM et RMC (voir la figure supplémentaire S6) [Cormier et Cuello 2012, 2011].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="148">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The distributions of bridging oxygens (BO), non-bridging oxygens (NBO) and free-oxygens (FO) (FO are not bonded to any Si atoms) are plotted in Figure9a.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les distributions des oxygènes pontants (OP), des oxygènes non-pontants (ONP) et des oxygènes libres (OL) (OL ne sont liés à aucun atome de Si) sont représentées sur la figure9a.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="149">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The NBO fraction has a decreasing trend with increasing MgO content.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La fraction ONP a une tendance décroissante avec l'augmentation de la teneur en MgO.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="150">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The presence of triply bonded O is always less than 0.9% of all oxygen atoms in glasses/liquids and the content is thus not significant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La présence de O triplement lié est toujours inférieure à 0.9% de la totalité des atomes d'oxygène dans les verres/liquides et la teneur n'est donc pas significative.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="151">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the liquid state, the NBO proportion increases, which is concomitant with a decrease in BO and FO.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A l'état liquide, la proportion de ONP augmente, ce qui est concomitant avec une diminution de OP et OL.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="152">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The low BO proportion is reflected by a lower average network connectivity that is quantified by the average number of n BO atoms around a silicon atom (Figure9b).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La faible proportion de OP se traduit par une connectivité moyenne du réseau plus faible qui est quantifiée par le nombre moyen de n atomes de OP autour d'un atome de silicium (figure9b).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="153">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average network connectivity shows increasing values as the MgO content increases in glasses and liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La connectivité moyenne du réseau montre des valeurs croissantes à mesure que la teneur en MgO augmente dans les verres et les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="154">
            <prop type="paragraph">36</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5. Discussion</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5. Discussion</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="155">
            <prop type="paragraph">37</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5.1. Comparison between atomistic models</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5.1. Comparaison entre les modèles atomistiques</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="156">
            <prop type="paragraph">38</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The EPSR models can be compared to our previous results obtained by combining MD simulations with RMC modelling [Cormier and Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les modèles EPSR peuvent être comparés à nos résultats précédents obtenus en combinant des simulations DM avec la modélisation RMC [Cormier et Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="157">
            <prop type="paragraph">38</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In CMS00.50, the average CN for Mg remains similar: CN_(MD+RMC) = 4.35 and CN_(EPSR) = 4.48 (Supplementary Figure S6a,b).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans CMS00.50, le NC moyen pour le Mg reste similaire:CN_(DM+RMC) = 4.35 et CN_(EPSR) = 4.48 (figure supplémentaire S6a,b).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="158">
            <prop type="paragraph">38</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The distribution of the various coordination sites gives almost an equal amount of ^([4])Mg (52%) and ^([5])Mg (41%) in EPSR while ^([4])Mg was predominant (68%) in the MD+RMC model.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La distribution des différents sites de coordination produit une quantité presque égale de ^([4])Mg (52%) et ^([5])Mg (41%) dans l'EPSR tandis que ^([4])Mg était prédominant (68%) dans le modèle DM+RMC.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="159">
            <prop type="paragraph">38</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For Ca in CMS50.00, the average CN and the site distribution are not substantially changed (Supplementary Figure S6c,d).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour le Ca dans la CMS50.00, le NC moyen et la distribution du site ne sont pas significativement modifiés (figure supplémentaire S6c,d).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="160">
            <prop type="paragraph">38</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It thus appears that both methods of data fitting give convergent results, strengthening the validity of this approach to determine the SRO.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il apparaît donc que les deux méthodes d'ajustement des données produisent des résultats convergents, renforçant la validité de cette approche pour déterminer le SRO.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="161">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The distributions of BO, NBO and FO show that EPSR models contain more BO and free O compared to MD+RMC models, with a slight compositional dependence (Figure9a). The higher BO content explains a high average connectivity in EPSR models (Figure9b) that increases with the MgO content as in MD+RMC models.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les distributions de OP, ONP et OL montrent que les modèles EPSR contiennent plus de OP et d'O libre que les modèles DM+RMC, avec une légère dépendance de composition (figure9a). La teneur plus élevée en OL explique une connectivité moyenne élevée dans les modèles EPSR (figure9b) qui augmente avec la teneur en MgO comme dans les modèles DM+RMC.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="162">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join corresponds to metasilicate compositions so that n is expected to have a value of2.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le joint MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ correspond à des compositions de métasilicate de sort que l'on s'attend à ce que n ait une valeur de2.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="163">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The departure from this value for glasses is higher for EPSR than for MD+RMC.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'écart par rapport à cette valeur pour les verres est plus élevé pour EPSR que pour DM+RMC.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="164">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Interestingly, the liquid EPSR models have values closer to MD+RMC models, probably because MD+RMC models retain more structural characteristic features of the high-temperature state due to the intrinsic fast quenching rates in MD simulations and insufficient relaxation of the structure in RMC modelling of glasses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il est intéressant de noter que les modèles EPSR liquides ont des valeurs plus proches des modèles DM+RMC, probablement parce que les modèles DM+RMC conservent davantage les caractéristiques structurales de l'état à haute température en raison des vitesses de trempe rapides intrinsèques dans les simulations DM et de la relaxation insuffisante de la structure dans la modélisation RMC des verres.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="165">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Q^(n) speciation (Q^(n) is a SiO₄ tetrahedra containing n BO atoms) shows more Q³ and Q⁴ and less Q², Q¹ an Q⁰ in EPSR models compared to MD+RMC models (Figure10).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La spéciation Q^(n) (Q^(n) est un tétraèdre SiO₄ contenant n atomes de OP) montre plus de Q³ et de Q⁴ et moins de Q², de Q¹ et de Q⁰ dans les modèles EPSR par rapport aux modèles DM+RMC (figure10).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="166">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Both models present discrepancies with the Q^(n) proportions determined experimentally by ²⁹Si NMR for CMS00.50, CMS25.25 and CMS50.00 glasses [Schneider etal. 2003, Sen etal. 2009, Zhang etal. 1997], as these measurements determined higher Q² and Q¹ contents and lower Q³ and Q⁴ contents compared to models.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les deux modèles présentent des écarts avec les proportions de Q^(n) déterminées expérimentalement par RMN de ²⁹Si pour les verres CMS00.50, CMS25.25 et CMS50.00 [Schneider etal. 2003, Sen etal. 2009, Zhang etal. 1997], car ces mesures ont déterminé des teneurs plus élevées en Q² et en Q¹ et des teneurs plus faibles en Q³ et en Q⁴ par rapport aux modèles.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="167">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A recent MD study with advanced potentials indicates Q^(n) speciation for CMS00.50 and CMS50.00 very similar to our results with an underestimation of Q² and an overestimation of Q³ and Q⁴ [Shih etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une récente étude DM avec des potentiels avancés indique une spéciation Q^(n) pour CMS00.50 et CMS50.00 très similaire à nos résultats avec une sous-estimation de Q² et une surestimation de Q³ et de Q⁴ [Shih etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="168">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These results indicate that additional constraints should be incorporated in the models to improve the description of some specific structural units or groups.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces résultats indiquent que des contraintes supplémentaires devraient être incorporées dans les modèles pour améliorer la description de certaines unités ou groupes structuraux spécifiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="169">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, careful comparison between experimental and atomistic models should be provided to ensure continuous improving in modelling and simulations of glasses and melts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En outre, une comparaison minutieuse entre les modèles expérimentaux et atomistiques devrait être fournie pour assurer une amélioration continue de la modélisation et des simulations de verres et de liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="170">
            <prop type="paragraph">41</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5.2. Evolution of Si environment with temperature</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5.2. Évolution de l'environnement de Si en fonction de la température</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="171">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For the Si–O pair, the CN(r) shows a clear plateau (Figure7a) that indicates a well-defined environment around Si atoms corresponding to SiO₄ tetrahedra in both glasses and liquids, with very small proportions of other coordinated sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour la paire Si–O, le NC(r) montre un plateau clair (figure7a) qui indique un environnement bien défini autour des atomes de Si correspondant aux tétraèdres de SiO₄ dans les verres et les liquides, avec de très faibles proportions d'autres sites coordonnés.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="172">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>SiO₄ tetrahedra are poorly affected by an increase in temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les tétraèdres de SiO₄ sont peu affectés par une augmentation de la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="173">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The position of the first peak in the total D(r) functions is not informative as it is affected by Mg–O contributions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La position du premier pic dans les fonctions totales D(r) n'est pas informative car elle est affectée par les contributions de Mg-O.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="174">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In CMS50.00 (Mg-free sample), the position of the Si–O peak is increased by + 0.01Å with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans CMS50.00 (échantillon sans Mg), la position du pic Si–O est augmentée de + 0.01Å avec la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="175">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Si–O PPDFs determined from the EPSR models do not show significant changes with temperature except a broadening consistent with thermal disordering.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les PPDF Si–O déterminés à partir des modèles EPSR ne montrent pas de changements significatifs en fonction de la température, à l'exception d'un élargissement cohérent avec un désordre thermique.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="176">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The structure along the MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join is highly depolymerized with a high proportion of Q² and Q³ species, in agreement with previous experimental findings [De Sousa Meneses etal. 2006, Schneider etal. 2003, Zhang etal. 1997].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La structure le long du joint MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ est fortement dépolymérisée avec une proportion élevée d'espèces Q² et Q³, en accord avec les résultats expérimentaux précédents [De Sousa Meneses etal. 2006, Schneider etal. 2003, Zhang etal. 1997].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="177">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, the degree of connectivity displayed in Figure9b is higher than expected considering the stoichiometry.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, le degré de connectivité affiché à la figure9b est plus élevé que prévu compte tenu de la stoechiométrie.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="178">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The glass/melt structures present a broad range of Q^(n) species compared to the structure of crystalline counterparts that is composed only of Q² species.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les structures verre/liquide présentent une large gamme d'espèces Q^(n) comparées à la structure des homologues cristallins qui est composée uniquement d'espèces Q².</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="179">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Based on observations on the 3D configurational boxes, the silicate network may possibly be described as a chain-like network structure of corner-sharing SiO₄ tetrahedra forming broken chains coexisting with few rings.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sur la base des observations sur les boîtes de configuration 3D, le réseau silicaté pourrait être décrit comme une structure de réseau en forme de chaîne de tétraèdres SiO₄ partageant les sommets formant des chaînes brisées coexistant avec quelques anneaux.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="180">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This differs from the topology of pyroxenes and pyroxenoids that is composed only of tetrahedral chains.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci diffère de la topologie des pyroxènes et des pyroxénoïdes qui est uniquement composée de chaînes tétraédriques.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="181">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, chemical evolutions are visible in Figure9: the substitution of Ca by Mg yields a slight increase in connectivity associated with more BO and FO.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De plus, des évolutions chimiques sont visibles sur la figure9: la substitution du Ca par le Mg conduit à une légère augmentation de la connectivité associée à plus de OP et de OL.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="182">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, as Mg and Ca cations have the same charge, the Mg/Ca mixing does not require significant charge redistribution in the structure, which explains small network modifications (Figures9 and 10).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, comme les cations Mg et Ca ont la même charge, le mélange Mg/Ca ne nécessite pas de redistribution significative des charges dans la structure, ce qui explique les petites modifications du réseau (figures9 et 10).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="183">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The difference in cationic radii is essentially accommodated by a distribution of the two cations in multiple distinct sites (Figures7 and8).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La différence de rayons cationiques est essentiellement compensée par une distribution des deux cations dans de multiples sites distincts (figures7 et8).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="184">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>There is a clear trend for higher NBO content and lower BO and FO contents in liquids compared to glasses (Figure9a).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On observe une nette tendance à une teneur plus élevée en ONP et à des teneurs plus faibles en OP et en OL dans les liquides par rapport aux verres (figure9a).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="185">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These changes in oxygen speciation, associated with lower Q³ species and higher Q¹ species, indicate that the liquid network is less connected.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces changements dans la spéciation de l'oxygène, associés à des espèces Q³ plus faibles et à des espèces Q¹ plus élevées, indiquent que le réseau liquide est moins connecté.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="186">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>FO species correspond to oxygen not bounded to any SiO₄ tetrahedra and can thus be a signature for regions that are enriched in Mg and Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les espèces OL correspondent à de l'oxygène non lié à des tétraèdres SiO₄ et peuvent donc être une signature pour des régions enrichies en Mg et Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="187">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Conversely, the high proportion of BO can indicate highly polymerized silicate regions depleted in Mg and Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Inversement, la forte proportion de OL peut indiquer des régions de silicate hautement polymérisées appauvries en Mg et Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="188">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As FO and BO contents increase upon cooling, the segregation between silicate-rich and (Mg,Ca)-rich regions is more important in glasses compared to melts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Au fur et à mesure que les teneurs en OL et en OP augmentent lors du refroidissement, la ségrégation entre les régions riches en silicate et les régions riches en (Mg, Ca) est plus importante dans les verres que dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="189">
            <prop type="paragraph">45</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5.3. Evolution of Mg environment with temperature</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5.3. Évolution de l'environnement de Mg en fonction de la température</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="190">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In glasses, the Mg site distribution indicates not only a prevalence of ^([4])Mg sites but also a large amount of ^([5])Mg sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les verres, la distribution des sites de Mg indique non seulement une prévalence des sites de ^([4])Mg, mais aussi une grande quantité de sites de ^([5])Mg.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="191">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The presence of polyhedra with 4- and 5-fold coordination is also well established for other divalent cations such as Fe²⁺, Ni²⁺ or Zn²⁺ [Cormier etal. 2021, Galoisy and Calas 1993, Jackson etal. 2005, Waychunas etal. 1988].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La présence de polyèdres quadricoordonné et pentacoordonné est également bien établie pour d'autres cations divalents tels que Fe²⁺, Ni²⁺ ou Zn²⁺ [Cormier etal. 2021, Galoisy et Calas 1993, Jackson etal. 2005, Waychunas etal. 1988].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="192">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the liquids, higher coordinated sites are present, mainly ^([5])Mg and a small amount of ^([6])Mg, coexisting with still a large amount of ^([4])Mg (Figure8).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les liquides, des sites à coordinence plus élevée sont présents, principalement ^([5])Mg et une petite quantité de ^([6])Mg, coexistant avec encore une grande quantité de ^([4])Mg (figure8).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="193">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Upon increasing temperature, there is thus a site redistribution that is reflected in the evolution of the average CN(Mg–O) near 4.5 in glasses and near 4.7–4.8 in liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Lors de l'augmentation de la température, il y a donc une redistribution des sites qui se reflète dans l'évolution du NC moyen (Mg–O) proche de 4.5 dans les verres et proche de 4.7-4.8 dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="194">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These values agree with very recent MD simulations for CMS00.50 [Shih etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces valeurs concordent avec des simulations de DM très récentes pour CMS00.50 [Shih etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="195">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Mg–O environment is more ordered in CMS00.50 glass compared to other glasses as seen in the Mg–O PPDF that exhibits a well-defined first peak (Figure5a).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'environnement Mg–O est plus ordonné dans le verre CMS00.50 que dans d'autres verres, comme on le voit dans le PPDF de Mg–O qui présente un premier pic bien défini (figure5a).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="196">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average CN(Mg–O) in CMS00.50 is the lowest, in agreement with previous findings [Cormier and Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le NC(Mg–O) moyen dans CMS00.50 est le plus bas, en accord avec les résultats précédents [Cormier et Cuello 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="197">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Otherwise there is no clear compositional dependence either in glasses or in liquids within the scatter of the data.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Autrement, il n'y a pas de dépendance claire avec la composition, que ce soit dans les verres ou dans les liquides, au vu de la dispersion des données.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="198">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A plateau is discernible in the CN(r) in glasses (Figure7b), allowing to define the first oxygen coordination shell around Mg atoms, whereas it is more difficult to determine the correct inflexion points for liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un plateau est visible dans le NC(r) des verres (figure7b), permettant de définir la première couche de coordination de l'oxygène autour des atomes de Mg, alors qu'il est plus difficile de déterminer les points d'inflexion corrects pour les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="199">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Inspection of the first peak position in the Mg–O PPDFs reveals a shift from 2.02 ± 0.02Å in glasses to 1.98 ± 0.02Å in liquids (Figure5 and Supplementary FigureS7a).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La lecture de la position du premier pic dans les PPDF de Mg–O révèle un passage de 2.02 ± 0.02Å dans les verres à 1.98 ± 0.02Å dans les liquides (figure5 et figure supplémentaire S7a).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="200">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Though this evolution of the maximum peak position could indicate a coordination decrease, a long tail in the high r-side in liquids implies the contribution of additional long Mg–O distances that explain the increase in CN with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Bien que cette évolution de la position maximale du pic puisse indiquer une diminution de la coordinence, une longue traîne du côté des r élevés pour les liquides implique la contribution additionnelle de longues distances Mg–O qui expliquent l'augmentation du NC avec la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="201">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Previous XRD or EXAFS studies have usually obtained low Mg CNs [Matsubara etal. 1988, Taniguchi etal. 1997, Yin etal. 1983] due to the difficulties to correctly determine the CN when an asymmetric distribution of distances exists.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les études précédentes de DRX ou d'EXAFS ont généralement obtenu des NC bas pour Mg [Matsubara etal. 1988, Taniguchi etal. 1997, Yin etal. 1983] en raison des difficultés à déterminer correctement le NC lorsqu'il existe une distribution asymétrique des distances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="202">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Because of disorder and site distortion, high-r contributions are regularly not detected in EXAFS data as this method is more sensitive to nearest neighbors [Kroeker and Stebbins 2000].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En raison du désordre et de la distorsion du site, les contributions de r élevées ne sont régulièrement pas détectées dans les données EXAFS car cette méthode est plus sensible aux voisins les plus proches [Kroeker et Stebbins 2000].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="203">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The modelling approaches (EPSR or RMC) give a more accurate determination of CN as this value is not based on a Gaussian fit.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les approches de modélisation (EPSR ou RMC) assurent une détermination plus précise du NC car cette valeur n'est pas basée sur un ajustement gaussien.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="204">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The shortening of Mg–O distances in the liquids is remarkable since a thermal expansion is expected.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le raccourcissement des distances Mg–O dans les liquides est remarquable puisqu'une dilatation thermique est attendue.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="205">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These short Mg–O distances are compensated by the presence of long Mg–O ones, resulting in the high r-side tail and yielding a more distorted environment in the liquid than in the glass.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces courtes distances de Mg–O sont compensées par la présence de longues distances de Mg–O, ce qui entraîne la traîne du côté des r élevés et produit un environnement plus déformé dans le liquide que dans le verre.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="206">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A different behavior may be observed for divalent transition metals in the molten states.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un comportement différent peut être observé pour les métaux de transition divalents à l'état fondu.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="207">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Indeed, a shortening of the Ni–O distances in a Na_(1.95)Ni_(0.05)Si₂O₅ melt has been inferred by high-temperature X-ray absorption spectroscopy [Farges etal. 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, un raccourcissement des distances Ni–O dans un liquide Na_(1.95)Ni_(0.05)Si₂O₅ a été déduit par spectroscopie d'absorption des rayons X à haute température [Farges etal. 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="208">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This was interpreted as an increasing content of ^([4])Ni during the glass to melt transition.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci a été interprété comme une teneur croissante en ^([4])Ni pendant la transition du verre à la l'état liquide.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="209">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Fe²⁺ has also been found in four-fold coordination in alkali silicate glasses and melts with no temperature effects [Waychunas etal. 1988].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Du Fe²⁺ quadricoordonné a également été trouvé dans les verres et des liquides de silicate alcalin sans effets de température [Waychunas etal. 1988].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="210">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However such EXAFS studies may be insensitive to long Ni–O or Fe–O distances, especially in the liquid state.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, de telles études EXAFS peuvent être insensibles aux longues distances Ni–O ou Fe–O, en particulier à l'état liquide.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="211">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Very few studies have been performed insitu to understand the Mg environment in silicate melts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Très peu d'études ont été réalisées insitu pour comprendre l'environnement du Mg dans les liquides silicatés.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="212">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>George and Stebbins have obtained ²⁵Mg NMR spectra up to 1743K in a diopside melt and a melt close to CMS12.38 compositions (but with 6mol% Al₂O₃) [George and Stebbins 1998] and Fiske and Georges on CMS29.14 at 1673K [Fiske and Stebbins 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>George et Stebbins ont obtenu des spectres RMN de ²⁵Mg jusqu'à 1743K pour un diopside liquide et pour un liquide proche des compositions CMS12.38 (mais avec 6%mol Al₂O₃) [George et Stebbins 1998] et Fiske et Georges sur CMS29.14 à 1673K [Fiske et Stebbins 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="213">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For the liquids, George and Stebbins have observed a change with addition of Ca (or alkalis) with a shift of the peak position to higher frequencies indicating a decrease in the average CN(Mg–O).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour les liquides, George et Stebbins ont observé un changement avec l'addition de Ca (ou d'alcalis) avec un déplacement de la position du pic vers des fréquences plus élevées indiquant une diminution du NC moyen (Mg–O).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="214">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However these changes are small.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, ces changements sont minimes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="215">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>There is a strong temperature dependence of CN(Mg–O) with substantially smaller CN in the glass [Fiske and Stebbins 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On observe une forte dépendance du NC(Mg–O) en fonction de la température, le NC étant sensiblement plus bas dans le verre [Fiske et Stebbins, 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="216">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The NMR chemical shifts at high temperatures are in agreement with a CN between five and six and significantly different to the one expected for four-fold coordination [George and Stebbins 1998].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les déplacements chimiques en RMN à haute température sont en accord avec un CN compris entre cinq et six et significativement différents de celui attendu pour une coordinence quatre [George et Stebbins 1998].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="217">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This behavior is consistent with the increase in CN from the glass to the liquid as deduced from the present diffraction data analysis.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce comportement est cohérent avec l'augmentation du NC du verre au liquide, comme déduite de la présente analyse des données de diffraction.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="218">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Gaussian fits of high-temperature X-ray PDF do not show any Mg coordination change for the enstatite composition (CMS00.50) [Wilding etal. 2010], while a small Mg–O coordination increase from 4.8 in the glass to 5.1 in the liquid for a CMS37.00 sample (37.5MgO–62.5SiO₂) has been revealed using several Gaussian functions to fit the Mg–O contribution [Benmore etal. 2020].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les ajustements gaussiens de la PDF aux rayons X à haute température ne montrent aucun changement de coordinence de Mg pour la composition de l'enstatite (CMS00.50) [Wilding etal. 2010], alors qu'une petite augmentation de la coordinence de Mg–O de 4.8 dans le verre à 5.1 dans le liquide pour un échantillon CMS37.00 (37.5MgO-62.5SiO₂) a été révélée en utilisant plusieurs fonctions gaussiennes pour ajuster la contribution de Mg–O [Benmore etal. 2020].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="219">
            <prop type="paragraph">49</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5.4. Evolution of Ca environment with temperature</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5.4. Évolution de l'environnement de Ca en fonction de la température</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="220">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Similar to Mg, analysis of EPSR models indicate that Ca cations are localized in a wide distribution of sites (Figure8b).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Comme pour le Mg, l'analyse des modèles EPSR indique que les cations sont localisés dans une large distribution de sites (figure8b).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="221">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Ca environment is dominantly ^([6])Ca with both ^([5])Ca and ^([7])Ca in glasses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'environnement de Ca est principalement constitué de ^([6])Ca avec à la fois du ^([5])Ca et du ^([7])Ca dans les verres.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="222">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The site speciation is redistributed to higher coordinated sites in liquids (Figure8b): less ^([5])Ca and ^([6])Ca and more ^([7])Ca and ^([8])Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La spéciation du site est redistribuée à des sites à coordinence plus élevée dans les liquides (figure8b): moins de ^([5])Ca et de ^([6])Ca et plus de ^([7])Ca et de ^([8])Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="223">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average coordination of Ca is higher than that of Mg in agreement with its lower field strength (defined as the ratio z∕d², where z denotes the cation charge and d is the cation–oxygen bond length).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La coordinence moyenne de Ca est plus élevée que celle de Mg, conformément à sa plus faible intensité de champ (définie comme le rapport z∕d², où z désigne la charge cationique et d la longueur de la liaison cation-oxygène).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="224">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Evolution of the first Ca–O distance in the Ca–O PPDFs shows a similar behavior than the Mg–O ones with increasing temperature: shortening of the average Ca–O bond length from 2.30 ± 0.02Å to 2.25 ± 0.01Å and a broadening and asymmetric distribution to the high r-side (Figure5 and Supplementary FigureS7b).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'évolution de la première distance Ca–O dans les PPDF Ca–O montre un comportement similaire à celui des PPDF Mg–O pour une température croissante: raccourcissement de la longueur moyenne des liaisons Ca–O de 2.30 ± 0.02Å à 2.25 ± 0.01Å et une distribution élargie et asymétrique du côté des r élevés (figure5 et figure supplémentaire S7b).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="225">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average CN(Ca–O) is increased from ∼5.8 in the glasses to ∼6.3 in the liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le NC(Ca–O) moyen est augmenté de ∼5.8 dans les verres à ∼6.3 dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="226">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is consistent with MD simulations of CaSiO₃ glass/melt that indicate both short and long Ca–O distances in the melt [Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci est cohérent avec les simulations DM du verre/liquide de CaSiO₃ qui indiquent à la fois des courtes et longues distances de Ca–O dans le liquide [Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="227">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the latter investigation, a symmetric Gaussian fit of the first Ca–O peak yields a decrease in the Ca–O CN from 6 in the glass to 5 in the liquid [Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans cette dernière étude, un ajustement gaussien symétrique du premier pic Ca–O conduit à une diminution du NC de Ca–O de 6 dans le verre à 5 dans le liquide [Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="228">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, using additional Gaussian functions in the fit, the CN(Ca–O) does not vary with temperature (6.6 in the glass and 6.5 in the liquid) for a CMS20.00 sample (20CaO–80SiO₂) measured using high-temperature XRD [Benmore etal. 2020].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, en utilisant des fonctions gaussiennes supplémentaires dans l'ajustement, le NC(Ca–O) ne varie pas avec la température (6.6 dans le verre et 6.5 dans le liquide) pour un échantillon CMS20.00 (20CaO-80SiO₂) mesuré à l'aide de DRX à haute température [Benmore etal. 2020].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="229">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This again emphasizes that a distorted environment cannot easily be captured by a simple Gaussian fit.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cela souligne à nouveau qu'un environnement déformé ne peut pas facilement être capturé par un simple ajustement gaussien.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="230">
            <prop type="paragraph">51</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5.5. Distribution of Ca and Mg</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5.5. Distribution de Ca et Mg</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="231">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To understand the connection of Mg sites with the tetrahedral silicate network, we have calculated the number of NBO and BO around cations (Figure11).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour comprendre la connexion des sites de Mg avec le réseau silicaté tétraédrique, nous avons calculé le nombre de ONP et OP autour des cations (figure11).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="232">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>An important proportion of O neighbors are NBO (∼60%) and this proportion decreases only weakly with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une proportion importante de voisins O sont ONP (∼60 %) et cette proportion ne diminue que faiblement en fonction de la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="233">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The proportion of BO in the first coordination shell around Ca is higher than for Mg indicating a preferential association of Ca with BO.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La proportion de OP dans la première couche de coordination autour de Ca est plus élevée que pour Mg, indiquant une association préférentielle de Ca avec OP.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="234">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is attributed to the lower field strength of Ca compared to Mg and thus its lower ability to charge-balancing the negative charge around NBO sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci est attribué à la plus faible intensité de champ de Ca par rapport à Mg et donc à sa plus faible capacité à équilibrer la charge négative autour des sites ONP.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="235">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A ^([4])Mg site implies strong bond strengths and, thereby, a BO atom that is connected to two SiO₄ and one MgO₄ would be severely overbonded.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un site ^([4])Mg implique de solides forces de liaison et, par conséquent, un atome OL qui est connecté à deux SiO₄ et un MgO₄ serait surlié de façon importante.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="236">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Therefore, the oxygen connecting Mg to Si is preferentially a NBO atom.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ainsi, l'oxygène reliant Mg à Si est préférentiellement un atome ONP.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="237">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The high proportion of Ca–BO bonds may be explained by Ca atoms partly residing in more polymerized silicate-rich regions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La proportion élevée de liaisons Ca–OP peut s'expliquer par le fait que les atomes de Ca se trouvent en partie dans les régions riches en silicates plus polymérisés.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="238">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This different behavior between Mg and Ca is supported by a O¹⁷-NMR study indicating that the Ca–Mg cation mixing may not be entirely random along the MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join [Allwardt and Stebbins 2004].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette différence de comportement entre Mg et Ca est corroborée par une étude de RMN de ¹⁷O indiquant que le mélange de cations Ca–Mg peut ne pas être entièrement aléatoire le long du joint MgSiO₃-CaSiO₃ [Allwardt et Stebbins 2004].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="239">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, the Ca–Mg ordering is small compared to other cation mixing that associates cations having larger differences in charge and radius [Cormier etal. 2010].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, l'arrangement ordonné Ca–Mg est faible par rapport à d'autres mélanges de cations qui associent des cations présentant des différences de charge et de rayon plus importantes [Cormier etal. 2010].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="240">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The increase in Ca and Mg CNs in the liquids is associated with higher proportions of BO in the first coordination shell but the preferential association of BO around Ca is preserved.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'augmentation des NC de Ca et Mg dans les liquides est associée à des proportions plus élevées de OP dans la première couche de coordination, mais l'association préférentielle de OP autour de Ca est préservée.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="241">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The connection of cations with the silicate network can be further probed from the Si–Mg and Si–Ca PPDFs (Figure5 and Supplementary FigureS7c,d).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La connexion des cations avec le réseau silicaté peut être sondée plus en détail à partir des PPDF Si–Mg et Si–Ca (figure5 et figure supplémentaire S7c, d).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="242">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the Si–Mg PPDFs, the first peak is at 3.2Å in glasses and at 3.3Å in liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les PPDF de Si–Mg, le premier pic est à 3.2Å dans les verres et à 3.3Å dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="243">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The shift is small but apparent (Supplementary FigureS7c).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le décalage est faible mais apparent (figure supplémentaire S7c).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="244">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These distances determined from the EPSR fits mainly indicate corner-sharing polyhedra.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces distances déterminées à partir des ajustements EPSR indiquent principalement des polyèdres partageants des sommets.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="245">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Indeed, very few examples of edge-sharing between MgO₄ and SiO₄ in EPSR models give Si–Mg distances at 2.7–2.9Å.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, quelques exemples de partage d'arêtes entre MgO₄ et SiO₄ dans les modèles EPSR donnent des distances Si–Mg à 2.7–2.9 Å.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="246">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the Mg–Si PPDFs in Figure12a (see also Supplementary FigureS8a), a shoulder at 2.75Å is discernible in the first peak at 3.28Å and correspond to edge-sharing between SiO₄ tetrahedra and ^([5])Mg and ^([6])Mg sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les PPDF Mg–Si de la figure12a (voir également la figure supplémentaire S8a), un épaulement à 2.75 Å est perceptible dans le premier pic à 3.28 Å et correspond au partage d'arêtes entre les tétraèdres SiO₄ et les sites ^([5])Mg et ^([6])Mg.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="247">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is also consistent with a recent DFT numerical study of Ca–Mg aluminosilicate glasses [Gong etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceci est également cohérent avec une étude numérique récente par DFT (sigle pour Density Functional Theory) sur les verres d'aluminosilicate Ca–Mg [Gong etal. 2021].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="248">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The intensity at the position of edge-sharing is higher in liquids while the corner-sharing intensity dominates in glasses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'intensité à la position correspondant au partage d’arêtes est plus élevée dans les liquides tandis que dans les verres l'intensité correspondant au partage des sommets domine.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="249">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Similarly in Mg–Mg PPDFs (Figure12c and Supplementary FigureS8c), the intensity at edge-sharing position between Mg polyhedra is higher in glasses than in liquids, and this latter shows higher intensities at Mg–Mg face-sharing and corner-sharing positions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De même, dans les PPDF Mg–Mg (figure12c et figure supplémentaire S8c), l'intensité correspondant au partage d’arêtes entre les polyèdres de Mg est plus élevée dans les verres que dans les liquides, et ces derniers montrent des intensités plus élevées aux niveaux des partages de Mg–Mg par faces et par sommets.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="250">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This variation in Mg–Si and Mg–Mg PPDFS indicate less variability in glasses compared to liquids with mainly Mg–Si corner-sharing and Mg–Mg edge-sharing at ambient temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette variation dans les PPDF Mg–Si et Mg–Mg indique une variabilité moindre dans les verres par rapport aux liquides avec principalement le partage des sommets Mg–Si et le partage des arêtes Mg–Mg à température ambiante.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="251">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Two distinct peaks are observed in the Ca–Si PPDF of glasses (Figure12b and Supplementary FigureS8b) at 2.95Å and 3.50Å that are assigned to edge- and corner-sharing connectivity between SiO₄ tetrahedra and Ca polyhedra, respectively [Gong etal. 2021], with dominantly corner-sharing linkages.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Deux pics distincts sont observés dans le PPDF Ca–Si des verres (figure12b et figure supplémentaire S8b) à 2.95Å et 3.50Å qui sont attribués à la connexion par partage d'arêtes et de sommets respectivement entre les tétraèdres SiO₄ et les polyèdres Ca, [Gong etal. 2021], avec une dominance de liaisons par partage des sommets.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="252">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The intensity corresponding to Si–Ca edge-sharing decrease with temperature, a behavior dissimilar to Si–Mg linkages.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'intensité correspondant au partage d'arêtes Si–Ca décroît avec la température, un comportement différent des liaisons Si–Mg.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="253">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The Ca–Ca PPDFs show a small peak at 2.60Å that decreases with less CaO content, indicating a significant proportion of Ca–Ca face-sharing in CMS50.00 glass (Figure12e and Supplementary FigureS8e).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les PPDF Ca–Ca montrent un petit pic à 2.60Å qui diminue avec moins de teneur en CaO, ce qui indique une proportion significative de partage des faces Ca–Ca dans le verre CMS50.00 (figure12e et figure supplémentaire S8e).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="254">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Such face-sharing connections are characteristic features of Ca-rich glasses as they disappear in the corresponding liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De telles liaisons par partage des faces sont caractéristiques des verres riches en Ca car elles disparaissent dans les liquides correspondants.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="255">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The large fraction of Ca–Ca face-sharing in the glass suggests nano-heterogeneities and Ca clustering [Benmore etal. 2010], which can result from partial liquid–liquid phase separation upon cooling [Benmore etal. 2020].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La grande proportion de partage de face Ca–Ca dans le verre suggère des nano-hétérogénéités et un regroupement de Ca [Benmore etal. 2010], qui peuvent résulter d'une séparation de phase liquide-liquide partielle lors du refroidissement [Benmore etal. 2020].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="256">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Upon cooling, a decrease in the population of Ca–Ca corner-sharing and an increase in Ca–Ca edge-sharing were previously suggested based on analysis of bond angle distributions in MD simulations of CaSiO₃ glass/melt [Benmore etal. 2010].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Lors du refroidissement, une diminution de la population de Ca–Ca partageant des sommets et une augmentation de Ca–Ca partageant des arêtes ont été précédemment suggérées sur la base de l'analyse des distributions des angles de liaison dans des simulations DM de verre/liquide CaSiO₃ [Benmore etal. 2010].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="257">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This result is confirmed in the present investigation based on PPDFs analysis in all glasses and this trend is observed for both Ca–Ca and Ca–Mg linkages (Ca–Mg corner-sharing position has lower intensities and Ca–Mg edge-sharing position has higher intensities with a temperature decrease).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce résultat est confirmé dans la présente étude basée sur l'analyse des PPDF de tous les verres et cette tendance est observée pour les liaisons Ca–Ca et Ca–Mg (Ca–Mg a des intensités plus faibles au niveau du partage des sommets et Ca–Mg a des intensités plus élevées au niveau du partage des arêtes avec une diminution de la température).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="258">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For the intermediate compositions, the Ca–Mg contribution (Figure12d) is well-defined, in agreement with a mixing between the two different cations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour les compositions intermédiaires, la contribution Ca–Mg (figure12d) est bien définie, en accord avec un mélange entre les deux cations différents.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="259">
            <prop type="paragraph">56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The increasing fraction of edge-shared Ca/Mg polyhedra with decreasing temperature results in increasing the polymerization and Ca/Mg clustering. The Ca/Mg aggregation increases more rapidly near the glass transition temperature, which can partly explain the steep continuous rise in viscosity in the supercooled liquid as T_(g) is approached [Benmore etal. 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La proportion croissante de polyèdres Ca/Mg partageant des arêtes avec une température décroissante entraîne une augmentation de la polymérisation et du regroupement Ca/Mg. L'agrégation Ca/Mg augmente plus rapidement au voisinage de la température de transition vitreuse, ce qui peut expliquer en partie la forte augmentation continue de la viscosité dans le liquide surfondu à l'approche de la T_(g) [Benmore etal. 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="260">
            <prop type="paragraph">57</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5.6. Structure of silicate melts</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5.6. Structure des liquides silicatés</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="261">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Glasses differ from melts by the configurational contributions that appear in thermodynamic properties above T_(g) and that imply a substantial change in structure with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les verres diffèrent des liquides en raison des contributions configurationnelles qui apparaissent dans les propriétés thermodynamiques au-dessus de T_(g) et qui impliquent un changement substantiel de la structure avec la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="262">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In silicate glasses/melts, a change in Q^(n) distribution has been inferred from Raman and NMR studies, indicating that the disproportionation reaction 2Q^(n) ⇄ Q^(n−1) + Q^(n+1) is displaced to the right in melts [Mysen and Frantz 1993, Stebbins 1995].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les verres/liquides silicatés, un changement dans la distribution de Q^(n) a été déduit des études de Raman et de RMN, indiquant que la réaction de dismutation 2Q^(n) ⇄ Q^(n−1) + Q^(n+1) est décalée vers la droite dans les liquides [Mysen et Frantz 1993, Stebbins 1995].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="263">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Though this contribution is important, the resulting heat capacity cannot account completely for the measured configurational heat capacity, indicating the occurrence of other structural modifications [Stebbins 2008].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Bien que cette contribution soit importante, la capacité thermique résultante ne peut pas complètement expliquer la capacité thermique configurationnelle mesurée, indiquant l'apparition d'autres modifications structurales [Stebbins 2008].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="264">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the EPSR models, changes in Q^(n) distribution is small (less Q³ and more Q¹ and Q⁰ at high temperature).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les modèles EPSR, les changements dans la distribution de Q^(n) sont faibles (moins de Q³ et plus de Q¹ et de Q⁰ à haute température).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="265">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Additional temperature-induced structural changes can be various: conformational relaxation of the network at IRO, site thermal expansion, coordination change or local distortion [Calas etal. 2006, Henderson etal. 2006, Majérus etal. 2004].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les changements structuraux induits par la température peuvent être divers: relaxation conformationnelle du réseau couvrant l’ordre à moyenne distance, dilatation thermique du site, changement de coordinence ou distorsion locale [Calas etal. 2006, Henderson etal. 2006, Majérus etal. 2004].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="266">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For the CMS system, the present analysis points to a considerable disordering around Mg and Ca cations at both short and medium range scale, as both cations in melts tend to enter larger sites with a change in the connection between polyhedra (Figures8 and12).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour le système CMS, la présente analyse met en évidence un désordre considérable autour des cations Mg et Ca à la fois à courte et à moyenne échelle, car dans les liquides, les deux cations ont tendance à entrer dans des sites plus grands avec un changement dans la connexion entre les polyèdres (figures8 et12).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="267">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The enhanced cation mobility with temperature allows cations to explore energetically less favorable sites with higher coordination that favors an entropy increase [de Ligny and Westrum 1996].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>À haute température, la mobilité accrue des cations leur permet d'explorer des sites énergétiquement moins favorables avec une coordinence plus élevée qui favorise une augmentation de l'entropie [de Ligny et Westrum 1996].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="268">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Our results indicate that the glass/melt structures of the two end members present significant differences though the well-defined Mg–Ca PPDFs is indicative of substantial mixing between the two sub-structures.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nos résultats indiquent que les structures des verres/liquides des deux membres terminaux présentent des différences significatives bien que les PPDF de Mg–Ca bien définis indiquent un mélange substantiel entre les deux sous-structures.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="269">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The average CN is different between Mg and Ca with high coordinated sites for Ca and the increase in temperature yields the cations to be localized in further more coordinated sites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le NC moyen est différent entre Mg et Ca avec des sites à coordinence élevées pour Ca et l'augmentation de la température entraîne une localisation des cations dans des sites à coordinence encore plus élevée.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="270">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As a likely consequence of the larger cationic polyhedra, major modifications with temperature are seen in the cation–cation or cation–silicon linkages to accommodate the random packing of distinct MgO_(x) and CaO_(x) polyhedra.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En conséquence probable des polyèdres cationiques plus grands, des modifications majeures sont observées, en fonction de la température, dans les liaisons cation–cation ou cation-silicium pour tenir compte de l'empilement aléatoire de polyèdres MgO_(x) et CaO_(x) distincts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="271">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The greater diversity of connections explains an increase of the configurational entropy in the liquids.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La plus grande diversité des connexions explique une augmentation de l'entropie configurationnelle dans les liquides.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="272">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The structural organization evolves continuously with compositions between the two end members and, thereby, the changes are compatible with the expected ideal Ca/Mg mixing [Neuville and Richet 1991].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'organisation structurale évolue continuellement en fonction de la composition atomique entre les deux membres terminaux et, de ce fait, les changements sont compatibles avec le mélange idéal Ca/Mg attendu [Neuville et Richet 1991].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="273">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Dynamic processes such as viscous flow are controlled by the mechanism of Si–O bond breaking occurring during Q^(n)-species exchange, as proposed for SiO₂-rich silicate liquids [Farnan and Stebbins 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les processus dynamiques tels que l'écoulement laminaire sont contrôlés par le mécanisme de rupture des liaisons Si–O survenant lors de l'échange d'espèces Q^(n), comme proposé pour les liquides silicatés riches en SiO₂ [Farnan et Stebbins 1994].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="274">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In more depolymerized liquids, it was suggested that Ca–O and Mg–O bond breaking and cation mobility could significantly participate to structural relaxation and flow processes [Nasikas etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les liquides davantage dépolymérisés, il a été suggéré que la rupture des liaisons Ca–O et Mg–O et la mobilité des cations pourraient participer de manière significative aux processus de relaxation structurale et d'écoulement [Nasikas etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="275">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Indeed, a correlation between Mg motions and viscosity was confirmed in a high-temperature NMR study [George and Stebbins 1998], which indicates that this cation is strongly bounded to the silicate network.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, une corrélation entre les mouvements de Mg et la viscosité a été confirmée dans une étude RMN à haute température [George et Stebbins 1998], ce qui indique que ce cation est fortement lié au réseau silicaté.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="276">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The cationic dynamics could be further enhanced by the increase entropy in the liquids resulting from diverse MgO_(x) and CaO_(x) connections.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La dynamique cationique pourrait être encore renforcée par l'augmentation de l'entropie dans les liquides résultant de diverses connexions MgO_(x) et CaO_(x).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="277">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>No studies have investigated in details the relaxation near T_(g) and it is then an open question if a decoupling behavior occurs as in aluminosilicate systems [Gruener etal. 2001] and if there is a different decoupling behavior between Mg and Ca containing systems.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Aucune étude n'a étudié en détail la relaxation près de T_(g) et la question reste ouverte de savoir si un comportement de découplage se produit comme dans les systèmes aluminosilicates [Gruener etal. 2001] et s'il existe un comportement de découplage différent entre les systèmes contenant du Mg et du Ca.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="278">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>When approaching the glass transition, it has been demonstrated that CaO_(x) edge-shared polyhedra tend to cluster within the silicate network of CaSiO₃ [Benmore etal. 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>À l'approche de la transition vitreuse, il a été démontré que les polyèdres à arêtes partagées CaO_(x) ont tendance à se regrouper dans le réseau silicaté de CaSiO₃ [Benmore etal. 2010, Skinner etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="279">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Similar increasing cationic heterogeneities are suggested in the present study for the complete MgSiO₃–CaSiO₃ join.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La présente étude suggère des hétérogénéités cationiques croissantes similaires pour l'ensemble du joint MgSiO₃-CaSiO₃.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="280">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The increase in IRO near T_(g) precludes the liquid to find a minimum basin corresponding to the crystal structure in its potential energy landscape.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'augmentation de l’ordre à moyenne distance proche de T_(g) empêche le liquide de trouver un bassin minimum correspondant à la structure cristalline dans son paysage d'énergie potentielle.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="281">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Such heterogeneities related to the Mg/Ca organization could also limit cation mobility, increase the viscosity and thereby favor glass formation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De telles hétérogénéités liées à l'organisation Mg/Ca pourraient également limiter la mobilité des cations, augmenter la viscosité et favoriser ainsi la formation du verre.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="282">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The presence of intrinsic heterogeneities in the glass structure has been reported recently in many aluminosilicate systems for cation mixing (Na–K aluminosilicate [Le Losq etal. 2017, Le Losq and Neuville 2013]; Ca–Mg aluminosilicate [Allu etal. 2018] and their spatial extent can be affected by the quenching rate [Dargaud etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La présence d'hétérogénéités intrinsèques dans la structure du verre a été rapportée récemment dans de nombreux systèmes aluminosilicates présentant un mélange de cations (aluminosilicate Na–K [Le Losq etal. 2017, Le Losq et Neuville 2013]; aluminosilicate de Ca–Mg [Allu etal. 2018] et leur étendue spatiale peut être affectée par la vitesse de trempe [Dargaud etal. 2012].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="283">
            <prop type="paragraph">62</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>6. Conclusions</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>6. Conclusions</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="284">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The structure of a series of CaSiO₃–MgSiO₃ glasses and melts have been investigated by neutron and XRD using aerodynamic levitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On a étudié la structure d'une série de verres et de liquides CaSiO₃–MgSiO₃ par diffraction des neutrons et des rayons X en utilisant la lévitation aérodynamique.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="285">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Experimental data have been fitted using the EPSR method to obtain atomistic models over the short and medium range order.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des données expérimentales ont été ajustées en utilisant la méthode EPSR pour obtenir des modèles atomistiques à petite et moyenne échelle.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="286">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The coordination of Mg and Ca has been determined at ambient and high temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La coordinence de Mg et de Ca a été déterminée à température ambiante et à haute température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="287">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Results show sites with higher coordination in the liquids compared to those in the glasses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les résultats révèlent des sites avec une coordinence plus élevée dans les liquides que dans les verres.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="288">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This CN evolution implies modifications of the connection between Ca and Mg polyhedra and the connection of Ca and Mg polyhedra with SiO₄ tetrahedra.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette évolution du NC implique des modifications de la connexion entre les polyèdres Ca et Mg et la connexion des polyèdres Ca et Mg avec les tétraèdres SiO4.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="289">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Specifically, decreasing the temperature increases the proportion of Si–(Mg,Ca) corner-sharing, Si–Ca edge-sharing, (Mg,Ca)–(Mg,Ca) face- and edge-sharing and decreases the proportion of (Mg,Ca)–(Mg,Ca) corner-sharing.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Plus précisément, la diminution de la température augmente la proportion de sommets partagés pour Si–(Mg,Ca), d'arêtes partagés pour Si–Ca, de faces partagées pour (Mg,Ca)–(Mg,Ca) et d'arêtes partagées pour (Mg,Ca) et diminue la proportion de sommets partagés pour (Mg,Ca)–(Mg,Ca).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="290">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These changes suggest cationic heterogeneities along the glass series.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces changements suggèrent des hétérogénéités cationiques sur l'ensemble de la série de verres.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="291">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Ca-rich compositions present Ca–Ca face-sharing and Ca is more connected to BO than Mg indicating that Ca²⁺ cations are slightly preferentially localized in polymerized silicate regions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les compositions riches en Ca présentent un partage de faces Ca–Ca et Ca est plus lié à OP que Mg, ce qui indique que les cations Ca²⁺ sont légèrement localisés de manière préférentielle dans les régions de silicate polymérisé.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="292">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The findings of these modifications at IRO bring a deeper understanding of the configurational changes with temperature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les résultats de ces modifications de l’ordre à moyenne distance permettent de mieux comprendre les changements de configuration en fonction de la température.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="293">
            <prop type="paragraph">64</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Conflicts of interest</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Conflits d’intérêts</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="294">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les auteurs n'ont aucun conflit d'intérêts à déclarer.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>