<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for TAL-2020-61_2_ID=construction-d_E2_80_99un-corpus-parall_C3_A8le-_C3_A0-partir-de-corpus-comparables-pour-la-simplification-de. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2020-61_2_ID=construction-d_E2_80_99un-corpus-parall_C3_A8le-_C3_A0-partir-de-corpus-comparables-pour-la-simplification-de</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La simplification automatique a pour objectif de produire une version de textes plus facile à comprendre à destination d’un public identifié.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The purpose of automatic simplification is to create version of texts which is easier to understand for a given targeted population.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le plus souvent, le lexique et les règles de simplification sont acquis à partir de corpus parallèles.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Usually, lexicon and rules required for the simplification are acquired from parallel corpora.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Comme de tels corpus n’existent pas en français, nous proposons des méthodes pour les construire à partir de corpus comparables.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Since such corpora are not available for French, we propose methods for their creation from comparable corpora.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Notre méthode repose sur une étape de filtrage, destinée à ne garder que les meilleures phrases candidates à l’alignement, et une étape d’alignement considérée comme un problème de catégorisation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Our method relies on filtering step, which purpose is to keep the best sentence candidates for alignment, and alignment step considered as categorization problem.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il s’agit de décider si une paire de phrases est alignable ou non.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The aim is to decide whether a pair of sentences is alignable or not.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous exploitons différents types de descripteurs (essentiellement basés sur le lexique et les corpus) et obtenons jusqu’à 0,97 de F-mesure avec les données équilibrées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We exploit different types of features (mainly issued from lexicon and corpora) and get up to 0.97 F-measure with balanced data.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>