<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2017PSLEE039. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2017PSLEE039</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse se propose d'étudier la grammaticalisation, processus d'évolution linguistique par lequel les éléments fonctionnels de la langue se trouvent remplacés au cours du temps par des mots ou des constructions de contenu, c'est-à-dire servant à désigner des entités plus concrètes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This work aims to study grammaticalization, the process by which the functional items of a language come to be replaced with time by content words or constructions, usually providing a more substantial meaning.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La grammaticalisation est donc un cas particulier de remplacement sémantique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Grammaticalization is therefore a particular type of semantic replacement.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Or, la langue faisant l'objet d'un consensus social bien établi, il semble que le changement sémantique s'effectue à contre-courant de la bonne efficacité de la communication ;</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, language emerges as a social consensus, so that it would seem that semantic change is at odds with the proper working of communication.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>pourtant, il est attesté dans toutes les langues, toutes les époques et, comme le montre la grammaticalisation, toutes les catégories linguistiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Despite of this, the phenomenon is attested in all languages, at all times, and pervades all linguistic categories, as the very existence of grammaticalization shows.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces profils de fréquence sont extraits de la base de données de Frantext, qui permet de couvrir une période de sept siècles.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These frequencies of use are extracted from the textual database Frantext, which covers a period of seven centuries.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les distributions statistiques des observables décrivant ces deux phénomènes sont obtenues et quantifiées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The statistical distribution of the different observables related to these two phenomenal features are extracted.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un modèle de marche aléatoire est ensuite proposé reproduisant ces deux phénomènes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A random walk model is then proposed to account for this two-sided frequency pattern.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La latence s'y trouve expliquée comme un phénomène critique, au voisinage d'une bifurcation point-col.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The latency period appears as a critical phenomenon in the vicinity of a saddle-node bifurcation, and quantitatively matches its empirical counter-part.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une extension de ce modèle articulant l'organisation du réseau sémantique et les formes possibles de l'évolution est ensuite discutée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Finally, an extension of the model is sketched, in which the relationship between the structure of the semantic network and the outcome of the evolution could be discussed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>