<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2015PA100180. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2015PA100180</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Considéré comme un historien qui sacrifie rigueur et exactitude à son souci de la rhétorique, Quinte-Curce jouit, et avec lui son histoire « romancée », d’une réputation en demi-teinte.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Considered a historian who sacrifices his rigor and accuracy for the sake of rhetoric, Curtius Rufus enjoys, and with him his “fictionalized” history as well, a halftone reputation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’historien se livre alors à une véritable entreprise de démystification qui touche la nature même de cet Orient merveilleux, la fortune providentielle dont se réclame le Macédonien et même le langage.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The historian attempts to debunk the very nature of this wonderful East, the providential fortune claimed by Macedonian, and even language.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sont ainsi condamnés la quête effrénée de gloire que poursuit le roi, et son rêve de divinisation : l’Orient est synonyme de renversement généralisé des normes et des valeurs, la fortune une illusion conduisant à un sentiment d’impunité.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The unbridled quest for glory pursued by the king and his dream of deification are here condemned: the East stands for a general inversion of norms and values, and fortune becomes an illusion leading to a feeling of impunity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En filigrane, il propose aussi un idéal du pouvoir qui repose essentiellement sur l’équilibre et sur la responsabilité du prince.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Implicitly, it also proposes an ideal of power mainly based on balance and on the responsibility of the prince.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Par là, il interroge, au regard des réalités politiques de son temps, la pertinence d’un mythe central dans l’imaginaire politique romain et dont l’ombre plane sur tous les ambitieux, à commencer par les empereurs ou les candidats à l’Empire.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The historian questions the relevance of a central myth of the Roman political imagination in the political context of the times, whose shadow looms over all ambitious men, starting with emperors or candidates for the Empire.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Son récit bien mené incite donc à une réflexion réelle sur l’exercice du pouvoir, ses enjeux et ses limites.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>His well crafted narrative is a call for a reflection on the actual exercise of power, its challenges and limitations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>