<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2012ECDN0019. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2012ECDN0019</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'idée ainsi défendue est que de tels outils permettraient l'automatisation partielle des processus d'analyse des besoins et de synthèse des concepts de solution.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This thesis suggests the use of tools from the disciplines of Computational Linguistics and Knowledge Representation with the idea that such tools would enable the partial automation of two processes of Conceptual Design: the analysis of Requirements and the synthesis of concepts of solution.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le point de vue sur le développement conceptuel développé dans cette recherche est basé sur les méthodologies de développement systématique développées dans la littérature.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The viewpoint on Conceptual Design developed in this research is based on the systematic methodologies developed in the literature.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'évolution de ces méthodologies apporte une description précise des tâches à réaliser par l'équipe de conception afin de parvenir à un produit efficace et performant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The evolution of these methodologies provided precise description of the tasks to be achieved by the designing team in order to achieve successful design.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Par conséquent, l'argument de cette thèse est qu'il est possible de créer des modèles informatiques de certaines de ces tâches afin d'assister l’équipe de conception dans la reformulation du problème de conception ainsi que dans l'exploration de l'espace de conception.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Therefore, the argument of this thesis is that it is possible to create computer models of some of these tasks in order to partially automate the refinement of the design problem and the exploration of the design space.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En ingénierie des exigences, la définition des besoins consiste à identifier les besoins des divers intervenants puis à les formaliser en spécifications du produit.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In Requirements Engineering, the definition of requirements consists in identifying the needs of various stakeholders and formalizing it into design specifications.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La difficulté est alors que ces personnes expriment leurs besoins avec des niveaux de clarté et des champs lexicaux différents.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>During this task, designers face the problem of having to deal with individuals from different expertise, expressing their needs with different levels of clarity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces travaux de recherche aborde la question du traitement des exigences exprimées en langage naturel (dans ce cas en anglais).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This research tackles this issue with requirements expressed in natural language (in this case in English).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'analyse de ces besoins est réalisée à différents niveaux linguistiques : lexicaux, syntaxiques et sémantiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The analysis of needs is realised from different linguistic levels: lexical, syntactic and semantic.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le niveau lexical traite de la signification des mots du langage.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The lexical level deals with the meaning of words of a language.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le niveau sémantique est l’étude du sens précis d’utilsation des mots dans leur contexte.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The semantic level aims at finding about the specific meaning of words in the context of a sentence.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette recherche fait un usage intensif d'un atlas sémantique basé sur le concept mathématique de clique provenant de la théorie des graphes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This research makes extensive use of a semantic atlas based on the concept of clique from graph theory.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce concept permet le calcul de distances entre un mot et ses synonymes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Such concept enables the computation of distances between a word and its synonyms.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En outre, une méthodologie et une métrique de similitude ont été définies pour clarifier les exigences aux niveaux syntaxique, lexical et sémantique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Additionally, a methodology and a metric of similarity was defined for clarifying requirements at syntactic, lexical and semantic levels.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="14">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette méthodologie intègre des outils de collaborateurs de recherche.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This methodology integrates tools from research collaborators.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="15">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour le processus de synthèse, une représentation numérique des concepts de connaissance nécessaires à la création de solutions de préconception a été développée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the synthesis process, a Knowledge Representation of the necessary concepts for enabling computers to create concepts of solution was developed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>