<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2017LORR0080. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2017LORR0080</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans de nombreux domaines, les données peuvent être de grande dimension.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In many application areas, data elements can be high-dimensional.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ça pose le problème de la réduction de dimension.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This raises the problem of dimensionality reduction.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les techniques de réduction de dimension peuvent être classées en fonction de leur but : techniques pour la représentation optimale et techniques pour la classification, ainsi qu'en fonction de leur stratégie : la sélection et l'extraction des caractéristiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The dimensionality reduction techniques can be classified based on their aim: dimensionality reduction for optimal data representation and dimensionality reduction for classification, as well as based on the adopted strategy: feature selection and feature extraction.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'ensemble des caractéristiques résultant des méthodes d'extraction est non interprétable.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The set of features resulting from feature extraction methods is usually uninterpretable.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ainsi, la première problématique scientifique de la thèse est comment extraire des caractéristiques latentes interprétables ?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Thereby, the first scientific problematic of the thesis is how to extract interpretable latent features?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La réduction de dimension pour la classification vise à améliorer la puissance de classification du sous-ensemble sélectionné.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The dimensionality reduction for classification aims to enhance the classification power of the selected subset of features.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous voyons le développement de la tâche de classification comme la tâche d'identification des facteurs déclencheurs, c'est-à-dire des facteurs qui peuvent influencer le transfert d'éléments de données d'une classe à l'autre.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We see the development of the task of classification as the task of trigger factors identification that is identification of those factors that can influence the transfer of data elements from one class to another.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La deuxième problématique scientifique de cette thèse est comment identifier automatiquement ces facteurs déclencheurs ?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The second scientific problematic of this thesis is how to automatically identify these trigger factors?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous visons à résoudre les deux problématiques scientifiques dans le domaine d'application des systèmes de recommandation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We aim at solving both scientific problematics within the recommender systems application domain.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous proposons d'interpréter les caractéristiques latentes de systèmes de recommandation basés sur la factorisation de matrices comme des utilisateurs réels.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We propose to interpret latent features for the matrix factorization-based recommender systems as real users.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous concevons un algorithme d'identification automatique des facteurs déclencheurs basé sur les concepts d'analyse par contraste.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We design an algorithm for automatic identification of trigger factors based on the concepts of contrast analysis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Au travers d'expérimentations, nous montrons que les motifs définis peuvent être considérés comme des facteurs déclencheurs</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Through experimental results, we show that the defined patterns indeed can be considered as trigger factors</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>