<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2016COMP2254. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2016COMP2254</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La production documentaire en contexte professionnel entraîne généralement un processus de révision dans lequel les documents doivent être relus avant validation et publication.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Documentary production in a professional context often involves a revising process in which documents need to be proofread before validation and publication.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette tâche importante fait face à de nouvelles difficultés avec le numérique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This important task faces new challenges when dealing with digital documents.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En tant que technologie d'écriture numérique avancée, les chaînes éditoriales XML sont un cadre pertinent pour l'étude de la relecture de documents numériques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As an advanced digital writing technology, XML publishing chains are a relevant framework for studying proofreading of digital documents.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une partie des propositions faites dans ce mémoire a mené à la réalisation de prototypes ayant été expérimentés dans des situations d'usage des chaînes éditoriales Scenari en contexte pédagogique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Part of the contribution presented here has led to the development of prototypes that have been experimented in the use of Scenari publishing chains in a pedagogical context.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces prototypes s'appuient sur des formes linéaires de relecture permettant notamment la comparaison de deux versions du document en se basant sur un algorithme de différentiel.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These prototypes rely on linear proofreading views allowing in particular the comparison between two versions of the document based on a diff algorithm.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>