<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2014CLF20016. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2014CLF20016</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette recherche s’intéresse à l’usage de deux variables du français traditionnellement décrites comme phonologiques : la liaison et l’élision du schwa.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This study deals with the usage of two French linguistic variables liaison and elision, which are traditionally described as phonological variables.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces variables sont étudiées au cours d’interactions naturelles entre trois enfants et leurs parents respectifs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>They are studied during natural interactions between three children and their parents.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Plus précisément, l’objectif de cette thèse est de décrire les particularités du discours adressé à l’enfant (DAE) au niveau de l’usage des variables phonologiques et de mesurer leur impact sur l’émergence de la production de ces mêmes variables chez l’enfant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>More precisely, the aim of this thesis is to describe the specificities of the child directed speech (CDS) concerning the usage of liaison and elision to measure their impact on the emergence of these phonological variables in the speech of the children.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Après la présentation du cadre théorique d’analyse et de la méthodologie de recueil, de structuration et d’analyse des données, le travail de recherche s’organise en trois parties.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>After the presentation of the theoretical context of the study (Usage-Based Models and Construction Grammar) and the methodology used to collect, structure, and analyse the data, the research is divided into three analysis sections.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La première étude basée sur corpus, descriptive, a deux principaux objectifs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The aim of the first corpus based study, a descriptive one, is twofold.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans un premier temps, il s’agit de mesurer à quelle variation les jeunes enfants sont exposés au domicile familial.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The first objective is to describe the variation to which children are exposed at home.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ensuite, le but est de confronter les résultats des études précédentes sur l’acquisition de la liaison, principalement obtenus à partir de tâches expérimentales, à des données issues de corpus denses d’interactions parent-enfant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A second objective is to compare the results of previous studies on liaison acquisition, obtained mainly from experimental tasks, with data extracted from dense corpora collected during natural interactions between the children and their parents.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette étude a notamment permis de relever l’influence de facteurs liés à l’usage, comme la fréquence, sur l’emploi des variables phonologiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In particular, this study shows that usage factors, including the frequency of items, influence the production of phonological variables.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La seconde étude se focalise sur les caractéristiques du DAE.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The second study focuses on the specificities of CDS.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les résultats présentés démontrent notamment que l’usage des variables phonologiques est modulé en DAE, et ce essentiellement à un stade précoce.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The results show that the usage of phonological variables is modulated in CDS, essentially at an early stage of language acquisition.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette modulation s’atténue ensuite au cours du développement linguistique des jeunes sujets.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, this modulation attenuates during the child’s development.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La dernière étude de ce travail de recherche permet de mettre en relation les productions enfantines et parentales.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The aim of the third study is to connect parent’s productions and children’s productions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il apparaît que le développement de la variation phonologique va dans le sens des hypothèses émises par les modèles basés sur l’usage : la variation phonologique est à un stade précoce mémorisée à l’intérieur de constructions spécifiques, particulièrement fréquentes et saillantes dans le DAE.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It appears that the results concerning the development of phonological variation are in step with the assumptions provided by the usage-based models: at an early stage, the variation is memorized into specific constructions, particularly salient and frequent in CDS.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>