<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en" srclang="FR" tgtlang="EN" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2024-11-15" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for MERSENNE-mersenne14. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>mersenne14</docid>
        <url_src>https://comptes-rendus.academie-sciences.fr/chimie/articles/fr/10.5802/crchim.179/</url_src>
        <url_tgt>https://comptes-rendus.academie-sciences.fr/chimie/articles/10.5802/crchim.179-en/</url_tgt>
        <author>Hervé This</author>
        <title_en>Louis Pasteur, from physical chemistry to biology</title_en>
        <title_fr>Louis Pasteur: de la physico-chimie à la biologie</title_fr>
        <volume>CRCHIM, 2022, Volume 25, Pasteur</volume>
        <translator>Catherine W.</translator>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <prop type="paragraph">1</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Louis Pasteur: de la physico-chimie à la biologie</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Louis Pasteur, from physical chemistry to biology</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Louis Pasteur commença ses travaux de recherche scientifique par des études de cristallographie, qui le conduisirent à distinguer différentes formes d’acides tartriques et de tartrates.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Louis Pasteur began his scientific research with crystallographic studies, which led him to distinguish different forms of tartaric acids and tartarates.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sa nomination à l’université de Lille, dans un environnement industriel qui lui fit étudier les alcools amyliques, contribua à réorienter son activité scientifique, mais il restait surtout mu par son hypothèse selon laquelle la «dissymétrie optique» était l’apanage du vivant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>His appointment to the University of Lille, in an industrial environment that led him to study amyl alcohols, helped to reorient his scientific activity, but he remained mainly driven by his hypothesis that “molecular dissymmetry” was the prerogative of the living.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <prop type="paragraph">2</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Butant sur l’inactivité optique de certains composés organiques, il abandonna progressivement une recherche pour laquelle manquaient des concepts chimiques qui ne furent élaborés que plus tard, par d’autres, pour étudier des fermentations, avant d’aller explorer les micro-organismes qui causaient ces dernières.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Stumbling on the optical inactivity of certain organic compounds, he progressively abandoned a research for which chemical concepts were missing and which were only elaborated later, by others, to study fermentation, before going to explore the micro-organisms which caused them.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <prop type="paragraph">3</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pourquoi Louis Pasteur (1822–1895) est-il passé de ses études initiales de cristallographie, mesurant la rotation du plan de polarisation de la lumière après la traversée de cristaux ou de solutions, aux explorations des fermentations, qui l’ont ensuite conduit aux études de microbiologie? Dans un article précédent[1], les travaux de Pasteur sur le dédoublement des acides tartriques et des tartrates ont été analysés à partir de tous ses articles scientifiques (initiaux, et comparés aux rééditions ultérieures, notamment dans des recueils de ses œuvres): il a été montré comment Pasteur était l’héritier scientifique direct de Jean-Baptiste Biot (1774–1862) et d’Auguste Laurent (1807–1853), et comment il avait bénéficié des idées fondatrices de ce dernier, qui était son «tuteur» dans le laboratoire d’Antoine-Jérôme Balard (1802–1876).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Why did Louis Pasteur (1822–1895) move away from his initial studies of crystallography, measuring the rotation of the plane of polarisation of light after crossing crystals or solutions, to explorations of fermentation, which then led him to study microbiology? In a previous article [1], Pasteur's research on the doubling of tartaric acids and tartrates were analysed based on the entirety of his scientific articles (initial versions, also compared with later editions, notably in collections of his works). It was shown how Pasteur was the direct scientific heir of Jean-Baptiste Biot (1774–1862) and Auguste Laurent (1807-1853), and how he had benefited from the founding ideas of the latter, who was his "tutor" in the laboratory of Antoine-Jérôme Balard (1802–1876).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <prop type="paragraph">4</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans le présent texte, le projet est différent, et double: toutes les publications et notes de Pasteur, de 1848 à 1880, sont utilisées en vue d’une meilleure compréhension de la transition entre ses travaux de cristallographie et ses études des fermentations, qui marquent la fin de la période considérée dans ce texte; toutes ne sont cependant pas citées, car une telle étude a été faite par Flack[2].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the present text, the project is different, and double in scale: all of Pasteur's publications and notes from 1848 to 1880 are used for a better understanding of the transition between his crystallographic research and his studies of fermentations, which mark the end of the period considered in this text; however, not all are cited as such a study was made by Flack[2].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Est analysée ici l’évolution d’une pensée scientifique, pour un homme qui a inspiré des hagiographes tout autant que des détracteurs, certains d’entre eux oubliant que les hypothèses, idées et théories que les scientifiques utilisent opérationnellement évoluent lentement, parfois contradictoirement, à mesure que les résultats d’expérience s’ajoutent.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Here we analyse the evolution of scientific thought for a man who has inspired hagiographers as well as detractors, some of them forgetting that the hypotheses, ideas, and theories that scientists use operationally evolve slowly, sometimes contradictorily, as the results of experiments are added.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’histoire de cette évolution et celle des progrès de la théorie atomique sont mises en correspondance, afin de comprendre comment Pasteur a «réussi à tracer un chemin de certitudes au travers de grandes incertitudes», ce qui, pour Debru, «est la définition même de la science expérimentale moderne»[3].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The history of this evolution and that of the progress of atomic theory are elaborated side by side in order to understand how Pasteur "succeeded in tracing a path of certainty through great uncertainties," which, for Debru, "is the very definition of modern experimental science"[3].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des citations (en italiques) sont données, dans la mesure où elles montrent les idées de Pasteur plus fidèlement que des commentaires de ses textes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Quotes (in italics) are given in cases where they show Pasteur's ideas more faithfully than the commentary of his texts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De nombreux termes utilisés par Pasteur et ses contemporains, quand ils sont cités ici, sont placés entre guillemets, afin que ne leur soit pas attribuée une acception moderne, qui serait anachronique ou indue.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Many terms used by Pasteur and his contemporaries, when quoted here, are placed in quotation marks so that they are not given a modern meaning, which would be anachronistic or undue.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <prop type="paragraph">5</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Enfin une synthèse est faite entre des hypothèses concurrentes, à propos de l’évolution des recherches de Pasteur, de la cristallographie vers la biochimie et la microbiologie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Finally, a synthesis is made between competing hypotheses about the evolution of Pasteur's research, from crystallography to biochemistry and microbiology.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ajoutons que, pour ces analyses, ne sont donnés ici que des extraits des publications les plus saillantes, car Pasteur se répète beaucoup.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We add that for these analyses, only excerpts from the most prominent publications are given here, because Pasteur repeats himself frequently.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sauf exception, les publications sont évoquées dans un ordre chronologique, afin de bien séparer les faits —établis à partir des publications essentiellement à l’Académie des sciences— et les idées données dans des textes publiés postérieurement (par Pasteur ou par ses historiens) et qui faussent évidemment l’appréciation de la pensée de Pasteur au moment où il fait ses travaux.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>With some exceptions, the publications are mentioned in chronological order, in order to clearly separate the facts —established based on publications primarily from the Académie des Sciences (French Academy of Sciences)— and the ideas given in later published texts (by Pasteur or by his historians) and which clearly distort the appreciation of Pasteur's thinking at the time when he conducted his research.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="14">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A propos des notions d’atomes et de molécules, des anachronismes ont été évités, la discussion détaillée de l’évolution des idées de Pasteur à ce propos étant effectuée dans[1];</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>With regard to notions of atoms and molecules, anachronisms are avoided, the detailed discussion of the evolution of Pasteur's ideas on this subject having been made in[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="15">
            <prop type="paragraph">6</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>toutefois des observations relatives à ces notions continueront de s’imposer quand elles permettront de mieux comprendre la pensée de Pasteur à l’époque où il fait ses travaux et de mieux percevoir les raisons de son changement d’orientation scientifique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, observations related to these concepts will continue to be necessary when they allow a better understanding of Pasteur's thinking at the time he conducted his research, and to better understand the reasons for his change in scientific orientation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="16">
            <prop type="paragraph">7</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>1. Les acides tartriques et les composés organiques</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>1. Tartaric acids and organic compounds</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="17">
            <prop type="paragraph">8</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’étude dont les résultats sont donnés ici commence avec la publication du 22 mai 1848[4], qui correspondait à l’annonce, à l’Académie des sciences, de la découverte à laquelle Pasteur se référera souvent: l’«acide racémique», découvert par l’industriel alsacien Charles Kestner (1803–1870), était un mélange de deux énantiomères (c’est la terminologie moderne pour désigner des composés dont les molécules sont images l’une de l’autre dans un miroir) de l’ «acide tartrique» (ou acide 2,3-dihydroxybutanedioïque); ces composés sont aujourd’hui désignés par (2R, 3R), ou (+), et par (2S, 3S), ou (−)[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The study whose results are given here begins with the publication of May 22, 1848[4], which corresponded to the announcement at the Académie des Sciences of the discovery to which Pasteur would often refer: "racemic acid". Discovered by the Alsatian industrialist Charles Kestner (1803-1870), racemic acid was a mixture of two enantiomers (modern term used to designate compounds whose molecules are mirror images of each other) of "tartaric acid" (or 2,3-dihydroxybutanedioic acid); these compounds are today designated by (2R, 3R), or (+), and by (2S, 3S), or (−)[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="18">
            <prop type="paragraph">9</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur était sorti de l’École normale supérieure deux ans plus tôt, et Balard l’avait accueilli dans son laboratoire, où travaillait Laurent, qui s’était mis en disponibilité de son poste de professeur de chimie de l’Université de Bordeaux[5, 6].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur had graduated from the École Normale Supérieure two years earlier, and Balard had welcomed him to his laboratory, where Laurent worked, having taken a sabbatical from his position as professor of chemistry at the University of Bordeaux[5, 6].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="19">
            <prop type="paragraph">9</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les contributions de Laurent aux travaux initiaux de Pasteur —et notamment au résultat de 1848— furent essentielles: Laurent enseigna à Pasteur à utiliser conjointement la cristallographie et la mesure de l’activité optique (c’est-à-dire la mesure de la rotation du plan de polarisation de la lumière, quand cette dernière traverse des cristaux ou des solutions).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Laurent's contributions to Pasteur's initial works —and in particular to the 1848 result— were essential: Laurent taught Pasteur to use crystallography and the measurement of optical activity in conjunction (namely the measurement of the rotation of the plane of polarisation of light when the latter passes through crystals or solutions).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="20">
            <prop type="paragraph">9</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Mieux encore, Laurent fournit à Pasteur les cristaux que ce dernier analysa[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Better still, Laurent provided Pasteur with the crystals that he analysed[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="21">
            <prop type="paragraph">9</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pourtant Laurent ne fut pas cité dans l’article décrivant le dédoublement des tartrates, ce qui le conduisit à adresser aux Comptes rendus de l’Académie des sciences, quelques semaines après la publication de la découverte des deux acides tartriques (+) et (−), un article où il signalait ses apports[7](dans les évocations ultérieures des travaux ayant conduit au dédoublement des tartrates, Pasteur ne cita que rarement Laurent, et il y a lieu de s’en étonner).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Yet Laurent was not quoted in the article describing the duplication of tartrates. This led him to send an article to the journal Comptes Rendus de l'Académie des Sciences (in English, **Proceedings of the Academy of Sciences**) a few weeks after the publication of the discovery of the two tartaric acids (+) and (−), in which he indicated his contributions[7](in the later references to the research which led to the duplication of tartrates, Pasteur rarely quoted Laurent, which is surprising).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="22">
            <prop type="paragraph">10</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les principaux scientifiques qui avaient préparé la découverte annoncée le 22 mai 1848 étaient René Just Haüy (1743–1822), Louis-Joseph Gay-Lussac (1778–1850), Carl Scheele (1742–1786), Kestner, François Arago (1786–1853), Eilhard Mitscherlich (1794–1863), Biot et Laurent[1]. L’acide tartrique (+) avait été étudié depuis 1769, et la découverte par Kestner de ce qui fut nommé «acide paratartrique», ou encore «acide thannique» (il avait été découvert à Thann, en Alsace), en 1822, fut évidemment cruciale pour l’identification de deux des trois isomères de l’acide tartrique (voir la Figure1) : plus précisément, pour son étude, Pasteur fit usage de techniques d’étude de l’orientation des faces des cristaux par des techniques initialement mises au point par William Hyde Wollaston (1766–1828) et par Biot, ainsi que de mesures de la rotation du plan de polarisation de la lumière, mises au point par Biot, sur la base de découvertes d’Étienne-Louis Malus (1775–1812) et d’Arago.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The principal scientists who had prepared the discovery announced on 22 May 1848 were René Just Haüy (1743–1822), Louis-Joseph Gay-Lussac (1778–1850), Carl Scheele (1742–1786), Kestner, François Arago (1786–1853), Eilhard Mitscherlich (1794–1863), Biot, and Laurent[1]. Tartaric acid (+) had been studied since 1769, and Kestner's discovery of what was called "paratartaric acid", or "thannic acid" (having been discovered in Thann, Alsace) in 1822 was obviously crucial for the identification of two of the three isomers of tartaric acid (see Figure1): more precisely, for his study, Pasteur made use of techniques for studying the orientation of the faces of the crystals by using techniques initially developed by William Hyde Wollaston (1766–1828) and by Biot, as well as measurements of the rotation of the plane of polarisation of light, developed by Biot on the basis of discoveries by Étienne-Louis Malus (1775–1812) and Arago.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="23">
            <prop type="paragraph">11</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Après Biot, Pasteur répéta que les composés organiques étaient plus fréquemment actifs optiquement que les composés minéraux[9]: «Chacun sait, en effet, depuis les belles et nombreuses recherches de M. Biot, que beaucoup de substances organiques jouissent de la propriété singulière de dévier à l’état de dissolution le plan de polarisation des rayons lumineux».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Following Biot, Pasteur reiterated that organic compounds were more frequently optically active than mineral compounds [9]: "Everyone knows, indeed, from the beautiful and numerous researches of M. Biot, that many organic substances have the unique property in the state of dissolution of deviating the plane of polarisation of light rays."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="24">
            <prop type="paragraph">11</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il organisa ses études autour de cette idée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He organised his research around this idea.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="25">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette époque était antérieure de plus de dix ans au premier congrès international des chimistes, que Friedrich August Kekulé (1829–1896), Charles Adolphe Würtz (1817–1884) et Karl Weltzien (1813–1870) organisèrent à Karlsruhe et où Stanislao Cannizzaro (1826–1910), reprenant des idées d’Amadeo Avogadro, fit circuler un mémoire qui proposait une définition claire des notions d’atomes et de molécules.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This period predated the first international congress of chemists by more than ten years, which Friedrich August Kekulé (1829–1896), Charles Adolphe Würtz (1817–1884) and Karl Weltzien (1813–1870) organised in Karlsruhe and where Stanislao Cannizzaro (1826–1910), taking up the ideas of Amadeo Avogadro, circulated a thesis which proposed a clear definition of the concepts of atoms and molecules.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="26">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En revanche, en 1848, ces notions étaient très indistinctes, au point d’être interchangeables dans les paroles, les écrits et les pensées scientifiques, et le terme de «dissymétrie moléculaire», employé par Pasteur et d’autres à côté de «dissymétrie optique», dans les années 1850 — et même dans les décennies suivantes —, ne peut pas être interprété avec le sens de «molécule» que nous avons aujourd’hui; c’est une des raisons pour laquelle nous proposons de ne pas lui substituer les expressions «chiralité moléculaire» ou «chiralité», au contraire des termes «hémiédrie» ou «activité rotatoire», qui ont conservé leur sens exact, parce qu’expérimental[10, 11].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>On the contrary, in 1848, these notions were very indistinct, to the point of being interchangeable in words, scientific writings and thinking. The term "molecular asymmetry," used by Pasteur and others alongside "optical asymmetry" in the 1850s — and even in the following decades — cannot be interpreted with the meaning of "molecule" that we have today; this is one of the reasons why we propose not to substitute it with the expressions "molecular chirality" or "chirality," unlike the terms "hemihedria" or "rotational activity," which have retained their exact meaning due to being experimental[10, 11].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="27">
            <prop type="paragraph">12</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans[1], il est montré que Pasteur utilisait le mot «molécule» avec une acception proche de celle qu’avait donnée Haüy[12], quand il proposait que les cristaux étaient des empilements de «molécules intégrantes», ayant généralisé l’observation selon laquelle un petit cristal rhomboédrique qui s’était cassé avait fait apparaître un cristal rhomboédrique plus petit.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In[1], it is shown that Pasteur used the word "molecule" with a meaning similar to that given by Haüy[12] when he proposed that the crystals were stacks of "integrant molecules," having generalised the observation in which a small rhombohedral crystal which had broken had made a smaller rhombohedral crystal appear.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="28">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est ce que l’on détecte notamment dans[13], quand Pasteur écritque Haüy «admettait très-bien que deux substances de même composition chimique [il s’agit ici de composition chimique élémentaire, c’est nous qui précisons] pouvaient avoir des formes cristallines différentes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is what is detected in[13], when Pasteur wrotethat Haüy "admitted very well that two substances of the same chemical composition [referring to elementary chemical composition, emphasis by us] could have different crystalline forms.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="29">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce qu’il n’admettait pas, et ce qui lui semblait inconcevable, c’est que des substances ayant la même composition chimique, et dont l’arrangement moléculaire des atomes élémentaires était le même [ici, c’est Pasteur qui souligne], eussent la même forme cristalline.»</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>What he did not admit, and what seemed inconceivable to him, was that substances having the same chemical composition, and whose molecular arrangement of the elementary atoms was the same [here, it is Pasteur who emphasises], had the same crystalline form."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="30">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La fin de cette citation montre nettement combien il serait erroné de croire que Pasteur put — comme ses contemporains — avoir une idée claire de la notion d’atome ou de molécule à l’époque que nous considérons ici.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The end of this quotation clearly shows how wrong it would be to believe that Pasteur — like his contemporaries — could have had a clear idea of the concept of an atom or a molecule at the time in history that we are considering here.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="31">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cela se retrouve dans «On peut donc très-bien, selon moi, jusqu’à preuve du contraire, admettre que cette variété de baryto-calcite n’est qu’une variété de baryte carbonatée unie par accident atome par atome au carbonate de chaux»[13, 14]: le mot«atome» ne peut désigner qu’une partie élémentaire.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This can be found in the following: "We can therefore very well, in my opinion, until proof to the contrary, admit that this variety of barytocalcite is only a variety of carbonate barite united by accident atom by atom with lime carbonate" [13, 14]: the word"atom" can only designate an elementary part.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="32">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De même pour le passage suivant: «Je pense dès lors qu’il est impossible de douter qu’un certain groupe moléculaire reste constant dans tous ces sels ; que l’eau de cristallisation, que les bases, reléguées aux extrémités de ce groupe, le modifient à ces extrémités seulement, ne touchant qu’à peine, et dans la mesure de la différence des angles observés entre les facettes, à l’arrangement moléculaire central.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Likewise for the following passage: "I therefore think that it is impossible to doubt that a certain molecular group remains constant in all these salts; that the water of crystallisation, that the bases, relegated to the extremities of this group, modify it at these ends only, barely touching, and to the extent of the difference of the angles observed between the facets, to the central molecular arrangement.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="33">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Assurément je ne fais que confirmer ici cette opinion que tous les chimistes énonceraient, savoir qu’entre tous les sels d’un même acide, il y a quelque chose de commun.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Certainly I am only confirming here the opinion that all the chemists would state, namely that among all the salts of the same acid, there is something in common.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="34">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces faits, cependant, nous montrent, en outre, l’étroite relation qui existe entre la forme cristalline et la constitution moléculaire, et le jour que l’on peut jeter, par les études cristallographiques, sur l’arrangement des atomes»[15, 16].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These facts, however, show us, moreover, the close relationship which exists between the crystalline form and the molecular constitution, and the light which can be cast, via crystallographic studies, on the arrangement of atoms" [15, 16].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="35">
            <prop type="paragraph">13</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette citation pose la question de savoir comment Pasteur et ses contemporains imaginaient les organisations à très petite échelle[10, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21]: dans une recherche sur les évolutions intellectuelles de Pasteur, cette question s’impose évidemment, notamment parce que les chimistes français, dont Pasteur[22], étaient férus des écrits d’Antoine Laurent de Lavoisier, lequel, reprenant Condillac, avait insisté sur l’importance de la nomenclature en chimie[23].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This quotation raises the question of how Pasteur and his contemporaries imagined these structures on a very small scale[10, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21]. When researching the intellectual evolution of Pasteur, this question is clearly necessary, especially because French chemists, including Pasteur[22], were passionate about the writings of Antoine Laurent de Lavoisier, who, taking up the work of Condillac, had insisted on the importance of nomenclature in chemistry[23].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="36">
            <prop type="paragraph">14</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Profitons de cette dernière citation pour observer que, si l’on utilise la terminologie moderne, alors il est exact que la cristallographie donne des informations sur l’arrangement des atomes; en revanche, il serait anachronique de voir dans la fin de la phrase de Pasteur la préfiguration des travaux de William Henry Bragg (1862–1942) et de William Lawrence Bragg (1890–1971) en 1915, puisque les rayons X ne furent découverts qu’en 1895 par Wilhelm Konrad Röntgen (1845–1923)[24].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>With this last quotation we can observe that if modern terminology is used, then it is true that crystallography gives information on the arrangement of atoms; on the other hand, it would be anachronistic to see the prefiguration of the works of William Henry Bragg (1862–1942) and William Lawrence Bragg (1890–1971) in 1915 at the end of Pasteur's sentence, since X-rays were not discovered until 1895 by Wilhelm Konrad Röntgen (1845–1923)[24].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="37">
            <prop type="paragraph">15</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Certains ont considéré comme «remarquable que, sans l’idée claire d’atomes et de molécules, on ait pu imaginer que la chiralité moléculaire [Pasteur parle, lui, de «dissymétrie optique» ou de «dissymétrie moléculaire»] ait été le résultat d’arrangements hélicoïdaux d’objets dans les cristaux», et ils évoquent des textes —postérieurs au dédoublement des tartrates— où Pasteur discute une organisation tétraédrique[25, 26], mais il est anachronique de penser que Pasteur avait correctement compris que certains groupes chimiques (au sens moderne) formaient des motifs tétraédriques, car cette idée ne fut introduite que plus tard, par Joseph Achille Le Bel (1847–1930) et Jacobus Henricus van’t Hoff (1852–1911), et cette fois avec une idée moderne d’atomes et de molécules[10]. En outre, la «dissymétrie moléculaire» n’est pas le résultat d’arrangements «hélicoïdaux» des atomes, ni avec l’acception pastorienne, ni avec l’acception moderne du mot «atome»[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Some have considered it "remarkable that, without the clear idea of atoms and molecules, it could have been imagined that molecular chirality [Pasteur speaks of "optical asymmetry" or "molecular asymmetry"] was the result of helical arrangements of objects in crystals." They evoke texts —after the doubling of tartrates— where Pasteur discusses a tetrahedral organisation [25, 26], but it is anachronistic to think that Pasteur correctly understood that certain chemical groups (in the modern sense) formed tetrahedral patterns; this idea was only introduced later, by Joseph Achille Le Bel (1847–1930) and Jacobus Henricus van 't Hoff (1852–1911), and this time with a modern idea of atoms and molecules[10]. Moreover, "molecular asymmetry" is not the result of "helical" arrangements of atoms, neither with the pasteurian meaning, nor with the modern meaning of the word "atom"[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="38">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans les idées que Pasteur devait considérer pour ses interprétations, il y avait cette différence entre les composés organiques et les composés minéraux, identifiée par Biot[4, 9], mais aussi cet étonnement que le quartz fasse tourner le plan de polarisation, d’une part, tandis que l’«acide paratartrique» (ou acide racémique) et ses sels ne le fassent pas.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Among the ideas that Pasteur had to consider for his interpretations was the difference between organic compounds and mineral compounds, identified by Biot[4, 9]. He also was astonished by how quartz rotates the plane of polarisation, on the one hand, while "paratartaric acid" (or racemic acid) and its salts do not.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="39">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur écrivit ainsi, en 1850[14]: «La cause qui produit l’hémiédrie peut avoir deux origines distinctes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In 1850, Pasteur thus wrote [14]: "The cause that produces hemihedria can have two distinct origins.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="40">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle peut résider dans la molécule chimique elle-même, et se transporter à toutes les combinaisons de cette molécule.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It can reside in the chemical molecule itself, and be transported to all combinations of that molecule.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="41">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est ce qui a lieu pour l’acide tartrique et l’acide lévoracémique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is the case for tartaric acid and levoracemic acid.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="42">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La dissymétrie de la forme [du cristal] peut, d’autre part, n’être qu’une conséquence du mode d’agrégation des molécules dans le cristal, ce qui a lieu probablement dans le quartz.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The asymmetry of the shape [of the crystal] may, on the other hand, be only a consequence of the aggregation mode of the molecules in the crystal, which probably is what happens with quartz.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="43">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Or, dans ce dernier cas, la structure cristalline une fois détruite, il n’y a plus de dissymétrie, il n’y a plus de phénomène de polarisation rotatoire possible, et la substance, à l’état de dissolution ne peut dévier le plan de polarisation de la lumière.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the latter case, once the crystalline structure is destroyed, there is no longer any asymmetry, there is no longer any possible phenomenon of rotational polarisation, and the substance, in the state of dissolution, cannot deviate the plane of polarisation of the light.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="44">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle le déviera à l’état cristallisé.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It will deflect it to the crystallised state.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="45">
            <prop type="paragraph">16</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans le cas même où la dissymétrie existerait dans la molécule chimique, par suite d’un arrangement spécial des atomes dans cette molécule, il pourrait arriver que la substance ne la déviât pas à l’état de dissolution. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Even in the case where asymmetry exists within the chemical molecule, as a result of a special arrangement of atoms in this molecule, it may occur that the substance does not deviate it in the state of dissolution."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="46">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans cet extrait, la «molécule chimique» semble être la «molécule intégrante» de Haüy, une petite entité conjecturée et mal comprise à l’époque, comme on l’a signalé précédemment et dans[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this extract, the "chemical molecule" seems to be the "integral molecule" of Haüy, a small entity conjectured and misunderstood at the time, as previously reported in[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="47">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Quant à l’arrangement des «atomes», il ne peut donc s’agir non plus de la notion actuelle, malgré l’apparence de sens que prend la phrase a posteriori.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As for the arrangement of the "atoms", it therefore cannot be their current conception, despite the appearance of meaning that the sentence takes a posteriori.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="48">
            <prop type="paragraph">17</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Relue sans anachronisme, cette phrase contient des termes trop flous pour être considérée comme «presciente»[2, 27, 28].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Read without anachronism, this sentence contains terms that are too vague to be considered "prescient"[2, 27, 28].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="49">
            <prop type="paragraph">18</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Finalement le principal mérite de Pasteur, de ses années de thèse à la publication du dédoublement des tartrates, est son activité scientifique particulièrement soutenue, même s’il se répète largement, de publication en publication[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the end, the main merit of Pasteur, from his thesis years to the publication of the doubling of tartrates, is his particularly continuous scientific activity, even if he repeats himself widely from publication to publication[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="50">
            <prop type="paragraph">18</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sa capacité de synthèse doit également être observée, ce que montre notamment son article du 20 mars 1848[13], où sont cités les travaux de Laurent et d’autres, tels Gabriel Delafosse (1796–1878), qui fut élève de Biot et professeur de Pasteur: dans ce texte, sont analysées les formes cristallines de «toutes les substances dimorphes» alors connues de lui et de Delafosse, à savoir soufre, carbonate de calcium (aragonite), «baryto-calcite», «nitrate de potasse», «nitrate de soude», «sesquioxyde de fer», sulfure de cuivre, sulfure d’argent, «sulfate de potasse», iodure de mercure, «mésotypes», micas, «sulfotricarbonate de plomb», sulfate de nickel, séléniate de zinc, grenat, idocrase, chlorure de naphtaline, «chlorure de naphtaline monochlorée», pyrite, acide arsénieux, «acide titanique».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>His ability to synthesise must also be observed, as shown in his article of March 20, 1848[13], which cites the research of Laurent and others, such as Gabriel Delafosse (1796–1878), who was a pupil of Biot and a professor of Pasteur. In this text, the following crystalline forms are analysed: "all the dimorphic substances" then known to him and Delafosse, namely sulfur, calcium carbonate (aragonite), "baryto-calcite," "potash nitrate," "sodium nitrate," "iron sesquioxide," copper sulfide, silver sulfide, "potash sulfate," mercury iodide, "mesotypes," micas, "lead sulfotricarbonate," nickel sulfate, zinc selenate, garnet, idocrase, naphthalene chloride, "monochlorine naphthalene chloride," pyrite, arsenic acid, and "titanic acid".</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="51">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans le mémoire du 22 mai 1848[4], ce sont les «tartrates» et les «paratartrates» qui sont essentiellement considérés, mais le jeune scientifique cherche des généralisations fécondes : «On dira, et avec juste raison: Toutes les substances organiques qui dévient le plan de polarisation lorsqu’elles sont dissoutes jouiront donc de l’hémiédrie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the memoir of May 22, 1848[4], it is the "tartrates" and the "paratartrates" which are primarily considered, but the young scientist seeks fruitful generalisations: "It will be said, and rightly so: All organic substances that deviate from the plane of polarisation when they are dissolved will therefore enjoy hemihedria.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="52">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>J’aurais beaucoup désiré ne présenter ce travail à l’Académie qu’après avoir examiné les bases organiques, le camphre et d’autres substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>I would very much have liked to present this work to the Academy only after examining organic bases, camphor, and other substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="53">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Mais ici on rencontre de grandes difficultés pour la recherche de l’hémiédrie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>But here we encounter great difficulties in the search for hemihedria.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="54">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La beauté des cristaux des tartrates, leur grosseur, m’a servi considérablement.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The beauty of tartrate crystals, their size, served me considerably.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="55">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant j’ai pu facilement étudier le sucre candi, et je puis annoncer, d’après mes propres recherches, que cette substance est hémiédrique, et jouit à un haut degré de la pyro-électricité polaire.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, I have been able to study candy sugar easily, and I can announce from my own research that this substance is hemihedral, and enjoys a high degree of polar pyroelectricity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="56">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est même par l’étude de cette dernière propriété que j’ai été assuré de l’hémiédrie, dont je me suis rendu compte ensuite par l’observation attentive de la forme cristalline.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It was even by studying this latter property that I was assured of the hemihedria, which I then realised via careful observation of the crystalline form.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="57">
            <prop type="paragraph">19</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Postérieurement, j’ai trouvé que cette détermination avait été déjà faite il y a longtemps par le Dr Hankel. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Later, I found that this determination had already been made a long time ago by Dr. Hankel."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="58">
            <prop type="paragraph">20</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A ce stade, Pasteur était passé de l’étude morphologique des cristaux, à l’étude des rotations éventuelles du plan de polarisation qu’ils induisaient, ce qui l’avait conduit mieux caractériser l’hémiédrie des tartrates.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At this stage, Pasteur had moved away from the morphological study of the crystals to the study of the possible rotations of the plane of polarisation which they induced, which had led him to better characterise the hemihedria of tartrates.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="59">
            <prop type="paragraph">20</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’était une voie qui était apparue féconde, et qu’on le voit suivre dans ses travaux ultérieurs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It was a path that appeared fruitful, and which we see him following in his later research.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="60">
            <prop type="paragraph">21</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>2. L’après 1848</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>2. Post-1848</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="61">
            <prop type="paragraph">22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En avril 1849, alors qu’il poursuit ses études des tartrates, Pasteur annonce avoir découvert qu’un sel de l’acide formique est hémiédrique[13, 29]: «En terminant, j’annoncerai à l’Académie un résultat qui semble offrir beaucoup d’intérêt.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In April 1849, while pursuing his research on tartrates, Pasteur announced that he had discovered that a salt of formic acid was hemihedral [13, 29]: "In closing, I will announce to the Academy a result that seems to offer much interest.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="62">
            <prop type="paragraph">22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>J’ai trouvé le double caractère hémiédrique dans un autre sel organique, le formiate de strontiane.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>I found the double hemihedral character in another organic salt, strontiane formate.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="63">
            <prop type="paragraph">22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce sel cristallise en prismes droits à base rhombe, portant des facettes hémiédriques sur les arêtes de base, et qui conduisent à deux tétraèdres identiques, mais inverses [souligné par Pasteur]. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This salt crystallises in right prisms with a rhombic base, bearing hemihedral facets on the base edges, and which lead to two identical but inverse tetrahedrons [emphasis by Pasteur].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="64">
            <prop type="paragraph">22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Puis, à la fin de cette même année, Biot informa Pasteur que l’« alcool amylique», produit lors de la fermentation de la fécule de pomme de terre, déviait le plan de polarisation de la lumière[30].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, at the end of that same year, Biot informed Pasteur that "amyl alcohol," produced during the fermentation of potato starch, deviated from the plane of polarisation of light[30].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="65">
            <prop type="paragraph">22</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur signale des difficultés à caractériser physiquement le «composé», au-delà des déterminations de la composition élémentaire, et cela se comprend aujourd’hui, car il existe 12 composés isomères ayant la formule générale C 5 H 11 OH (voir la Figure2)[31].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur reported difficulties in physically characterising the "compound," beyond the determinations of the elemental composition; this is understandable today, since there are 12 isomeric compounds having the general formula C5H11OH (see Figure2)[31].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="66">
            <prop type="paragraph">23</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Si la fermentation apparaît ainsi dans le champ d’études scientifiques de Pasteur, il n’est pas certain que cela ait changé immédiatement le cours de ses travaux expérimentaux, car ses publications de 1849 restent consacrées aux acides tartriques et aux tartrates; d’ailleurs, pendant longtemps, Pasteur resta attaché à sa réussite de 1848 et en chercha des prolongements directs[30, 32].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>If fermentation thus appeared in Pasteur's field of scientific study, it is not certain that this immediately changed the course of his experimental research. His publications of 1849 remain devoted to tartaric acids and tartrates; moreover, for a long time, Pasteur remained attached to his 1848 success and pursued direct extensions of it [30, 32].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="67">
            <prop type="paragraph">24</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette observation est historiquement importante, car certains ont vu dans les études des alcools amyliques des raisons pour lesquelles, quelques années plus tard, Pasteur quitta progressivement la physico-chimie des cristaux pour les études de la fermentation, puis de la microbiologie, tandis que d’autres proposaient que la transition soit plutôt due à l’intérêt de Pasteur pour des problèmes industriels, quand il fut nommé à Lille en 1854[26].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This observation is historically important, for some saw in the studies of amyl alcohols reasons why, a few years later, Pasteur gradually left the physicochemistry of crystals to research fermentation, then microbiology. On the other hand, others proposed that the transition was rather due to Pasteur's interest in industrial problems when he was appointed to Lille in 1854[26].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="68">
            <prop type="paragraph">24</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous prendrons parti plus loin à ce propos.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We will take sides on this later.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="69">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En 1850, Pasteur continue donc de s’intéresser aux acides tartriques et aux tartrates de «chaux» (le terme de Pasteur est ici conservé, alors que, ici par exemple, on dirait aujourd’hui «calcium», tout comme on dirait potassium, sodium, ammonium, etc. dans ce qui suit), de «potasse», de «soude», d’«ammoniaque», «émétique de potasse», «émétique d’ammoniaque»[33], mais il étend ses travaux à d’autres composés organiques, et cela est précisément une piste féconde, puisque le vivant est source de chiralité, à défaut d’avoir l’apanage de faire tourner le plan de polarisation de la lumière[34]:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In 1850, therefore, Pasteur continued to be interested in tartaric acids and "lime" tartrates (the term used by Pasteur is retained here, whereas, for this example, in modern days we would say "calcium," just as we would say potassium, sodium, ammonium, etc.), "potash," "soda," "ammonia," "potash emetic," "ammonia emetic"[33]. However, he extended his research efforts to other organic compounds.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="70">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>«Les faits que j’ai recueillis cette année se rapportent à l’asparagine, à l’acide aspartique, à la combinaison du glucose avec le sel marin, et au formiate de strontiane.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This was indeed a promising path, since the living is a source of chirality, in the absence of having the prerogative to rotate the plane of polarisation of light[34]: "The facts that I collected this year relate to asparagine, aspartic acid, the combination of glucose with sea salt, and strontiane formate.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="71">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] En examinant la forme cristalline de l’asparagine, j’ai reconnu d’une manière indubitable que tous les cristaux de cette substance sont hémiédriques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] In examining the crystalline form of asparagine, I have undoubtedly recognised that all crystals of this substance are hemihedral.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="72">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’hémiédrie est, en outre, non superposable.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The hemihedria is, moreover, non-superposable.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="73">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il était donc probable que cette substance devait jouir de la propriété rotatoire, et c’est en effet ce que l’expérience a confirmé.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It was therefore likely that this substance should have the property of rotation, and this is indeed what the experiment has confirmed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="74">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Les relations qui unissent l’asparagine à l’acide aspartique, indiquaient l’existence probable de la propriété rotatoire dans l’acide aspartique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] The connections between asparagine and aspartic acid indicated the probable existence of the rotatory property in aspartic acid.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="75">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, l’acide aspartique dévie le plan de polarisation des rayons lumineux, et son pouvoir rotatoire a de grandes analogies avec celui de l’asparagine.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Indeed, aspartic acid deviates from the plane of polarisation of light rays, and its rotational capability has great analogies with that of asparagine.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="76">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Enfin, les recherches récentes des chimistes tendant à faire admettre que l’asparagine est l’amide de l’acide malique, j’étais conduit à rechercher le pouvoir rotatoire dans l’acide malique et les malates.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] Finally, as the recent research of chemists tend to admit that asparagine is the amide of malic acid, I was led to search for rotatory capability in malic acid and malates.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="77">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’expérience a encore répondu à mon attente.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The experiment met my expectations again.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="78">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’acide malique, et les sels qui en dérivent, ont la propriété de dévier le plan de polarisation des rayons lumineux ; et j’ai retrouvé l’hémiédrie non superposable dans plusieurs malates.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Malic acid, and the salts derived therefrom, have the property of deviating the plane of polarisation of the light rays; and I have found the non-superposable hemihedria in several malates.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="79">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Mais il est un fait sur lequel je veux surtout insister à propos de l’acide malique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>But there is a fact that I want to emphasise above all about malic acid.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="80">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cet acide offre, dans les particularités de son pouvoir rotatoire, des analogies très grandes avec les acides tartriques droit et gauche ; et ces analogies conduisent naturellement à penser qu’il existe d’intimes relations d’arrangements moléculaires dissymétriques, entre l’acide malique et l’un ou l’autre des deux acides tartriques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This acid offers, in the peculiarities of its rotational capability, very great analogies with the tartaric acids that are right-handed and left-handed; and these analogies naturally lead to the belief that there are intimate relations of asymmetric molecular arrangements between malic acid and one or the other of the two tartaric acids.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="81">
            <prop type="paragraph">25</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il est très vraisemblable qu’il doit exister, entre l’acide malique et l’un des deux acides tartriques, droit ou gauche, un groupement moléculaire commun, avec la modification que peut apporter, dans ce groupement, la différence de composition de ces acides [c’est l’auteur qui souligne]. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It is very likely that there must exist, between malic acid and one of the two tartaric acids, right-handed or left-handed, a common molecular group, with the modification that may be brought, in this group, by the difference in composition of these acids" [author emphasis].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="82">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Commentons ce passage en observant que l’asparagine n’est pas l’amide de l’acide malique (l’atome d’azote ne remplace pas l’atome de carbone stéréogénique) (voir la Figure3), mais, surtout, que l’hypothèse de «groupement moléculaire commun» entre les acides tartriques et les acides maliques n’est pas la cause de la communauté de propriétés optiques; c’est plutôt la tétravalence du carbone, et l’organisation tétraédrique de ses substituants, laquelle conduit à la chiralité.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We comment on this passage by observing that asparagine is not the amide of malic acid (the nitrogen atom does not replace the stereogenic carbon atom) (see Figure3), but, above all, that the hypothesis of "common molecular grouping" between tartaric acids and malic acids is not the cause of the cluster of optical properties; it is rather the tetravalence of carbon, and the tetrahedral organisation of its substituents, which leads to chirality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="83">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Évidemment, le signalement de ces erreurs ne peut être une critique de Pasteur, car les idées sur la notion de radical étaient encore très discutées; elles avaient été révisées par Laurent vers 1844, à partir de la théorie du dualisme électrochimique de Dumas[35], et c’est seulement en 1860 — c’est-à-dire l’année du colloque des chimistes de Karslruhe — qu’Auguste Cahours (1813–1891) s’autorisa à écrire[36, 37]: « On donne le nom de radicaux à des êtres particuliers dont la nature complexe peut être mise en évidence à l’aide de forces physiques ou par l’intervention des réactifs, mais qui, bien que formés de plusieurs éléments, présentent les caractères des corps simples et remplissent des fonctions exactement semblables.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Of course, noting these errors cannot be a criticism of Pasteur, for ideas on the concept of radicals were still much debated; they had been revised by Laurent around 1844, starting from the theory of the electrochemical dualism of Dumas[35], and it is only in 1860 — that is to say the year of the colloquium of the chemists of Karslruhe — that Auguste Cahours (1813–1891) authorised himself to write[36, 37]: "We give the name of radicals to particular entities whose complex nature can be demonstrated by means of physical forces or by the intervention of reagents, but which, although formed of several elements, have the characteristics of simple entities and fulfill exactly similar functions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="84">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce sont, en un mot, des composés qui possèdent la propriété de former avec les corps simples des combinaisons entièrement analogues à celles que produisent ces derniers par leur union mutuelle. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>They are, in short, compounds which possess the property of forming combinations with simple entities that are entirely similar to those produced by the latter via their mutual union."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="85">
            <prop type="paragraph">26</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>À cette époque, Cahours observait que certains radicaux avaient été isolés : le cyanogène, le cacodyle, etc., tandis que d’autres « n’ont à cette heure qu’une existence purement hypothétique» : le méthyle, l’éthyle, l’acétyle, le benzoïle, l’ammonium, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At that time, Cahours observed that some radicals had been isolated: cyanogen, cacodyle, etc. Others, however, "have at this time only a purely hypothetical existence": methyl, ethyl, acetyl, benzoyl, ammonium, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="86">
            <prop type="paragraph">27</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sur sa lancée, Pasteur publie le 30 septembre 1850 ses résultats d’étude du formiate de strontiane, de l’acide aspartique et d’aspartates, de l’asparagine, de l’acide malique, des malates, de l’acide fumarique et des fumarates, de l’acide maléique, du «glucosate de sel marin»[38].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>On September 30, 1850, Pasteur published his results of studies on strontiane formate, aspartic acid and aspartates, asparagine, malic acid, malates, fumaric acid and fumarates, maleic acid, and "sea salt glucosate"[38].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="87">
            <prop type="paragraph">27</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Comme pour d’autres articles antérieurs, il publie des paragraphes quasi identiques dans plusieurs articles successifs, conservant les termes «atomes» ou «molécules» pour des acceptions de son temps:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>As with other previous articles, he publishes almost identical paragraphs in several successive articles, retaining the terms "atoms" or "molecules" with the meanings of his time:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="88">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>«Pendant très longtemps on ignora complètement quelle pouvait être la cause de cette dissymétrie de la forme cristalline.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>"For a very long time it was completely unknown what could be the cause of this asymmetry of the crystalline form.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="89">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il n’existe qu’un seul travail, celui de M. Delafosse, où, pour la première fois, on ait essayé d’établir que ce phénomène de l’hémiédrie tenait à la constitution intime du cristal.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>There is only one work, that of Mr. Delafosse, where, for the first time, there was an attempt to establish that this phenomenon of hemihedria was due to the intimate constitution of the crystal.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="90">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour rendre compte du phénomène, M. Delafosse s’arrête à la structure interne, à la disposition des molécules physiques, sans aller jusqu’au mode d’arrangement des atomes dans la molécule chimique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To account for the phenomenon, Mr. Delafosse considers the internal structure, at the layout of physical molecules, without going as far as the mode of arrangement of atoms in the chemical molecule."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="91">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>» Pasteur était trop précis pour ne pas être conscient du rapprochement, dans la fin de cet extrait, entre les deux expressions «molécules physiques» et «molécule chimique», mais il n’y a pas, à notre connaissance, de discussion de sa part de cette différence.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur was too precise not to be aware of the relation, in the end of this excerpt, between the two expressions "physical molecules" and "chemical molecule," but there is, to our knowledge, no discussion on his part of this difference.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="92">
            <prop type="paragraph">28</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On en est réduit à rapprocher le premier terme des textes de Haüy (les «molécules intégrantes»), et à associer le second aux explorations des chimistes, sans que la relation entre les deux termes puisse être explicitée, à cette époque.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We are obliged to relate the first term to Haüy's texts (the "integrating molecules"), and associate the second with the explorations of chemists, without being able to explain the relationship between the two terms at this time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="93">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les conclusions du texte de 1851 sont quasiment mot à mot celles de 1850: «Les faits précédents conduisent à supposer que l’hémiédrie du formiate de strontiane ne tient pas à l’arrangement des atomes dans la molécule chimique, mais à l’arrangement des molécules physiques dans le cristal total.»</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The conclusions of the 1851 text are almost verbatim those of 1850: "The preceding facts lead us to suppose that the hemihedry of strontiane formate is not due to the arrangement of atoms in the chemical molecule, but to the arrangement of physical molecules in the total crystal."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="94">
            <prop type="paragraph">29</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette observation conforte l’hypothèse que nous venons de faire.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This observation reinforces the hypothesis we have just made.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="95">
            <prop type="paragraph">30</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Évidemment la question de l’activité optique des corps est loin d’être résolue, ce qui motive que Pasteur continue ses études[39]: «Or on n’a jamais, jusqu’à ce jour, donné naissance, par les procédés des laboratoires, à une substance ayant une action sur le plan de polarisation en partant de composés qui ne possédaient pas eux même cette faculté.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Clearly, the question of the optical activity of the entities is far from being resolved, which is why Pasteur continues his research: [39] "To this day, however, no laboratory methods have led to the production of a substance having an action on the plane of polarisation if it started with compounds that did not themselves possess this faculty.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="96">
            <prop type="paragraph">30</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>» Ici, on trouve un écho de ses idées sur l’activité optique des composés du vivant.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Here we find an echo of his ideas on the optical activity of living compounds.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="97">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette même année, Pasteur approche à nouveau la question des fermentations: partant de cristaux produits par Victor Dessaignes (1800–1885), un receveur de Vendôme qui faisait de la chimie dans un laboratoire personnel[40], il ne retrouve pas l’activité optique des cristaux «naturels».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>That same year, Pasteur again approached the question of fermentation: starting from crystals produced by Victor Dessaignes (1800–1885), a collector from Vendôme who conducted chemistry in a personal laboratory [40], he did not detect optical activity in "natural" crystals.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="98">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Or ces cristaux avaient été obtenus par fermentation du fumarate d’ammonium en acide aspartique[41].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These crystals had been obtained by fermentation of ammonium fumarate with aspartic acid [41].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="99">
            <prop type="paragraph">31</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pis, l’activité optique de l’ «acide aspartique» dépendait du pH: dextrarotatoire à pH élevé, lévorotatoire à faible pH.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Worse, the optical activity of "aspartic acid" depended on pH: dextrarotatory at high pH, levorotatory at low pH.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="100">
            <prop type="paragraph">32</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour autant, Pasteur poursuivit ses études de divers composés organiques, convaincu de l’importance de la découverte qu’il aurait faite avec les acides tartriques et les tartrates: «Aujourd’hui nous voyons que les combinaisons actives sur la lumière polarisée peuvent être assez peu altérées dans leur groupement moléculaire constitutif pour conserver, sans exception, toutes leurs propriétés chimiques, en perdant seulement, dans leurs molécules constituantes, cette dissymétrie spéciale qui produit le caractère droit ou gauche.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, Pasteur continued his research on various organic compounds, convinced of the importance of the discovery he may have made with tartaric acids and tartrates: "Today we see that the combinations active on polarised light can be little altered in their constituent molecular grouping to preserve, without exception, all their chemical properties, losing only, in their constituent molecules, this special asymmetry which produces the right-handed or left-handed character.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="101">
            <prop type="paragraph">32</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] L’ensemble de ces quatre particularités, qui forment autant d’exceptions aux lois ordinaires du phénomène rotatoire, ne s’est présenté encore dans aucune substance.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] All these four peculiarities, which form so many exceptions to the ordinary laws of the rotational phenomenon, have not yet appeared in any substance.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="102">
            <prop type="paragraph">32</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Or l’acide malique actif m’a offert ces mêmes particularités d’une manière plus saillante même que l’acide tartrique. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, active malic acid has offered me these same peculiarities in a more prominent way than tartaric acid."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="103">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A l’époque, il n’a pas trouvé l’acide mésotartrique, puisqu’il en conjecture l’existence[1]: «Il y a aussi de fortes raisons de croire qu’il peut exister un acide tartrique correspondant à l’acide malique inactif.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At the time, he had not found mesotartaric acid, shown by how he conjectures its existence[1]: "There are also strong reasons to believe that there may be a tartaric acid corresponding to inactive malic acid.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="104">
            <prop type="paragraph">33</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cet acide serait neutre sur la lumière polarisée comme l’acide racémique, mais différerait de ce dernier par sa constitution moléculaire, et ne pourrait être dédoublé en deux acides tartriques, droit et gauche. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This acid would be neutral with regards to polarised light like racemic acid, but would differ from the latter in its molecular constitution, and could not be split into two tartaric acids, right-handed and left-handed."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="105">
            <prop type="paragraph">34</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>3. 1852: Nommé à Strasbourg</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>3. 1852: Appointed in Strasbourg</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="106">
            <prop type="paragraph">35</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Quand Pasteur est nommé à l’université de Strasbourg, en 1852, il continue de publier rapidement, et toujours avec sa manière fleurie, classique à l’époque[1], mais surtout de façon très redondante, d’article en article: dans une communication de 1852[42], on retrouve les mêmes phrases que dans les textes précédents.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>When Pasteur was appointed to the University of Strasbourg in 1852, he continued to publish quickly, always with his fancy style which was classic of the time[1], but in a particularly redundant way from article to article: in a communication from 1852[42], we find the same sentences as in the previous texts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="107">
            <prop type="paragraph">36</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est l’époque où Mitscherlich lui signale la présence, en Saxe, d’une usine qui aurait produit industriellement le mélange racémique d’acides tartriques[43].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It was at this time that Mitscherlich reported to him the presence in Saxony of a factory which may have produced the racemic mixture of tartaric acids industrially [43].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="108">
            <prop type="paragraph">36</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Désireux de gagner le prix de la Société de pharmacie de Paris, Pasteur part pour la Saxe, mais, une fois sur place, il constate que la fabrication ne forme plus le mélange racémique depuis que l’usine a changé de fournisseur de tartre (du tartre du vin, à ne pas confondre avec le carbonate de calcium[1]).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Eager to win the award of the Société de pharmacie de Paris (Pharmacy Society of Paris), Pasteur left for Saxony. Once there, however, he noticed that the manufacturing process no longer produced a racemic mixture since the factory changed the supplier of tartar (wine tartar, not to be confused with calcium carbonate [1]).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="109">
            <prop type="paragraph">36</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il visite les carrières et conclut que le problème résulte du raffinage : le racémique est éliminé[43].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He visited the quarries and concluded that the problem resulted from refining: the racemic property was eliminated[43].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="110">
            <prop type="paragraph">37</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette même année, il continue ses études de la quinine, de la cinchonine et de la quinidine, observe que la quinine est faite de deux isomères, comme la cinchonine, mais il ne comprend pas que la quinidine n’est que l’isomère dextrogyre de la quinine.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>That same year, he continued his research on quinine, cinchonine and quinidine, observing that quinine was composed of two isomers, like cinchonine. However, he did not understand that quinidine was only the dextrorotatory isomer of quinine.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="111">
            <prop type="paragraph">37</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il observe que, au soleil, les solutions de ces composés changent de couleur, de sorte qu’il en vient à chauffer volontairement divers composés, à la recherche d’un effet sur l’activité optique (voir la Figure4).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He observed that in the sun, the solutions of these compounds change color. Based on this observation, he started voluntarily heating various compounds in search of an effect on optical activity (see Figure4).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="112">
            <prop type="paragraph">37</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il nomme «quinicine» la quinine chauffée et espère avoir trouvé un nouveau médicament, mais les tests cliniques, à l’Hôpital de la charité, à Paris, sont un échec[44].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He called the heated quinine "quinicine" and hoped to have found a new drug, but the clinical trials at the Hôpital de la Charité in Paris were a failure[44].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="113">
            <prop type="paragraph">38</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Surtout, à Strasbourg, il poursuit ses études de l’activité optique, explorant tous les échantillons des collections de la Faculté, et se convainc que les minéraux et les substances chimiques produites artificiellement en laboratoire seraient dominés par la symétrie, et que les seuls corps qui dévient le plan de polarisation de la lumière proviendraient de végétaux et d’animaux : le pouvoir rotatoire différencierait l’animé de l’inanimé, la vie de ce qui n’en est pas[42].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Above all, in Strasbourg, he continued his research on optical activity, exploring all the samples in the Faculty's collections, and convinced himself that the minerals and chemical substances artificially produced in the laboratory would be dominated by symmetry, and that the only entities that deviated from the plane of polarisation of light would come from plants and animals: the rotational capability would differentiate the animate from the inanimate, life from what is not [42].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="114">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A l’époque, et notamment grâce à Biot, de nombreux composés organiques optiquement actifs avaient été identifiés[45], tels que l’amygdaline, divers sucres, des huiles essentielles, l’acide mandélique (nommé alors «amygdalique»), le camphre, la morphine, la strychnine, la brucine, la cinchonine, la quinine, l’albumine, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At the time, and in particular thanks to Biot, numerous optically active organic compounds had been identified[45], such as amygdalin, various sugars, essential oils, mandelic acid (then called “amygdalic”), camphor, morphine, strychnine, brucine, cinchonine, quinine, albumin, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="115">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les composés actifs connus étaient donc majoritairement organiques, à l’exception notoire du quartz, mais ce dernier perdait son activité optique à l’état fondu.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The known active compounds were therefore predominantly organic, with the notorious exception of quartz, but the latter lost its optical activity in the molten state.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="116">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Et Pasteur d’émettre une hypothèse « universelle» qu’il conservera longtemps[44]: «Au moment de leur regroupement, les atomes élémentaires [l’expression seule suffit à montrer, à nouveau, combien la notion d’atome était différente de la nôtre] sont soumis à une influence dissymétrique et, comme toutes les molécules organiques qui ont pris naissance dans des circonstances analogues sont identiques, quelles que soient leur origine et le lieu de leur production, cette influence doit être universelle.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur made a "universal" hypothesis that he would keep for a long time [44]: "At the time of their grouping, the elementary atoms [the expression alone suffices to show, once again, how different their notion of an atom was from ours] are subjected to an asymmetric influence and, since all organic molecules which originated in similar circumstances are identical, whatever their origin and place of production, this influence must be universal.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="117">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle embrasserait le globe terrestre tout entier.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It would embrace the entire globe.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="118">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A elle serait due la dissymétrie moléculaire des produits organiques naturels des végétaux, produits que nous retrouvons chez les animaux à peu près sans altération, et où elle joue un rôle mystérieux duquel nous n’avons encore aucune idée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It is due to the molecular asymmetry of the natural organic products of plants, products that we find in animals almost without alteration, and where it plays a mysterious role of which we have no understanding yet.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="119">
            <prop type="paragraph">39</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’univers est un ensemble dissymétrique, et je suis persuadé que la vie, telle qu’elle se manifeste à nous, est fonction de la dissymétrie de l’univers ou des conséquences qu’elle entraîne».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The universe is an asymmetrical whole, and I am convinced that life, as it manifests itself to us, is a function of the asymmetry of the universe or of the consequences it entails."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="120">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans son texte où il présente en détail ses investigations sur les acides tartriques, Pasteur fait état des pratiques qui conduisent au racémique sans les comprendre, signalant d’ailleurs plusieurs fois que les eaux-mères ont attendu plusieurs années.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In his text, in which he presented in detail his investigations on tartaric acids, Pasteur reported the practices that lead to racemic properties without understanding them, moreover pointing out several times that mother liquors waited several years.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="121">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Puis, tandis qu’il publie des notes sur la quinidine, la strychnine, la quinine, la quinoïdine, le mystère du mélange racémique continue de le préoccuper[46, 47]: «D’ailleurs, on doit regarder l’ensemble des faces hémiédriques d’un cristal comme l’une des nombreuses formes secondaires que peut toujours revêtir une substance quelle qu’elle soit.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, while he published notes on quinidine, strychnine, quinine, and quinidine, the mystery of the racemic mixture continued to concern him [46, 47]: "Moreover, one must look at all the hemihedral faces of a crystal as one of the many secondary forms that any substance can always cover.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="122">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est que cette identité absolue pour tout ce qui n’est pas hémiédrie et sens du phénomène rotatoire [des tartrates] n’existe qu’autant que les deux acides tartriques sont unis à des combinaisons inactives sur la lumière polarisée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is because this absolute identity for all that is not hemihedria and sense of the rotational phenomenon [tartrates] exists only as long as the two tartaric acids are united with inactive combinations on polarised light.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="123">
            <prop type="paragraph">40</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Mais les place-t-on, eux ou leurs dérivés, en présence de produits qui ont une action moléculaire quelconque sur le plan de polarisation, alors toute identité cesse d’avoir lieu. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>But if they or their derivatives are placed in the presence of products which have any molecular action on the plane of polarisation, then any identity ceases to take place."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="124">
            <prop type="paragraph">41</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>4. Le basculement à Lille</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>4. The move to Lille</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="125">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le passage aux études des fermentations intervient à Lille, après que Pasteur a été nommé doyen de la nouvelle faculté des sciences, en 1854.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The transition to fermentation research took place in Lille, after Pasteur was appointed dean of the new faculty of science in 1854.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="126">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Certains ont dit que Pasteur aurait été conduit à étudier les fermentations en raison des activités industrielles de la région lilloise (fabrication d’alcool ou brasserie); d’autres ont supposé que Pasteur aurait été conduit aux études des fermentations par ses études de l’«alcool amylique»[48, 49, 50].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Some have said that Pasteur was led to study fermentation because of the industrial activities of the Lille region (alcohol manufacturing or breweries); others have assumed that Pasteur was led to research fermentation by his research on "amyl alcohol"[48, 49, 50].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="127">
            <prop type="paragraph">42</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous pensons qu’il n’y a pas lieu de choisir entre ces deux explications, car elles ne s’excluent pas: l’activité scientifique se fonde sur un ensemble de conditions, matérielles et intellectuelles; et la lecture des publications de Pasteur fait penser, en outre, qu’il avait déjà tant défriché le terrain de la chiralité qu’il avait pu juger de bonne stratégie scientifique d’envisager des questions nouvelles, afin de résoudre ou d’abandonner un problème qui résistait aux explorations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We believe that there is no need to choose between these two explanations, for they are not mutually exclusive: scientific activity is based on a set of conditions, material and intellectual; and the reading of Pasteur's publications suggests, moreover, that he had already cleared the ground of chirality extensively enough that he could consider it a good scientific strategy to consider new questions, in order to solve or abandon a problem whose solution evaded exploration.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="128">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Certes, autour de Lille, les industries agricoles et alimentaires étaient essentielles, avec notamment des fermentations alcooliques à partir de betteraves, mais aussi les brasseries[50, 51, 52].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Certainly, around Lille, the agricultural and food industries were essential, in particular alcoholic fermentations from beets, but also breweries[50, 51, 52].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="129">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Lors de la nomination de Pasteur, le ministre de l’instruction publique avait insisté sur les applications des sciences, en soutien aux industries de la région: «Je n’ai pas besoin, Monsieur, de vous rappeler toute l’importance qui s’attache au succès de cette nouvelle Faculté des sciences placée dans une ville qui est le centre le plus riche de l’activité industrielle dans le nord de la France»[53].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At the time of Pasteur's appointment, the Minister of Public Education had insisted on the applications of science, in support of the industries of the region: "I do not need, Sir, to remind you of the importance attached to the success of this new Faculty of Science placed in a city which is the richest center of industrial activity in the north of France"[53].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="130">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En conséquence, Pasteur fit des efforts pour que les étudiants n’aient pas seulement une formation théorique, mais également des connaissances technologiques et techniques: il organisa des visites d’usines[48, 54] et traita dans ses cours des phénomènes qui avaient lieu lors de la fermentation du jus de betterave[55].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Consequently, Pasteur made efforts to ensure that the students had not only theoretical training, but also technological and technical knowledge: he organised visits to factories[48, 54] and addressed the phenomena that took place during the fermentation of beet juice in his classes [55].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="131">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est là le versant de ce que je nomme l’ «hypothèse lilloise» de son évolution scientifique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This supports what I call the "Lille hypothesis" of his scientific evolution.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="132">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Toutefois ce changement de lieu de travail, qui conduisit à l’étude de composés organiques, rejoint aussi l’ «hypothèse universelle».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, this change of workplace, which led to the study of organic compounds, is also consistent with the "universal hypothesis."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="133">
            <prop type="paragraph">43</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il n’y a pas lieu d’opposer ces possibilités; au contraire, il y avait pour Pasteur une sorte de double évidence à évoluer vers les études des fermentations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>There is no need to oppose these possibilities; on the contrary, there was for Pasteur a sort of double logic to evolving towards research on fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="134">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce qui est certain, c’est que peu après le début des cours de l’année universitaire 1856–1857, à l’automne, le père d’un des étudiants, M. Bigo, fabriquant d’alcool à partir de jus de betteraves, soumit à Pasteur des difficultés de production: l’alcool obtenu à partir des betteraves était acide, de mauvaise qualité, et les cuves de fermentation avaient une odeur «fétide»[43].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>What is certain is that shortly after the beginning of the courses of the 1856–1857 academic year, in the autumn, the father of one of the students, M. Bigo, who made alcohol from beet juice, presented to Pasteur his production difficulties: the alcohol obtained from the beets was acidic, of poor quality, and the fermentation vats had a "foul" smell [43].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="135">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur accepta d’étudier le problème, et se trouva directement confronté à la question des fermentations[26, 51, 56].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur agreed to study the problem, and found himself directly confronted with the question of fermentation[26, 51, 56].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="136">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des indications factuelles de cet épisode figurent dans ses cahiers de laboratoire: on y trouve le nom de Bigo et le nom de la rue où se trouvait l’usine de ce dernier (à savoir la rue d’Esquermes, et non d’Esquermay comme cela a été écrit)[26, 50].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Factual indications of this episode can be found in his laboratory notebooks: the name of Bigo and the name of the street where Bigo's factory was located (namely, rue d'Esquermes, and not d'Esquermay as has been written)[26, 50].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="137">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En outre, on sait que, en décembre 1856, Marie Pasteur, l’épouse de Pasteur, écrivit à son beau-père: «Louis continue à travailler avec ardeur.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, it is known that in December 1856, Marie Pasteur, Pasteur's wife, wrote to her father-in-law: "Louis continues to work hard.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="138">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il est plongé maintenant dans le jus de betterave jusqu’au cou.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He is now immersed in beet juice up to his neck.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="139">
            <prop type="paragraph">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il passe ses journées dans une fabrique d’alcool»[57].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He spends his days in an alcohol factory" [57].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="140">
            <prop type="paragraph">45</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur identifia l’acide lactique comme un des produits qui nuisaient à la qualité des préparations de Bigo, et c’est ainsi qu’il fut conduit aux études de la fermentation lactique, ce dont il fit des parties de son cours[51]: le 2 février 1857, les trois premières lignes sont «Suite de l’étude de la fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur identified lactic acid as one of the products that adversely affected the quality of Bigo's mixtures. This is how he was led to research lactic fermentation, which he made part of his course[51]: on February 2, 1857, the first three lines are "Continuation of the study of fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="141">
            <prop type="paragraph">45</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le phénomène nous est connu dans ses conditions principales.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The phenomenon is known to us in its main conditions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="142">
            <prop type="paragraph">45</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Son importance exige plus de détails»[26].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Its importance demands more detail"[26].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="143">
            <prop type="paragraph">45</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est là non plus une hypothèse «amylique» ni «universelle», mais une hypothèse «lactique», qui n’est que secondairement «lilloise».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is no longer an "amyl" or "universal" hypothesis, but a "lactic" hypothesis, which is only secondarily a "Lille" hypothesis.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="144">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce qui est certain, aussi, c’est que c’est de cette époque lilloise (1855–1857) que datent deux articles sur l’alcool amylique[14].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>What is also certain is that it is from this Lille period (1855–1857) that two articles on amyl alcohol are dated [14].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="145">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le premier, déjà évoqué[30], est un petit résumé des travaux présentés à l’Académie des sciences en 1855: Pasteur y décrit la composition et la purification d’échantillons commerciaux d’ «alcool amylique», indiquant dans le résumé que l’alcool amylique commercial est un mélange de deux isomères très semblables, voire indiscernables chimiquement ou physiquement.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The first, already mentioned[30], is a short summary of the research presented to the Académie des Sciences in 1855: Pasteur describes the composition and purification of commercial samples of "amyl alcohol", indicating in the summary that commercial amyl alcohol is a mixture of two very similar isomers, perhaps even chemically or physically indistinguishable.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="146">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>À la fin de son article, Pasteur écrit que son intérêt pour ces composés est né de considérations cristallographiques: les deux alcools sont liquides dans les conditions ordinaires, mais il avait préparé une série de dérivés qui cristallisaient et trouvé que les dérivés de l’alcool optiquement actif violaient ses lois[28, 57, 58].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>At the end of his article, Pasteur wrote that his interest in these compounds arose from crystallographic considerations: the two alcohols are liquid under ordinary conditions, but he had prepared a series of derivatives that crystallised and found that the optically active alcohol derivatives violated his laws[28, 57, 58].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="147">
            <prop type="paragraph">46</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Découvrant une réfutation des théories qu’il avait lui-même proposées, Pasteur a dû être ébranlé, et il n’est pas certain que, avec les résultats expérimentaux dont il disposait alors, il ait pu imaginer comment il pouvait réconcilier des faits contradictoires.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Discovering a refutation of the theories that he himself had proposed, Pasteur had to have been shaken. It is not certain that, with the experimental results available to him at the time, he could imagine how he could reconcile contradictory facts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="148">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce qui n’est guère évoqué par les historiens qui se sont intéressés à la fermentation dans l’œuvre de Pasteur[26, 50], c’est que Pasteur s’intéressa aussi au lactose, cette même année 1856[58] : «Lorsque Kirchhoff, membre de l’Académie de Saint-Pétersbourg, eut publié la découverte si remarquable de la transformation de l’amidon en matière sucrée, Vogel essaya l’expérience de Kirchhoff sur le sucre de lait.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>What is hardly evoked by historians who were interested in the work in fermentation of Pasteur[26, 50] is that Pasteur was also interested in lactose, in that same year of 1856[58]: "When Kirchhoff, a member of the St. Petersburg Academy, had published the remarkable discovery of the transformation of starch into sweet matter, Vogel tried Kirchhoff's experiment on milk sugar.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="149">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il fit bouillir 100 grammes de sucre de lait avec 400 grammes d’eau et 2 grammes d’acide sulfurique, pendant quelques heures, en ajoutant de temps en temps un peu d’eau pour remplacer celle qui s’évaporait par l’ébullition.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He boiled 100 grams of milk sugar with 400 grams of water and 2 grams of sulfuric acid for a few hours, adding a little water occasionally to replace the water that evaporated by boiling.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="150">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La liqueur, saturée par la craie, évaporée à l’étuve, donna un sirop brun, épais, qui se prit en masse cristalline au bout de quelques jours».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The liquor, saturated by the chalk, evaporated in an oven, giving a thick brown syrup, which became crystalline after a few days."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="151">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Et il ajoute : «Cette matière, analogue à la cassonade, a une saveur bien plus sucrée que n’est une dissolution aqueuse la plus concentrée de sucre de lait.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He adds : "This material, analogous to brown sugar, has a much sweeter flavour than is a highly concentrated aqueous solution of milk sugar.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="152">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce goût excessivement sucré a fait soupçonner qu’il s’était formé du véritable sucre, propre à donner naissance à la fermentation alcoolique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This excessively sweet taste led to the suspicion that real sugar had formed, giving rise to alcoholic fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="153">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, à peine avait-on introduit ce produit, sous des circonstances favorables, avec la levure de bière, que la fermentation alcoolique s’est établie de la manière la plus vive, tandis que le sucre de lait ne fermente jamais.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This product had hardly been introduced, under favourable circumstances, with brewer's yeast, so that alcoholic fermentation was established in the strongest way, while milk sugar never ferments.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="154">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Tel est le sucre qui, avec de grandes apparences de raison sans doute a été pris pour du sucre de fécule ; et, à toutes les époques, les idées physiologiques émises sur le sucre de lait ont eu pour base la prétendue transformation de ce sucre en sucre de fécule.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] Such is the sugar which, with great reason, no doubt was taken for starch sugar; and, at all times, the physiological ideas expressed on milk sugar were based on the purported transformation of this sugar into starch sugar.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="155">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Mais, en réalité, le sucre de lait modifié par les acides est tout autre que le glucose.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>But, in reality, acid-modified milk sugar is quite different from glucose.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="156">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Je propose de le nommer lactose.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>I propose to call it lactose.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="157">
            <prop type="paragraph">47</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On réserverait le nom de sucre de lait ou de lactine pour le sucre cristallisable du lait. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The name milk sugar or lactin would be reserved for the crystallisable sugar of milk."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="158">
            <prop type="paragraph">48</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ici, la confusion du lactose avec le galactose ne doit pas conduire à ne pas repérer qu’apparaissent à nouveau des questions de fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Here, the confusion of lactose with galactose must not lead to the failure to detect that fermentation issues were again appearing.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="159">
            <prop type="paragraph">49</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cela précède le second mémoire, consacré aux alcools amyliques, où Pasteur examine la question cristallographique ainsi posée, et où il écrit ne pas parvenir à induire l’hémiédrie cristalline.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This preceded the second thesis, devoted to amyl alcohols, where Pasteur examined the crystallographic question thus posed, and where he writes to have not succeeded in inducing crystalline hemihedria.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="160">
            <prop type="paragraph">49</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il conclut que l’hémiédrie cristalline n’est pas une manifestation nécessaire de la «dissymétrie moléculaire»[30, 59].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He concludes that crystalline hemihedria is not a necessary manifestation of "molecular asymmetry"[30, 59].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="161">
            <prop type="paragraph">49</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Notons pour terminer que ce dernier article évoque «l’arrangement atomique des molécules», ce qui nous donne une indication supplémentaire pour analyser les conceptions structurales de Pasteur à cette époque.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Let us note in conclusion that this last article evokes "the atomic arrangement of molecules," which gives us an additional indication to analyse Pasteur's structural conceptions at this time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="162">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En 1857 et 1858, Pasteur s’explique sur la question des fermentations, nouveau champ qu’il substitue partiellement au premier[60, 61, 62] : «Je crois devoir indiquer en quelques mots comment j’ai été conduit à m’occuper de recherches sur les fermentations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In 1857 and 1858, Pasteur explained himself on the question of fermentation, a new field with which he partially replaced the first[60, 61, 62]: "I think I must indicate in a few words how I was led to concern myself with fermentation research. […]</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="163">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] On s’étonnera peut-être de me voir aborder un sujet de chimie physiologique bien éloigné en apparence de mes premiers travaux.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Perhaps it is surprising to see me approaching a physiological chemistry subject that is apparently far removed from my initial works.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="164">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il s’y rattache néanmoins très directement.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, it relates very directly to it.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="165">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans l’une de mes dernières communications à l’Académie, j’ai établi que l’alcool amylique, contrairement à ce que l’on avait cru jusqu’alors, était une matière complexe formée de deux alcools distincts, isomères, l’un déviant à gauche le plan de polarisation, l’autre dépourvu de toute action.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In one of my last communications to the Academy, I established that amyl alcohol, contrary to what had been thought until then, was a complex matter formed by two distinct isomeric alcohols, one deviating the plane of polarisation to the left, the other devoid of any action.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="166">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Je résolus dès lors de faire une étude approfondie des deux alcools amyliques, de déterminer, s’il était possible, les causes de leur production simultanée et leur véritable origine, sur laquelle certaines idées préconçues me portaient à partager l’opinion commune.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] I therefore resolved to carry out an in-depth study of the two amyl alcohols, to determine, if possible, the causes of their simultaneous production and their true origin, on which certain preconceptions led me to share the common opinion.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="167">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Si [l’alcool amylique], lorsqu’il est actif, avait le sucre pour origine, comme tous les chimistes l’admettent, son action optique serait empruntée à celle du sucre.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] If [amyl alcohol], when active, originated from sugar, as all chemists admit, its optical action would be borrowed from that of sugar.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="168">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est ce que je répugne à croire dans l’état actuel de nos connaissances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is what I am reluctant to believe in the current state of our knowledge.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="169">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Le groupe moléculaire de l’alcool amylique est trop distant de celui du sucre pour que, s’il en dérive, il en retienne une dissymétrie d’arrangement de ses atomes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] The molecular group of amyl alcohol is too distant from that of sugar, if it derives from it, for it to retain an asymmetry in the arrangement of its atoms.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="170">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Je le répète, ce sont là des idées préconçues.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Again, these are preconceived ideas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="171">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elles suffisaient cependant pour me déterminer à étudier quelle pouvait être l’influence du ferment dans la production des deux alcools amyliques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, they were sufficient for me to decide to study what influence the ferment might have on the production of the two amyl alcohols.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="172">
            <prop type="paragraph">50</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Car on voit toujours ces alcools prendre naissance dans l’opération de la fermentation, et c’était là une invitation de plus à persévérer dans la solution de ces questions. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These alcohols are always seen to originate in the process of fermentation; this was another invitation to persevere in finding the solution to these questions."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="173">
            <prop type="paragraph">51</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il ajoute également: «J’ai été conduit à m’occuper de la fermentation à la suite de mes recherches sur les propriétés des alcools amyliques et sur les particularités cristallographiques fort remarquables de leurs dérivés.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He also adds: "I was led to attend to fermentation following my research on the properties of amyl alcohols and on the very remarkable crystallographic peculiarities of their derivatives.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="174">
            <prop type="paragraph">51</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…]Je me propose d’établir dans la première partie de ce travail que, de même qu’il existe un ferment alcoolique, la levure de bière, que l’on trouve partout où il y a du sucre qui se dédouble [un mot important pour l’histoire de l’atomisme, puisque c’est le même que celui qui était utilisé pour la séparation des acides tartriques du racémique, mais qui a ici un sens différent, en langage moderne] en alcool et en acide carbonique, de même il y a un ferment particulier, une levure lactique toujours présente quand du sucre devient acide lactique, et que, si toute matière plastique azotée peut transformer le sucre en cet acide, c’est qu’elle est pour le développement de ce ferment un aliment convenable.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] I propose to establish in the first part of this work that, just as there is alcoholic fermenting, brewer's yeast, which is found everywhere where there is sugar that splits [an important word for the history of atomism, since it is the same as that which was used for the separation of tartaric acids from racemic, but which has a different meaning in modern language] into alcohol and carbonic acid, so there is a particular ferment, a lactic yeast always present when sugar becomes lactic acid, and that, if any nitrogenous plastic can transform the sugar into this acid, it is because it is for the development of this ferment a suitable food. […]</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="175">
            <prop type="paragraph">51</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Voyons maintenant les caractères de cette substance dont la production est corrélative des phénomènes compris sous la dénomination de fermentation lactique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Let us now see the characteristics of this substance, the production of which is correlative with the phenomena included under the name of lactic fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="176">
            <prop type="paragraph">51</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Au microscope, elle est formée de petits globules ou de petits articles très-courts, isolés ou en amas, constituant des flocons irréguliers».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] Under the microscope, it is comprised of small globules or very short segments, isolated or in clusters, constituting irregular flakes."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="177">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On ne discutera pas ici de la controverse sur la nature des fermentations, et le rôle des micro-organismes ou de ferments inanimés, mais on soulignera que, dans ce débat scientifique, Pasteur fondait ses points de vue sur son hypothèse «universelle» du vivant, comme l’indique la suite du texte: «Tels ont été pour moi l’occasion et le motif d’expériences nouvelles sur les fermentations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We will not discuss here the controversy about the nature of fermentation and the role of microorganisms or inanimate ferments, but we will emphasise that, in this scientific debate, Pasteur based his views on his "universal" hypothesis of life, as indicated in the rest of the text: "These were for me the opportunity and the reason for new experiments on fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="178">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Mais, comme il arrive souvent en pareille circonstance, mon travail s’est agrandi peu à peu et a dévié de sa première direction; de telle sorte que les résultats que je publie aujourd’hui paraissent étrangers à mes études antérieures.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>But, as often happens in such circumstances, my work has gradually expanded and deviated from its first direction; so that the results that I publish today seem foreign to my previous studies.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="179">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La liaison se montrera plus évidente dans ceux qui suivront.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The connection will be more evident in those that follow.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="180">
            <prop type="paragraph">52</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>J’espère pouvoir ultérieurement mettre en rapport les phénomènes de la fermentation et le caractère de dissymétrie moléculaire propre aux substances organiques».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>I hope to be able to relate the phenomena of fermentation to the molecular asymmetry inherent in organic substances."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="181">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Autrement dit, il y a une continuité entre ses expériences sur les cristaux et ses études des levures, et le fil conducteur est la dissymétrie[60].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In other words, there is a continuity between his experiments on crystals and his research on yeasts; the common thread is asymmetry[60].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="182">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>D’ailleurs, au lieu d’adopter une interprétation historique qui risquerait d’être fausse parce qu’excessivement tranchée, comment ne pas rappeler prudemment[63] que les textes où Pasteur évoque la «dissymétrie moléculaire» se sont progressivement éloignés des comptes rendus expérimentaux et pour devenir des mises en ordre de travaux?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, instead of adopting a historical interpretation that might be wrong because it is concluded with excessive certainty, how can we not cautiously recall [63] that the texts in which Pasteur evokes "molecular asymmetry" had gradually moved away from experimental reports to become structured research works?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="183">
            <prop type="paragraph">53</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cela a conduit Geison à des positions tranchées, quand il a détecté des différences entre notes, cahiers et publications de Pasteur[50].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This led Geison to distinct views, when he detected differences between Pasteur's notes, notebooks, and publications [50].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="184">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En tout cas, Pasteur commence par obtenir l’acide tartrique gauche à partir du racémique, preuve que ses préoccupations de chiralité ne sont —évidemment— pas éloignées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In any case, Pasteur began by obtaining the left-handed tartaric acid from the racemic, proof that his concerns of chirality were—clearly— not far removed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="185">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Puis, en 1858[64], il montre que l’acide succinique est «un produit normal, nécessaire, de la fermentation alcoolique»[65] : «Après quelques jours de fermentation, le liquide primitivement inactif [du racémique] possède un pouvoir rotatoire à gauche sensible, et ce pouvoir augmente progressivement à mesure que la fermentation se continue, de manière à atteindre un maximum.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, in 1858[64], he showed that succinic acid is "a normal, necessary product of alcoholic fermentation"[65]: "After a few days of fermentation, the initially inactive [racemic] liquid has a substantial rotatory power to the left, and this capability gradually increases as the fermentation continues, reaching a maximum.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="186">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Lafermentation est alors suspendue, Il n’y a plus trace d’acide droit dans la liqueur, qui, évaporée et mêlée à son volume d’alcool, donne immédiatement une abondante cristallisation de tartrate gauche d’ammoniaque.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Thefermentation is then suspended. There is no trace of right-handed acid in the liquor, which, evaporated and mixed with its volume of alcohol, immediately gives an abundant crystallisation of left-handed ammonia tartrate.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="187">
            <prop type="paragraph">54</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Voilà sans doute un excellent moyen de préparer l’acide tartrique gauche».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is undoubtedly an excellent way to prepare left-handed tartaric acid."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="188">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La lecture des mémoires de cette époque révèle que ce sont les capacités de chimiste de Pasteur qui permettent ses études innovantes des fermentations: Pasteur part, certes, d’études de la fermentation de l’acide lactique (lait aigri), parce que les travaux sur ce thème sont rares, contrairement à ceux de la fermentation alcoolique et qu’aucune levure lactique n’a été découverte, mais il faut souligner que l’acide lactique est un sous-produit de l’alcool amylique optiquement actif.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Reading the memoirs of this time reveals that it was Pasteur's abilities as a chemist that allowed for his innovative research on fermentation: Pasteur moved away, certainly, from researching fermentation of lactic acid (sour milk), because research on this theme is rare, unlike that of alcoholic fermentation, and because no lactic yeast had been discovered. It should be emphasised, however, that lactic acid is a by-product of optically active amyl alcohol.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="189">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Et son hypothèse sur la chiralité de la vie continue de le mouvoir: «Si l’on venait à me dire que, dans ces conclusions, je vais au-delà des faits, je répondrais que cela est vrai, en ce sens que je me place franchement dans un ordre d’idées qui […] ne peuvent être irrémédiablement démontrées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>And his hypothesis on the chirality of life continues to move him: "If I were to be told that, in these conclusions, I go beyond the facts, I would answer that this is true, in the sense that I place myself frankly in a way which […] cannot be definitively demonstrated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="190">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Il m’est avis, au point où je me trouve de mes connaissances sur le sujet, que quiconque jugera avec impartialité les résultats de ce travail et ceux que je publierai prochainement reconnaîtra avec moi que la fermentation s’y montre corrélative de la vie, de l’organisation de globules, non de la mort ou de la putréfaction de ces globules, pas plus qu’elle n’y apparaît comme un phénomène de contact, où la transformation du sucre s’accomplirait en présence du ferment sans rien lui donner, sans rien lui prendre. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] It is my opinion, according to my current knowledge of the subject, that anyone who will judge with impartiality the results of this work and those which I will publish shortly will recognise along with me that fermentation shows itself to be correlative of life, of the organisation of globules, not of the death or putrefaction of these globules, nor does it appear as a phenomenon of contact, where the transformation of sugar would be carried out in the presence of the ferment without giving it anything, without taking anything from it."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="191">
            <prop type="paragraph">55</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ici, on observera qu’il y avait des considérations sur le vivant, dans les études des activités optiques, et des considérations sur le vivant avec la fermentation: c’est un pont qui doit manifestement retenir l’attention, pour comprendre la transition de la cristallographie à la biochimie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Here, it will be observed that there were considerations for living entities in the research on optical activities, and considerations for the living with fermentation: this is the link that clearly needs to be noted in order to understand the transition from crystallography to biochemistry.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="192">
            <prop type="paragraph">56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur est alors lancé dans les études de la fermentation, maintenant la fermentation alcoolique, qu’il aurait initialement évitée tant elle avait été préalablement étudiée[66] : «Je vous prie de vouloir bien annoncer à l’Académie un résultat curieux et très-inattendu.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur was then launched into researching fermentation, now called alcoholic fermentation, which he would have initially avoided as it had been studied previously: [66] "I beg you to be kind enough to announce to the Academy a curious and very unexpected result.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="193">
            <prop type="paragraph">56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est la présence constante de la glycérine parmi les produits de la fermentation alcoolique».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It is the constant presence of glycerin among the products of alcoholic fermentation."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="194">
            <prop type="paragraph">56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il découvre d’abord[67] qu’il n’y a pas d’acide lactique dans la fermentation alcoolique;</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He first discovered [67] that there was no lactic acid in alcoholic fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="195">
            <prop type="paragraph">56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>puis il s’attaque nommément à Justus von Liebig, en faisant observer que, contrairement à ce que dernier avait publié, il n’y a pas d’ammoniac dans la fermentation alcoolique[68].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, he attacked Justus von Liebig by name, noting that, contrary to what the latter had published, there was no ammonia in alcoholic fermentation [68].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="196">
            <prop type="paragraph">57</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>5. Après 1860</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>5. After 1860</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="197">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En 1860, Pasteur est lancé dans les expériences sur les causes de la fermentation[69, 70] quand il fait ses leçons à la Société chimique de Paris (aujourd’hui la Société chimique de France)[71]: il y insiste sur les questions de chiralité en relation avec les fermentations, comme dans les fermentations des acides tartriques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In 1860, Pasteur was launched into experiments on the causes of fermentation[69, 70] when he lectured at the Société Chimique de Paris (Chemical Society of Paris), now the Société Chimique de France (Chemical Society of France)[71]: there he insisted on the issues of chirality related to fermentation, such as in the fermentation of tartaric acids.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="198">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il ne mentionne l’ «alcool amylique» que pour dire qu’il avait découvert un tel alcool inactif, ce qui est le départ d’une série de composés.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He mentions "amyl alcohol" only to say that he discovered such an inactive alcohol, which is the beginning of a series of compounds.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="199">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous proposons de voir, dans cette insistance sur la fermentation des acides tartriques, et pas sur l’alcool amylique, moins une volonté de reconstruire l’histoire qu’une manifestation d’un intérêt scientifique nouveau.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this emphasis on the fermentation of tartaric acids, and not on amyl alcohol, we propose to see less a desire to reconstruct history, but rather a manifestation of a new scientific interest.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="200">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>D’ailleurs, dans une conférence qu’il fit à la Société centrale de médecine vétérinaire en 1880[70], alors qu’il retraçait l’évolution de sa carrière, Pasteur ne dit rien de l’ «alcool amylique» et il indique clairement que c’est l’observation du métabolisme énantiosélectif des acides tartriques par des micro-organismes qui l’avait dirigé vers les fermentations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, in a lecture he gave to the Central Society of Veterinary Medicine in 1880[70], while tracing the evolution of his career, Pasteur said nothing about "amyl alcohol" and he clearly indicated that it was the observation of the enantioselective metabolism of tartaric acids by microorganisms that had directed him towards fermentation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="201">
            <prop type="paragraph">58</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette observation est intéressante, car elle montre le choix de Pasteur, parmi des causes multiples.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This observation is interesting because it highlights Pascal's personal choice out of multiple causes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="202">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Parallèlement à l’exploration de la transition vers l’étude des fermentations, nous avons suivi jusqu’ici l’évolution du sens qu’avaient, pour Pasteur, les mots «atomes» et «molécules», mais qu’en pensait-il en 1860 ?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Alongside the exploration of the transition to the study of fermentation, we have so far followed the evolution of Pasteur's meaning of the words "atoms" and "molecules." However, what did he think of these in 1860?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="203">
            <prop type="paragraph">59</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Considérons trois extraits [71]:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Consider three extracts[71]:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="204">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>1. «Rappelez-vous la définition de l’espèce chimique que j’indiquais tout à l’heure : c’est la collection de tous les individus identiques par la nature, la proportion et l’arrangement des éléments.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>1. "Remember the definition of the chemical species that I mentioned earlier: it is the collection of all individual entities that are identical in nature, the proportion and the arrangement of elements.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="205">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Dans les corps isomères, la nature et la proportion sont les mêmes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] In isomeric entities, their nature and proportion are the same.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="206">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’arrangement seul diffère.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The arrangement alone differs.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="207">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le grand intérêt de l’isomérie a été d’introduire dans la science ce principe que les corps peuvent être et sont essentiellement différents par cela seul que l’arrangement des atomes n’est pas le même dans leurs molécules chimiques. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The great interest of isomerism has been to introduce into science this principle that the entities can be and are essentially different by this alone that the arrangement of atoms is not the same in their chemical molecules."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="208">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>2. «Les atomes de l’acide [tartrique] droit sont-ils groupés suivant les spires d’une hélice dextrorsum, ou placés aux sommets d’un tétraèdre irrégulier, ou disposés suivant tel ou tel assemblage dissymétrique déterminé ?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>2. "Are the atoms of the right-handed [tartaric] acid grouped according to the turns of a dextrorotatory helix, or placed at the vertices of an irregular tetrahedron, or arranged according to a given asymmetric assembly?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="209">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous ne saurions répondre à ces questions.»</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We cannot answer these questions."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="210">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>3. «Permettez-moi de représenter grossièrement, quoique au fond avec justesse, la structure du quartz et celles des produits organiques naturels.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>3. "Allow me to represent roughly, albeit fundamentally with accuracy, the structure of quartz and that of natural organic products.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="211">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Imaginez un escalier tournant dont les marches seraient des cubes, ou tout autre objet à image superposable.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Imagine a rotating staircase with steps made of cubes, or any other object with a superposable mirror image.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="212">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Détruisez l’escalier, et la dissymétrie aura disparu.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Destroy the stairs, and the asymmetry will be gone.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="213">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La dissymétrie de l’escalier n’était que le résultat du mode d’assemblage de ses marches élémentaires.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The asymmetry of the staircase was only the result of the method of assembling its elementary steps.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="214">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Tel est le quartz.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Such is the case with quartz.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="215">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>[…] Imaginez, au contraire, le même escalier tournant formé de tétraèdres irréguliers pour marches.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>[…] Imagine, on the contrary, that the same rotating staircase is formed of steps made from irregular tetrahedra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="216">
            <prop type="paragraph">60</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Détruisez l’escalier, et la dissymétrie existera encore. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Destroy the stairs, and the asymmetry will still exist."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="217">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les deux leçons datent du 20 janvier et du 3 février, tandis que le congrès de Karlsruhe eut lieu du 3 au 5 septembre:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The two lessons date from 20 January and 3 February, while the Karlsruhe Congress took place from 3 to 5 September:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="218">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pasteur, n’ayant pas exploré la question particulière des théories atomiques, n’avait pas de raison de changer de point de vue.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur, having not explored the specific question of atomic theories, had no reason to change his point of view.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="219">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>D’ailleurs, ses termes restent mal fixés en 1863[43]: «Or les groupements atomiques qui composent les molécules de toutes les espèces chimiques sont des objets et des assemblages que nous trouvons autour de nous.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, its terms remain poorly fixed in 1863[43]: "Now the atomic groups that make up the molecules of all chemical species are objects and assemblies that we find around us.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="220">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A priori, donc, on peut croire qu’eux également doivent se partager en nos deux catégories : les groupements d’atomes qui ont un plan de symétrie et une image qui leur est superposable, et les groupements d’atomes qui n’ont pas de plan de symétrie et une image qui ne leur est pas superposable.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A priori, therefore, we can believe that they too must be divided into our two categories: groups of atoms that have a plane of symmetry and a mirror image that is superposable on itself, and groups of atoms that do not have a plane of symmetry and a mirror image that is not superposable on itself.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="221">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En d’autres termes, il doit y avoir des groupes d’atomes symétriques et d’autres dissymétriques, c’est-à-dire des groupes droits et gauches, des groupes inverses les uns des autres.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In other words, there must be groups of symmetrical atoms and other asymmetrical ones, that is to say right-handed and left-handed groups, groups that are the inverse of each other.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="222">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ceux-ci, nous les connaissons : c’est, par exemple, le groupe tartrique droit et le groupe tartrique gauche.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These are, for example, the right-handed tartaric group and the left-handed tartaric group.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="223">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il existe une foule de groupes d’atomes dissymétriques qui attendent encore la production artificielle ou naturelle de leurs inverses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>There are a host of groups of asymmetric atoms that are still awaiting the artificial or natural production of their inverses.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="224">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous avons le sucre droit : nous ignorons l’existence du sucre gauche.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We have the right-handed sugar; we do not know the existence of the left-handed sugar.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="225">
            <prop type="paragraph">61</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous avons l’albumine gauche, nous ignorons l’albumine droite. »</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We have the left-handed albumin; we are not aware of the right-handed albumin."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="226">
            <prop type="paragraph">62</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ici Pasteur parle de «groupements d’atomes» ou de «groupes d’atomes», et non plus de «molécules», et il n’est pas clair de savoir quelle relation il fait entre entités.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Here Pasteur speaks of "groupings of atoms" or "groups of atoms", and no longer of "molecules"; it is not clear what relationship he makes between entities.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="227">
            <prop type="paragraph">62</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En 1874, dans une lettre adressée à Michel Eugène Chevreul (1786–1889), Pasteur évoque une «définition de l’espèce» (chimique)[72], mais les analyses présentées dans[1] indiquent que, même dans les années 1910, les idées restaient mal fixées à ce propos.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In 1874, in a letter addressed to Michel Eugène Chevreul (1786–1889), Pasteur evoked a "definition of the (chemical) species"[72]. However, the analyses presented in[1] indicate that, even in the 1910s, ideas remained unclear on this subject.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="228">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En tout cas, les idées initiales sur la «dissymétrie moléculaire» ne l’ont pas quitté, après son changement de champ de recherche, et elles motivent que, en 1871, soit 15 ans après avoir arrêté ses travaux sur la chiralité, il ait encore pu croire à une base universelle de la chiralité, et repris des expériences pour l’établir[73].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In any case, his initial ideas on "molecular asymmetry" did not leave him after his change of field of research, and they imply that in 1871, that is to say 15 years after having stopped his research on chirality, he still believed in a universal basis of chirality, and resumed experiments to establish it [73].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="229">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il soutint cette idée en 1875: «Transformer un corps inactif en un autre corps inactif, qui a la faculté de se résoudre simultanément en un corps droit et son symétrique, n’est en rien comparable à la possibilité de transformation d’un corps inactif en un corps actif simple.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He supported this idea in 1875: "To transform an inactive entity into another inactive entity, which has the ability to simultaneously resolve itself into a right-handed entity and its symmetrical partner, is in no way comparable to the possibility of transforming an inactive entity into a simple active entity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="230">
            <prop type="paragraph">63</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est là ce qu’on n’a jamais fait ; c’est là, au contraire, ce que la nature vivante fait sans cesse sous nos yeux»[74].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We have never done this; on the contrary, living nature does it constantly before our eyes" [74].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="231">
            <prop type="paragraph">64</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En 1883, Pasteur continue de promouvoir son idée « universelle», physique, de l’origine de la chiralité[75]: «Que faut-il faire pour imiter la nature ?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In 1883, Pasteur continued to promote his "universal" idea of the physical origin of chirality: [75] "What must be done to imitate nature?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="232">
            <prop type="paragraph">64</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il faut rompre avec vos méthodes, qui sont, à ce point de vue, surannées et impuissantes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We must break with your methods, which are, from this point of view, outdated and powerless.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="233">
            <prop type="paragraph">64</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il faut chercher à faire agir des forces dissymétriques, recourir à des actions de solénoïde, de magnétique, de mouvement dissymétrique lumineux, à des actions de substances elles-mêmes dissymétriques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It is necessary to seek to make asymmetrical forces act, to resort to actions that are solenoid, magnetic, to luminous asymmetrical movement, to actions of substances that are themselves asymmetrical.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="234">
            <prop type="paragraph">64</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Lorsque, entraîné, enchaîné devrais-je dire, par une logique presque inflexible de mes études, j’ai passé des recherches de cristallographie et de chimie moléculaire à l’étude des ferments, j’étais tout entier à la pensée d’introduire la dissymétrique dans les phénomènes chimiques.»</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>When, pulled along, chained I should say, by the almost inflexible logic of my studies, I passed from the research of crystallography and molecular chemistry to the study of ferments, I was entirely thinking of introducing asymmetry into chemical phenomena."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="235">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ou encore : « Ces expériences accusent la ligne de démarcation profonde entre le règne minéral et le règne organique, puisque pour imiter ce que fait la nature, c’est-à-dire préparer un corps droit ou un corps gauche, nous sommes contraints de faire intervenir des actions toutes particulières, des actions de dissymétrie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Or again: "These experiments accentuate the deep dividing line between the mineral kingdom and the organic kingdom, since in order to imitate what nature does, that is to say to prepare a right-handed or a left-handed body, we are forced to involve very particular actions, actions of asymmetry.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="236">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La ligne de démarcation dont nous parlons n’est pas une question de chimie pure et d’obtention de produits tels ou tels, c’est une question de forces ; la vie est dominée par des actions dissymétriques dont nous pressentons l’existence enveloppante et cosmique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The dividing line we are talking about is not a question of pure chemistry and the production of such and such products; it is a question of forces: life is dominated by asymmetrical actions whose enveloping and cosmic existence we sense.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="237">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Je pressens même que toutes les espèces vivantes sont primordialement, dans leur structure, dans leurs formes extérieures, des fonctions de la dissymétrie cosmique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>I even feel that all living species are primarily, in their structure, in their external forms, functions of cosmic asymmetry.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="238">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La vie, c’est le germe et le germe, c’est la vie.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Life is the seed and the seed is life.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="239">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Or qui pourrait dire ce que seraient les devenir des germes, si l’on pouvait remplacer dans ces germes les principes immédiats, albumine, cellulose, etc., etc., par leurs principes dissymétriques inverses ?</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Now, who could say what the fate of these "seeds" would be, if we could replace in these seeds the immediate constituents, albumin, cellulose, etc., etc., with their inverse asymmetric constituents?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="240">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La solution consisterait d’une part, dans la découverte de la génération spontanée […] oui, il y a une séparation profonde entre le règne organique et le règne minéral.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The solution would consist, on the one hand, in the discovery of spontaneous generation […] yes, there is a deep separation between the organic kingdom and the mineral kingdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="241">
            <prop type="paragraph">65</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette ligne de démarcation a deux expressions : d’une part on n’a jamais fait un produit de synthèse, minéral ou organique […] d’autre part, la dissymétrie préside aux actions chimiques qui donnent lieu aux principes immédiats essentiels de la vie végétale».</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This dividing has two manifestations: on the one hand, we have never made a synthetic product, mineral or organic […] on the other hand, asymmetry presides over chemical actions that give rise to the immediate essential constituents of plant life."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="242">
            <prop type="paragraph">66</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les tentatives de Pasteur de produire de la chiralité moléculaire par l’action de forces physiques n’aboutirent pas[51, 73].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Pasteur's attempts to produce molecular chirality via physical forces did not succeed[51, 73].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="243">
            <prop type="paragraph">66</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pourtant il n’abandonna pas sa croyance dans le rôle de telles forces universelles dans la genèse de la chiralité moléculaire, et, même plus tard, il entreprit des expériences pour produire des composés optiquement actifs en utilisant des champs magnétiques, mais aucun facteur biologique[73].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Nevertheless, he did not abandon his belief in the role of such universal forces in the genesis of molecular chirality, and even later he conducted experiments to produce optically active compounds using magnetic fields, but no biological factors [73].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="244">
            <prop type="paragraph">66</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Entre-temps, les études des fermentations l’avaient conduit à l’étude des micro-organismes, et à toutes les réalisations pour lesquelles il est justement célèbre: fermentation acétique, maladie du ver à soie, maladie du charbon, rage, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the meantime, fermentation research had led him to study microorganisms, and to all the achievements for which he is rightly famous: acetic fermentation, silkworm disease, anthrax, rabies, etc.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="245">
            <prop type="paragraph">67</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Finalement l’examen des textes réunis ici montre comment des hypothèses fausses, fondées sur des théories insuffisantes, ont pu permettre à un scientifique remarquablement actif de progresser, d’accumuler des données expérimentales, qui, longtemps après qu’il s’était réorienté, ont été éclairées par des travaux d’autres scientifiques: les tétraèdres de Joseph Achille Le Bel (1947–1930) et de Jacobus Henricus Van’t Hoff (1852–1911) n’avaient rien à voir avec ceux de Pasteur, mais ils donnèrent la possibilité de comprendre la «dissymétrie moléculaire», et de faire advenir les idées de «chiralité»[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the end, examination of the texts gathered here shows how false hypotheses based on insufficient theories could allow a remarkably active scientist to progress, to accumulate experimental data, which, long after he had reoriented himself, were enlightened by the works of other scientists: the tetrahedrons of Joseph Achille Le Bel (1947-1930) and Jacobus Henricus Van 't Hoff (1852–1911) had nothing to do with those of Pasteur, but they allowed for the opportunity to understand "molecular asymmetry", and to advance the ideas of "chirality"[1].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="246">
            <prop type="paragraph">67</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En quelque sorte, Pasteur se justifie par anticipation à cet égard quand il réunit, en 1878, d’anciens travaux sur la «dissymétrie moléculaire» pour les publier sous le titre : «Études de chimie moléculaire ou recherches sur la dissymétrie dans les produits organiques naturels» (le livre ne fut pas achevé)[75].</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In a way, Pasteur justified himself in anticipation in this regard when, in 1878, he brought together earlier works on "molecular asymmetry" to publish them under the title: "Etudes de chimie moléculaire ou recherches sur la dissymétrie dans les produits organiques naturelles" ["Studies of molecular chemistry or research on asymmetry in natural organic products"] (the book was not completed)[75].</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="247">
            <prop type="paragraph">67</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il y écrit: « Mais, comme le dit quelque part Lavoisier, c’est le sort de tous ceux qui travaillent d’apercevoir un nouveau pas à faire sitôt qu’ils en ont fait un premier, et ils ne donneraient jamais rien au public, s’ils attendaient qu’ils eussent atteint le bout de la carrière qui se présente successivement à eux et qui paraît s’étendre à mesure qu’ils avancent pour la parcourir.»</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>He wrote: "But, as Lavoisier says somewhere, it is the fate of all those who work to see a new step that they should take as soon as they have taken the first one, and they would never give anything to the public if they waited until they had reached the end of the career which appears to them sequentially and which seems to be expanding as they progress."</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="248">
            <prop type="paragraph">67</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>C’est bien ce qu’il a fait.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This is indeed what he did.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="249">
            <prop type="paragraph">68</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Conflit d’intérêt</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Conflicts of Interest</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="250">
            <prop type="paragraph">69</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’auteur n’a aucun conflit d’intérêt à déclarer.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The author has no conflict of interest to declare.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>