<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for TAL-2006-47_2_ID=TAL-2006-47-2-06-Ferret. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2006-47_2_ID=TAL-2006-47-2-06-Ferret</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La segmentation thématique de documents a fait l’objet d’un nombre important de travaux dont il n’est pas toujours facile de dégager des conclusions claires, en particulier en ce qui concerne l’utilisation de connaissances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Topic segmentation was addressed by a large amount of work from which it is not easy to draw conclusions, especially about the need for knowledge.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans cet article, nous proposons d’examiner deux voies se situant dans le même cadre pour améliorer une méthode de segmentation fondée sur la simple récurrence lexicale.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this article, we propose in the same framework two methods for improving the results of a topic segmenter based on lexical reiteration.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces thèmes sont ensuite utilisés pour faciliter l’identification des similarités thématiques entre unités de discours.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These topics are then used to facilitate the detection of topical similarity between discourse units.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La seconde réalise le même but en faisant appel à une ressource externe, en l’occurrence un réseau de cooccurrences lexicales construit à partir d’un large corpus.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The second approach achieves the same goal by relying on an external resource, that is a network of lexical co-occurrences built from a large corpus.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces deux approches sont également combinées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These two approaches are also combined.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une évaluation de ces deux approches et de leur combinaison est réalisée dans un même cadre et illustre l’intérêt de cette combinaison.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>An evaluation of these approaches and their combination is performed in a reference framework and shows the interest of this combination.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>