<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2013ENMP0063. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2013ENMP0063</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Entailment vise à capturer les principaux besoins d'inférence sémantique dans les applications de Traitement du Langage Naturel.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Textual Entailment aims at capturing major semantic inference needs across applications in Natural Language Processing.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Depuis 2005, dans la Textual Entailment reconnaissance tâche (RTE), les systèmes sont appelés à juger automatiquement si le sens d'une portion de texte, le texte - T, implique le sens d'un autre texte, l'hypothèse - H</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Since 2005, in the Textual Entailment recognition (RTE) task, systems are asked to automatically judge whether the meaning of a portion of text, the Text - T, entails the meaning of another text, the Hypothesis - H.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse nous nous intéressons au cas particulier de l'implication, l'implication de généralité.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This thesis we focus a particular case of entailment, entailment by generality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour nous, il y a différents types d'implication, nous introduisons le paradigme de l'implication textuelle en généralité, qui peut être définie comme l'implication d'une peine spécifique pour une phrase plus générale, dans ce contexte, le texte T implication Hypothèse H, car H est plus générale que T.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For us, there are various types of implication, we introduce the paradigm of Textual Entailment by Generality, which can be defined as the entailment from a specific sentence towards a more general sentence, in this context, the Text T entailment Hypothesis H, because H is more general than T.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous proposons des méthodes sans surveillance indépendante de la langue de reconnaissance de l'implication textuelle par la généralité, pour cela, nous présentons une mesure asymétrique informatif appelée Asymmetric simplifié InfoSimba, que nous combinons avec différentes mesures d'association asymétriques à reconnaître le cas spécifique de l'implication textuelle par la généralité.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We propose methods unsupervised language-independent for Recognizing Textual Entailment by Generality, for this we present an Informative Asymmetric Measure called the Simplified Asymmetric InfoSimba, which we combine with different asymmetric association measures to recognizingthe specific case of Textual Entailment by Generality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse, nous introduisons un nouveau concept d'implication, les implications de généralité, en conséquence, le nouveau concept d'implications de la reconnaissance par la généralité, une nouvelle orientation de la recherche en Traitement du Langage Naturel.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This thesis, we introduce the new concept of implication, implications by generality, in consequence, the new concept of recognition implications by generality, a new direction of research in Natural Language Processing.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>