<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2018USPCA156. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2018USPCA156</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Notre recherche doctorale, qui s’inscrit dans le champ de l’acquisition d’une troisième langue et du plurilinguisme, a pour objectif d’apporter une meilleure compréhension du fonctionnement de la compétence plurilingue.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This research is set within the fields of third language acquisition and multilingualism with a focus on developing our understanding of how multilingual competence functions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle cherche plus particulièrement à déterminer si les langues d’un plurilingue jouent des rôles distincts dans l’acquisition d’une nouvelle langue au niveau des interactions translinguistiques lexicales et syntaxiques et si ces phénomènes sont associés.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The research attempts to determine if the languages of a multilingual play distinctive roles in the acquisition of a new language specifically regarding the lexical and syntactic components in crosslinguistic interactions, and whether there is convergence between these phenomena.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elle examine également les activités métalinguistiques et translinguistiques permettant aux apprenants de gérer et d’appréhender la langue cible.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The research also examines the metalinguistic and crosslinguistic activities which allow learners to manage and comprehend the target language.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour ce faire, nous avons réalisé onze études de cas de locuteurs de l’espagnol et de l’anglais avec des niveaux variés en français L3+.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The data for this research was collected from eleven case studies of speakers of Spanish and English with a variety of levels of proficiency in French.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces participants ont été soumis à trois tâches de production orale.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Participants were required to complete three speaking tasks.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Afin prendre en compte la nature complexe des interactions lorsque les langues en contact sont typologiquement proches et lorsque différents domaines linguistiques sont examinés, nous avons adopté une approche mêlant travaux menés dans le champ de l’acquisition d’une L3 à ceux menés dans l’étude des contacts de langues.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Approaches sourced from research from the fields of third language acquisition and language contact were utilised and developed to capture the complexity of the interactions, the typological relationship among the languages in contact, and the varying levels of the languages under examination.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Par le biais d’une analyse quantitative et qualitative, notre travail a mis en évidence le fonctionnement de la compétence plurilingue de nos participants.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Using quantitative and qualitative analysis this research demonstrates how multilingual competence operates.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ils activent en effet toutes leurs langues à des degrés divers, au niveau de différents types d’ITL, propriétés syntaxiques et domaines linguistiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The data indicates that participants activate all their languages to different degrees relating to different types of crosslinguistic interactions, syntactic properties and level of language.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nos participants mobilisent, par ailleurs, leur conscience métalinguistique et translinguistique afin de mieux appréhender la LC et gérer leur production en recourant à des cognats, à des consultations translinguistiques et à des inférences.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Participants also typically resort to their metalinguistic and crosslinguistic awareness to help them comprehend the target language and manage their output by the use of cognates, crosslinguistic consultations and inferences.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>