<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2015AVIG1149. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2015AVIG1149</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse propose d’examiner les façons dont l’expérience de visite peut être transformée dans le contexte d’une culture numérique qui touche les publics réels et les publics potentiels du musée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the context of a digital culture that affects the actual audiences and potential audiences of the museum, this thesis proposes to examine the ways in which the visitor’s experience can be transformed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>On s’interroge plus précisément sur les processus d’appropriation et de partage qu’entraine la pratique muséale à l’époque de la culture numérique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We wonder specifically about the appropriation and sharing processes that induce the museum practice in the era of digital culture.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour explorer cet objet de recherche, nous construisons un appareil méthodologique interdisciplinaire</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To explore this research item, we build an interdisciplinary methodological device between IT and Communication Sciences.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il permet d’élaborer un cadre analytique susceptible de saisir des pratiques qui se partagent et se combinent entre un espace numérique et un espace physique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It helps us to develop an analytical framework able to capture practices that are divided and combined between cyberspace and physical space.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De la sorte, nous proposons des protocoles de recherches hybrides et exploratoires qui offrent la possibilité de saisir, par leur association, des pratiques multiples de l’expérience de visite dans la triple temporalité de l’avant, du pendant et de l’après visite du musée.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this way, we propose hybrid and exploratory research protocols that provide the ability to capture, through their association, multiple practices of the visitor’s experience in a triple temporality of the before, the during and the after visit of the museum.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>À travers cette thèse nous mettons en évidence la façon dont le numérique intervient dans les pratiques de l’expérience de visite comme un objet technique spécifique et un système d’échange avec et dans lequel le visiteur et le visiteur potentiel reconfigurent leur relation à l’institution muséale, à sa collection, aux expositions et aux autres visiteurs et visiteurs potentiels.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Through this thesis, we highlight how digital devices and culture play a part in the practices of the visitor’s experience as a specific technical object and an exchange system and in which the visitor and potential visitor reconfigure their relationship to museum, its collection, exhibitions and other visitors and potential visitors.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>