<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2017SACLC078. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2017SACLC078</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet,afin de rester compétitives, les entreprises concevant des systèmes cherchent à leur rajouter de plus en plusde fonctionnalités.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Systems are becoming more and more complex, because to stay competitive, companies whichdesign systems search to add more and more functionalities to them.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette compétitivité introduit aussi une demande de réactivité lors de la conception desystèmes, pour que le système puisse évoluer lors de sa conception et suivre les demandes du marché.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Additionally, this competition impliesthat the design of systems needs to be reactive, so that the system is able to evolve during its conception andfollow the needs of the market.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>De plus, la langue naturelle est difficile à traiter automatiquement, par exemple, onpeut difficilement déterminer avec un programme informatique que deux exigences en langue naturelle secontredisent.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Additionally, natural language is hard to process automatically: for example, it is hard to determine, usingonly a computer program, that two natural language requirements contradict each other.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, la langue naturelle reste indispensable dans les spécifications que nous étudions,car elle reste un moyen de communication pratique et très répandu.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, naturallanguage is currently unavoidable in the specifications we studied, because it remains very practical, and itis the most common way to communicate.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous cherchons à compléter ces exigences en langue naturelle avec des éléments permettant à la fois de lesrendre moins ambiguës et de faciliter les traitements automatiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We aim to complete these natural language requirements with elements which allow to make them lessambiguous and facilitate automatic processing.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces éléments peuvent faire partie demodèles (d’architecture par exemple) et permettent de définir le lexique et la syntaxe utilisés dans lesexigences.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These elements can be parts of models (architectural modelsfor example) and allow to define the vocabulary and the syntax of the requirements.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous avons testé les principes proposés sur des spécifications industrielles réelles et développéun prototype logiciel permettant de réaliser des tests sur une spécification dotée de ces éléments de syntaxeet de lexique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We experimented theproposed principles on real industrial specifications and we developped a software prototype allowing totest a specification enhanced with these vocabulary and syntax elements.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>