<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2017MONTS021. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2017MONTS021</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le Web d’aujourd’hui est formé, entre autres, de deux types de contenus que sont les données structurées et liées du Web sémantique et les contributions subjectives des utilisateurs du Web social.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Nowadays, the Web is formed by two types of content which are linked: structured data of the so-called Semantic Web and users’ contributions of the Social Web.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’approche ViewpointS a été conçue comme un formalisme creuset apte à intégrer ces deux types de contenus, en préservant la subjectivité des interactions du Web Social.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The ViewpointS approach was de-signed as an integrative formalism capable of mixing these two types of content while preserving the subjectivity of the interactions of the Social Web.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>ViewpointS est une approche de représentation subjective des connaissances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>ViewpointS is a subjective knowledge repre-sention approach.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’approche propose aussi un second degré de subjectivité.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The approach also provides a second level of subjectivity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, viewpoints peuvent être interprétés différemment selon l’utilisateur grâce au mécanisme de perspective.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Indeed, the viewpoints can be interpreted differently according to the user through the perspective mechanism.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les ressources du Web sont représentées et liées par les viewpoints dans le Graphe de Connaissances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In our frame-work, resources from the Web are tied by viewpoints in a Knowledge Graph.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>A partir du Graphe de Connaissances contenant les viewpoints et les ressources du Web une Carte de Connaissances composée de synapses et de ressources est créée qui est le fruit de l’interprétation et de l’agrégation des viewpoints.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>From the Knowledge Graph containing viewpoints and Web resources a Knowledge Map consisting of “synapses” and re-sources is created as a result of the interpretation and aggregation of viewpoints.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Chaque viewpoint contribue à la création, au renforcement ou à l’affaiblissement d’une synapse qui relie deux ressources.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The evolution of the ViewpointS synapses may be considered analog to the ones in the brain in the very simple sense that each viewpoint contributes to the establishment, strengthening or weakening of a syn-apse that connects two resources.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L’échange de viewpoints est le processus de sélection qui permet l’évolution des synapses d’une manière analogue à celles qui évoluent dans le cerveau au fil d’un sélectionnisme neuronal.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The exchange of viewpoints is the selection process ruling the synapses evolution like the selectionist process within the brain.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous investiguons dans cette étude l’impact que peut avoir la représentation subjective des connaissances dans divers scénarii de construction collective des connaissances.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We investigate in this study the potential impact of our subjective representation of knowledge in various fields: information search, recommendation, multilingual ontology alignment and methods for calculating semantic distances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>