<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for TAL-2000-41_3_ID=2000-41_3-4. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2000-41_3_ID=2000-41_3-4</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans cet article, nous passons en revue les principales difficultés que posent les noms propres aux applications de traitement de la parole.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In this paper, we review some of the problems related to the processing of proper names in the context of speech processing applications.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Deux applications sont plus particulièrement étudiées, à savoir la reconnaissance de la parole grand vocabulaire et la synthèse de la parole.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Two specific applications are focused on, automatic speech recognition (ASR) and text-to-speech synthesis (TTS).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour ces deux applications, nous montrons que la prise en compte des noms propres par les modules de traitement linguistique (modèles syntaxiques pour la reconnaissance, système de conversion graphème-phonème pour la synthèse) implique l'analyse de larges corpus de textes et le développement de volumineux dictionnaires de noms propres.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>For both applications, we discuss the extend to which the various linguisitic modules involved (language modelling for ASR, grapheme-to-phoneme conversion for TTS) can benefit from the analysis of large corpora, and from the development of large lexica of proper names.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les méthodes pratiques pour construire de telles ressources sont présentées et discutées.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Practical methods for the development of such resources are presented and discussed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>