<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2009PA112164. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2009PA112164</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse se penche sur l'analyse et les contraintes d'élaboration des composants permettant aux systèmes de répondre à des questions en domaine ouvert.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This thesis bends over the analysis and the constraints of elaboration of components for open domain questions answering systems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les systèmes de questions réponses (SQR) sont adaptés à cette tâche, car ils associent une question factuelle à une réponse précise.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The questions answering systems (QAs) is adapted to this task, because they associate a factual question with a precise answer.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il est proposé d'adapter les SQR à une tâche d'interaction afin de leur définir un cadre d'adaptation générique aux systèmes de dialogue.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It is suggested adapting the QAs to a task of interaction to define to them a frame of generic adaptation to the systems of dialogue.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sont étudiés, les techniques existantes pour les SQR en domaine ouvert, les différents modèles de dialogue homme-machine ainsi que des systèmes à la limite entre le dialogue et la recherche d'informations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The existing techniques for the QAs in opened domain, the various models of man-machine dialog as well as systems in the limit between the dialogue and the search for information are studied.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ensuite, est présenté la construction d'un modèle de structure permettant de décrire les interactions entre des questions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Then, is presented the construction of a model of structure allowing to describe the interactions between questions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Du cadre formel, est déduis une méthode de calcul qui est évalué.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Of the formal frame, is deduct a method of calculation which is estimated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Afin de discuter cette évaluation et de voir comment utiliser notre modèle, il est réalisé une analyse des moteurs de recherche pour les systèmes de questions réponses.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To discuss this evaluation and see how using our model, is realized the analysis of search engines for the systems of questions answers.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans une dernière partie, il est présenté une utilisation des données calculées pour l'amélioration des résultats de réponses aux questions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In a last part, is presented a use of the data calculated for the improvement of the results of answers to the questions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>