<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2012LORR0038. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2012LORR0038</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>L'enjeu de cette thèse est l'acquisition automatique de nouveaux sens lexicaux.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The issue at stake is the automated meaning allocation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous définissons un modèle théorique sur l'émergence d'un nouveau sens pour une unité lexicale ayant déjà un sens codé.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In a first time, a theoretical scheme is elaborated to describe meaning change for a lexical unit already defined in a lexical resource.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Nous la modélisons à partir d'indices quantitatifs articulés à des principes issus de la sémantique textuelle.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Our model relies on quantitative evidence and it is inspired from text semantics.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le sens codé est représentécomme un ensemble structuré de traits sémantiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The preexisting meaning is represented as a structured set of semantic features.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il est modulé en discours sous l'effet de récurrences d'autres traits.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The context modifies it dueto salient semantic featuresin texts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La dynamique du sens est représentée à l'aide de descripteurs de granularité sémantique variable.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These dynamic change is comprehended through description strata ranging from coarse-grained to fine-grained semantic units.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ensuite, nous proposons des ressources et outils adaptés, relevant de la linguistique de corpus.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In a second time, we dwell on relevant resources and tools from corpus linguistics.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En pratique, le Trésor de la Langue Française informatisé fournit les sens codés.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Concretely, we use the Trésor de la Langue Française informatisé as a dictionary.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une plateforme transforme ses définitions en ensembles de traits sémantiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Its entries are automatically converted into bags of semantic features.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Trois corpus journalistiques des années 2000 servent de ressources textuelles.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The textual dataconsists in three recent journalistic corpus.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les outils mathématiques, essentiellementstatistiques, permettent de jouer sur la structure des ressources, d'extraire des unités saillantes et d'organiser l'information.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The resources are considered are mathematic spaces and statistical tools are used to extract significant units and to structure information.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Enfin, nous établissons les grandes lignes d'une procédure pour allouer de façon semi-automatique un nouveau sens.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In a last time, we give an outline of a process to allocate automatically a new meaning.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Elles sont étayées par des expériences illustratives.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Experiments illustrate each step.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="14">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Il s'appuie sur des jeux de contrastes multiples, permettant de nuancer l'informationsémantique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Through this approach, it is possible to qualify the new meaning in a precise and structured way.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>