<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2010CNAM0721. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2010CNAM0721</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Leur qualité joue par conséquent un rôle déterminant dans le succès du système final.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Conceptual models (CM) serve as the blueprints of information systems and their quality plays decisive role in the success of the end system.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Des études ont montré que la majeure partie des changements que subit un SI concerne des manques ou des défaillances liés aux fonctionnalités attendues.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>It has been witnessed that majority of the IS change-requests result due to deficient functionalities in the information systems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sachant que la définition de ses fonctionnalités incombe à la phase de l’analyse et conception dont les MC constituent les livrables, il apparaît indispensable pour une méthode de conception de veiller à la qualité des MC qu’elle produit.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Therefore, a good analysis and design method should ensure that CM are correct and complete, as they are the communicating mediator between the users and the development team.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Notre approche vise les problèmes liés à la qualité de la modélisation conceptuelle en proposant une solution intégrée au processus de développement qui à l’avantage d’être complète puisqu’elle adresse à la fois la mesure de la qualité ainsi que son amélioration.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Our approach targets the problems related to conceptual modeling quality by proposing a comprehensive solution.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La proposition couvre les aspects suivants:</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>We designed multiple artifacts for different aspects of CM quality.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>En effet, un des manques constaté dans le domaine de la qualité des MC est l’absence de consensus sur les concepts et leurs définitions.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Most of the existing literature on CM quality evaluation represents disparate and autonomous quality frameworks proposing non-converging solutions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Un pattern de qualité sert à aider un concepteur de SI dans l’identification des critères de qualité applicables à sa spécification, puis de le guider progressivement dans la mesure de la qualité ainsi que dans son amélioration.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>ii. Formulation of quality patterns to encapsulate past-experiences and good practices as the selection of relevant quality criteria (including quality attributes and metrics) with respect to a particular requirement (or goal) remains trickier for a non-expert user.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Sachant que la plupart des approches existantes s’intéresse à la mesure de la qualité et néglige les moyens de la corriger.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These quality patterns encapsulate valuable knowledge in the form of established and better solutions to resolve quality problems in CM.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>iii. Formulation d’une méthode orientée qualité incluant à la fois des concepts, des guides et des techniques permettant de définir les concepts de qualité souhaités, leur mesure et l’amélioration de la qualité des MC.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>iii. Designing of the guided quality driven process encompassing methods and techniques to evaluate and improve the conceptual models with respect to a specific user requirement or goal.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>iv. Développement d'un prototype "CM-Quality".</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>iv. Development of a software prototype “CM-Quality”.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>