<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2017USPCA143. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2017USPCA143</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce travail a pour objet l’adaptation des toponymes thaïlandais en français dans un corpus de quatre guides touristiques francophones.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The present research examined the problems in adapting Thai toponyms or place names in a corpus of four French guidebooks on Thailand.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les analyses linguistiques et traductologiques montrent que les toponymes thaïlandais sont bien intégrés en français aux différents niveaux de leur adaptation.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The linguistic and translation analysis showed that Thai toponyms were well integrated in French at different levels.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ils sont d’abord romanisés par divers systèmes, parfois avec la francisation graphématique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Firstly, they were romanised by various systems including using French graphemes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Au niveau sémantico-référentiel, leur valeur fondamentale est locative mais dans certains contextes, ils peuvent subir une interprétation métonymique et métaphorique.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>In the referential semantic perspective, their fundamental value is locative, but in some contexts they could be metonymically amd metaphorically interpreted.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ainsi le transfert sémantique est possible par les divers procédés traductologiques.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Moreover, despite the problem of meaning and non-translation of the proper names, the semantic transfer of Thai toponyms into French was possible by using various translation procedures.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Avec la traduction libre, l’auteur peut modifier la traduction de la dénomination d’origine ou créer une nouvelle forme dénominative en présentant la caractérisation dominante du référent.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The author could modify the literal translation of Thai toponyms or create a new one to better present the dominant characterisation of the place with free translation technique.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces stratégies soulignent une fonction pragmatique spécifique du guide touristique : permettre au lecteur d’identifier des lieux qui lui sont inconnus en suscitant son intérêt pour une langue-culture étrangère.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These strategies revealed the pragmatic nature of the guidebooks which is to make the reader discover or know the unknown place and arouse the reader’s interest.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>