<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2020LORR0168. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2020LORR0168</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le but du Registre National du Cancer (RNC) du Luxembourg est de collecter des données sur le cancer et la qualité des traitements au Luxembourg.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The aim of the National Cancer Registry (NCR) in Luxembourg is to collect data about cancer and the quality of cancer treatment.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Afin d’obtenir des données de haute qualité et comparables avec celles d’autres registres ou pays, le RNC suit les règles et standards internationaux de codification comme la Classification International des Maladies pour l’Oncologie (COM-O).</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To obtain high quality data that can be compared with other registries or countries, the NCR follows international coding standards and rules, such as the International Classification of Diseases for Oncology (ICD-O).</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ces standards sont complexes et considérables, compliquant fortement le processus de collecte des données.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>These standards are extensive and complex, which complicates the data collection process.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les encodeurs en charge de la collecte des données sont souvent confrontés à des situations dans lesquelles des données sont manquantes ou contradictoires, les empêchant d’appliquer les règles fournies.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The operators, i.e. the people in charge of this process, are often confronted with situations where data is missing or contradictory, preventing the application of the provided guidelines.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Pour les aider dans leur tâche, les exports de codification du RNC répondent aux questions de codage des encodeurs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To assist in their effort, the coding experts of the NCR answer coding questions asked by operators.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cependant, ces réponses requièrent beaucoup de temps des experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This assistance.is time consuming for experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le but de ce projet est de réduire le temps d’expert nécessaire et de faciliter le travail des encodeurs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>To help reduce this burden on experts and to facilitate the operators’ task, this project aims at implementing a coding assistant that would answer coding questions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>D’un point de vue scientifique, cette thèse s’intéresse au problème de synthèse d’informations à partir d’un ensemble de données provenant de différentes sources avec des contraintes et recommandations à respecter.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>From a scientific point of view, this thesis tackles the problem of extracting the information from a set of data sources under a given set of rules and guidelines.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Le raisonnement à partir de cas est utilisé pour résoudre ce problème car cette méthodologie ressemble à cette employée par les experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Case-based reasoning has been chosen as the method for solving this problem given its similarity with the reasoning process of the coding experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>La méthode de résolution conçue utilise des arguments fournis par les experts de codification dans le cadre de questions posées précédemment par les encodeurs.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The method designed to solve this problem relies on arguments provided by coding experts in the context of previously solved problems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Ce document décrit comment ces arguments servent à identifier des questions similaires et à expliquer la réponse aux encodeurs et aux experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This document presents how these arguments are used to identify similar problems and to explain the computed solution to both operators and coding experts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Une évaluation préliminaire a été réalisée pour évaluer la performance de la méthode et identifier des pistes d’améliorations.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>A preliminary evaluation has assessed the designed method and has highlighted key areas to improve.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Dans un premier temps, le travail produit porte sur les registres du cancers et la codification médicale, cependant l’approche est généralisable à d’autres domaines.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>While this work focused on cancer registries and medical coding, this method could be generalized to other domains.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>