<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx version="1.4b">
    <header creationtool="xml.etree.ElementTree" creationtoolversion="1.3.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="FR" o-tmf="XML" creationdate="2023-04-28" creationid="MaTOS">
        <note>This is the sentence alignement file for THE-theses.fr-2018TOUR4022. segId begin by 1, tuid = segId</note>
        <docid>2018TOUR4022</docid>
        <elem type="sourceLanguage">FR</elem>
        <elem type="targetLanguage">EN</elem>
    </header>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Cette thèse se situe à l’intersection de deux domaines de recherche scientifique la Reconnaissance d’</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>This thesis is focused on Graph Matching (GM) problems and in particular the Graph Edit Distance (GED) problems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Alors que le second se focalise sur la résolution de problèmes d’</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>However, these problems are known to be complex and hard to solve, as the GED is a NP-hard problem.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Parmi les problèmes difficiles existants en ROS, le problème de la distance d’édition entre graphes (DEG) a été sélectionné comme le cœur de ce travail.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>Operations Research (OR) field offers a wide range of exact and heuristic algorithms that have accomplished very good results when solving optimization problems.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Les contributions portent sur la conception de méthodes adoptées du domaine RO pour la résolution du problème de DEG.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>So, basically all the contributions presented in thesis are methods inspired from OR field.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <tuv xml:lang="FR">
                <seg>Explicitement, des nouveaux modèles linéaires en nombre entiers et des matheuristiques ont été développé à cet effet et de très bons résultats ont été obtenus par rapport à des approches existantes.</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="EN">
                <seg>The proposed heuristic approaches are adapted versions of existing MILP-based heuristics (also known as matheuristics), by considering problem-dependent information to improve their performances and accuracy.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>